<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The history of monastical conventions and military institutions, with a survey of the court of Rome, or, A description of the religious and military orders in Europe, Asia and Africa for above twelve hundred years being a brief account of their institution, confirmation, rules, habits, and manner of living ... together with a survey of the court of Rome &amp;c. in all the great offices and officers ecclesiastical and civil dependant thereon ... with many other things worthy of note according to what has been recorded by candid authors of diverse nations ... / faithfully collected by J.S.</title>
            <author>J. S.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1686</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 247 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 108 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62155</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S66</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R29342</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11076927</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11076927</idno>
            <idno type="VID">46268</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A62155)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 46268)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1431:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The history of monastical conventions and military institutions, with a survey of the court of Rome, or, A description of the religious and military orders in Europe, Asia and Africa for above twelve hundred years being a brief account of their institution, confirmation, rules, habits, and manner of living ... together with a survey of the court of Rome &amp;c. in all the great offices and officers ecclesiastical and civil dependant thereon ... with many other things worthy of note according to what has been recorded by candid authors of diverse nations ... / faithfully collected by J.S.</title>
                  <author>J. S.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[11], 197 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for H. Rhodes,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1686.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Licensed May 11, 1686."</note>
                  <note>Contains engraved frontispiece.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Monasticism and religious orders.</term>
               <term>Military religious orders.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:46268:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:46268:1"/>
            <p>THE HISTORY OF <hi>Monaſtical Conventions,</hi> AND Military Inſtitutions With a SURVEY of the COURT of <hi>ROME.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>OR, A Deſcription of the Religious and Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Orders in <hi>Europe, Aſia</hi> and <hi>Africa,</hi> for above twelve hundred years, being a brief Account of of their Inſtitution, Confirmation, Rules, Habits, and manner of Living; the Qualification of their Inſtitutors, and the time of their reſpective Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions, extending to either Sex, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Together with a Survey of the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> &amp;c. in all the Great Offices, and Officers Eccleſiaſtical and Civil dependant thereon; as alſo the Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of the Conſiſtories, Conclave and thoſe that have been uſed in the Creation of Cardinals; Election of the High-Biſhop or Pope, and his Triumphant Coronation Proceſſion, and that of his taking Poſſeſſion of the <hi>Lateran</hi> Church in <hi>Rome;</hi> with what is obſerved in his Sickneſs, and the manner of Solemnizing his Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Obſequies; with many other things wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of Note, according to what has been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded by Candid Authors of divers Nations, and faithfully Collected</p>
            <p>By <hi>J. S.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LICENSED <hi>May</hi> 11. 1686.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>H. Rhodes</hi> next door to the <hi>Swan-Tavern</hi> near <hi>Bride-Lane</hi> in <hi>Fleet-ſtreet.</hi> 1686.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:46268:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>A proſpect of a monaſtical Life and Pilgramage</head>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <head>Jeruſalem taken by the Chriſtians Anno 1099</head>
                  <q>In hoc vincis</q>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <head>The Pontifical prosceſſion to the Eateran Church</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:46268:2"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:46268:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:46268:3"/>
            <head>THE EPISTLE TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>REader, in the following Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe you will find the Cauſe and Original of a Monaſtick Life, referring to either Sex, <hi>viz.</hi> as well of Nuns as Eremites, Monks and Friers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of divers Orders and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions, with the Motives that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced their Founders to ſuch Pious and Charitable <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndertakings, and the Time of their Inſtitution; the account of their Progreſs, Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Increaſe and Decay for upwards of <hi>1200</hi> years: Alſo the Rules and
<pb facs="tcp:46268:4"/>Habits preſcribed to the ſeveral Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and the Regulation of the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſteries and Covents, as they are warranted by Authors, the truth of whoſe Teſtimony has not been reduced under the leaſt ſcruple or imagination of Falſity or Partiality; in taking a Survey of which, you will not only find what Progreſs Religion made in the World, ſince its marvellous light removed the ſhadows of Ignorance and Atheiſm; but many other remarkable things, affording much variety. To theſe Orders, properly termed Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous becauſe devoted to Religious Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and the propagation of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion; I have added others, <hi>viz.</hi> Military Orders of Knighthood, which have been, and are at preſent in the Chriſtian World, with the Time of their Inſtitution, the Countries they were erected in, their Habit, Badges, Collars, And the names of thoſe Kings, Princes, and Noble-man, who erected them moſtly for the defence of the Christian Cauſe; as well in the
<pb facs="tcp:46268:4"/>Holy land, as in <hi>Europe</hi> and <hi>Afri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca;</hi> non were they, when the Infidels, like a deluge, ſought to carry all before them, a little ſerviceable, as appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Valour and Conduct of ſome of them againſt the Sultans of <hi>Egypt</hi> in <hi>Paleſtine;</hi> and others by Eclipſing the Turkiſh Moons with blood at the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Sieges of <hi>Rhodes, Candia,</hi> &amp;c. To theſe I have added a Survey of the Court and City of <hi>Rome,</hi> in all its great Offices, Places of Honour and Eminency, from the Pontifical Chair, to the Inferior Officers, Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical and Civil; with the Conſistorial Order and Proceedings in the Conclave Election of a Pope to fill the empty Throne, and what is Obſervable and Remarkable on that occaſion, and in the ſplendid Proceſſion to the <hi>Lateran</hi> Church; the manner of Benediction, Creation of Cardinals, and many other things very Remarkable; in which is deſcribed the Magnificence and Splen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor of that great Court and City, as it has been faithfully delivered, and
<pb facs="tcp:46268:5"/>what may be very much ſerviceable to Readers, or Writers of Hiſtory, or other matters that any way concern the affairs of either, or border on things of this nature. And thus much I thought fit briefly to lay down, as well for the Pleaſure and Inſtruction of the Curious, as to prevent Mistakes or Miſconstructions in the Ignorant, who generally are abuſed by Miſrepre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentations: And hoping this Candid <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndertaking may pleaſe ſome, and give offence to none, Reader, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main yours to oblige you in what I may,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>J. S.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="introduction">
            <pb facs="tcp:46268:5"/>
            <head>The Introduction, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IN the dawn of the Goſpel, when as St. <hi>John</hi> obſerves in his <hi>Apocalypſe, The woman had given her the wings of an Eagle to fly into the Wilderneſs, from the the face of the Dragon, who caſt out a flood of water to carry her away:</hi> When the Primitive Chriſtians, to avoid the perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions ſtirred up againſt them by the Prince of Darkneſs, in the Reigns of the Heathen Emperors, fled into Mountains, Woods, Caves, and ſolitary Places, there to injoy (though in the greateſt exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Poverty) that Religion in the free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of its exerciſe, which they valued infinitely beyond tlie Pomp and Glory of the Univerſe, as knowing their bleſſed <hi>Redeemer lived,</hi> and that he would not fail to Crown their Labour in the end <hi>with Life and Immortality,</hi> with a <hi>Crown of Glory that will never fade:</hi> Then it was, that many Devout Chriſtians, being wonderfully taken with ſuch Solitude, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together
<pb facs="tcp:46268:6"/>weaned themſelves from the world, and deſpiſing its vanities, choſe to live and dye in the privacy of their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirements; for the ſupport of whom, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or rather the more immediate hand of Providence, by unexpected ways, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced the food whereby they did ſubſiſt; and theſe from the Deſarts and obſcure Places, where they choſe to reſide, as alſo their ſingleneſs of Life, were called <hi>Eremites,</hi> or <hi>Monachies,</hi> held by the Church in high eſteem for their Piety and Devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and of theſe in the Primitive Times <hi>Paul, Hillarian, Baſil,</hi> and <hi>Hierom</hi> were note-worthy, who lived in that Eſtate, and were imitated by others, no leſs de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout than themſelves: But when the Church had Peace, eſpecially under the happy Reign of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great, and many of thoſe Emperors that ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded him in the <hi>Eaſtern</hi> and <hi>Weſtern</hi> Empires; thoſe that were ſcattered in ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary places, that they might be at hand to proclaim the Goſpel-Truths to thoſe, who as then <hi>ſat in darkneſs,</hi> or but dim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beheld its <hi>marvellous Light,</hi> choſe to change their Hutts and Caves for conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient places in populous Towns and Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, where they lived together in a poor, but contented Eſtate; having all things
<pb facs="tcp:46268:6"/>in common amongſt themſelves; and from thence the places in which they choſe to reſide, were called Monaſteries, Convents or Cloiſters. Nor was it long, e're by their good example, in a devout way of living, the number was increaſed; nor were there wanting devout Women, who, as we may properly term it, left the world, that is, the enjoyment of worldly things, and voluntarily choſe to live in ſuch retirements; and from their recluſe manner of living and ſingleneſs of life, were called <hi>Nonnae</hi> or Nuns, or as ſome will have it from the <hi>Egyptian</hi> word <hi>Nonnus,</hi> and were further diſtinguiſhed by the name of <hi>Moniales,</hi> from whence the word Monaſtery ſeemeth to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived. Great indeed was their Devotion, inſomuch that increaſing in holy zeal, and a fervent deſire of heavenly things, they procured to themſelves the name of <hi>Sanctimoniales;</hi> and from theſe good beginings the ſeveral holy Orders ſprung, and were (as the Church in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed, and ſpread her ſilver Wings of Peace, to ſhadow her Children from the heat of perſecution) at divers times con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted and confirmed; of whoſe ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Riſes and Progreſſes I intend to ſpeak, that thoſe who are unacquainted there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with,
<pb facs="tcp:46268:7"/>may be fully ſatisfied, and Miſtakes or Miſrepreſentations rectified and avoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: That at one view much of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture paſt and preſent, may impartially be ſurveyed, without offending any by augmenting or extenuating. And ſo take them briefly in order, as they are war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranted on the credit of ſuch Authors, as have been curious in the ſearch and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry of thoſe things, and left them to our conſideration as undoubted Truths; as alſo what relates to the Offices and Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies of the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:46268:7"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 1.</hi> A Diſcourſe of divers Religious Orders, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted and Eſtabliſhed in the Primitive Times, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> at the <hi>Thabeneſii,</hi> the Monks of St. <hi>Baſil</hi> and St. <hi>Hierom,</hi> &amp;c. with the Rules preſcribed for their manner of Living, and ſtrictneſs of Life, their Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nents, management of Affairs, Habit, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>CHriſtianity prevailing, and in ſpite of Oppoſition, mounting like the victorious Palm under weight and oppreſſion; the Church that before was bleſſed with Internal Peace, found the like External Bleſſing, under that glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Chriſtian Emperor, <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great; and not only Peace, but Incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement, inſomuch that Piety and Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing began more and more to flouriſh, and a ſetled Method and Order in Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal matters to be regularly obſerved; which in the days of Perſecution, could not be brought to perfection, all the ſtrict Profeſſors being forced to live in Caves and Deſarts like Eremites, or fly
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:46268:8"/>from one place to another, to avoid the Sword or Flames: So that the firſt well ſetled Orders we read of, were called <hi>Thabenneſii,</hi> from the Iſle of <hi>Thabenna,</hi> in the Province of <hi>Thebais,</hi> the place of their Abode; and theſe were eſtabliſhed by one <hi>Pachomius</hi> an Eremite, who in the Reign of <hi>Conſtantius,</hi> Son to <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great, convened divers Religious Men, and giving them the Title or Stile of Monks, preſcribed the following Rules, <hi>viz.</hi> That they ſhould cohabit or live to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in one Houſe, in which Houſe were divers little Cells, every Cell allot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for three perſons; yet that they ſhould eat together in common, at a Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble placed in the Hall for that purpoſe, eating or abſtaining being otherwiſe left to their diſcretion. That they muſt take their repoſe in Chairs, and not in Beds; the Cloaths that were allotted them were made of Goat-skins, which they put not off, unleſs when they received the Bleſſed Sacrament: Hoods they like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe had, with which they covered their faces, and in their eating were injoyned ſilence, and to be intent upon what they were about: Prayers were likewiſe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joined them twelve times a day, as alſo in the Evening, and in the Night, a
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:46268:8"/>Pſalm going before each Prayer: Their Cells, or as ſome will have it, their Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders were twenty four; and in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner they lived up to the ſtrictneſs of their Profeſſion in honeſt Demeanor and Piety, which ſtirred up and incited others to imitate them. Nor was St. <hi>Baſil</hi> Presbyter of <hi>Caeſarea</hi> in <hi>Cappadocia</hi> ſlow in erecting, or cauſing to be erected, places for Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Worſhip, and giving Inſtructions to thoſe that had betaken themſelves to ſuch places: For being moleſted by <hi>Euſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bius</hi> his Biſhop, leſt they contending, any trouble might be raiſed to the Church, or occaſion of ſcandal given to the enemies of the Goſpel; he withdrew himſelf to a Monaſtery in <hi>Pontus,</hi> and ſent his invitation to ſuch as had choſen to dwell in Caves, or other the like Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirements, to leave thoſe Solitudes and come to him: When getting together a competent number, he preſcribed them Rules under ninety five Heads, and were by moſt of the <hi>Eaſtern</hi> Monks embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the which by reaſon they tend to Piety, and the ſettlement of a good Living, I think not amiſs to repeat.</p>
               <p>As firſt, They were enjoyned to love God with all their hearts, ſoul and ſtrength, and their Neighbour as them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:46268:9"/>2. To ground and fix the love of God upon his Glory, Power and Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency, as he is in himſelf, and on his Bounty, Goodneſs, and Mercy towards us. 3. That the love of our Neighbour be founded upon the Will and Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God, and on his Love towards us who were his enemies. 4. That they ſhould live together for the ſake of mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Help, Comfort, Inſtruction, Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of Virtue, Efficacy of Prayer, and ſecurity from danger. 5. That they ſhould renounce and forſake the Pleaſures and Vanities of the world. 6. That they ſhould diſpoſe of their wealth to the poor and needy. 7. That none, without trial, be admitted into their Fraternity. 8. That Children, with the conſent of their Parents, may be admitted. 9. That they ſhould endeavour to be temperate in all things, as well in Diet as Behaviour. 10. That meaſures be ſet down for their eating and drinking. 11. That none ſtrive for Superiority at the Table, or elſewhere. 12. That their Apparel be plane and decent, that they girded them with a girdle. 13. That they walk not af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their own Senſuality, but ſquare their Actions by the word of God. 14. That next to God they be obedient to their Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periors.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:46268:9"/>15. That they ſhould ſerve God with upright hearts, and all ferventneſs of affection. 16. That he who ſhould be their Governor, conſider he is God's Miniſter, and be careful and tender over his charge. 17. That at firſt he reprove the Offendors with meekneſs and gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; but if they prove obſtinate, and will not be reclaimed, then he is to account them as <hi>Heathens</hi> and <hi>Publicans,</hi> &amp;c. 18. That he ſuffer not the leaſt offence to paſs unreproved. 19. That Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance be ſincerely performed. 20. That it be accompanied with good works. 21. And with Confeſſion. 22. That if any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon relapſe, he muſt uſe more ſincerity in his Repentance than before. 23. Let him who reproves be as a Father, or a Phyſitian, and the reproved perſons, as Sons and Patients. 24. That no man be obſtinate, or ſeek to excuſe, or juſtifie himſelf in any evil courſe or undertaking. 25. That amongſt them all things be Common. 26. That men of Eſtates ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to their Kindred what is their due, and the remainder to the poor. 27. That none that are entred, return to their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents houſes, unleſs to give them Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and that to be done by the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of their Superiors. 28. Through
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:46268:10"/>which none muſt give way for their minds to wander after vanity. 29. That to avoid idle and ſinful Dreams, they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply themſelves to meditation on the Law and Word of God. 30. That with the ſame affection our bleſſed Saviour waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Diſciples feet, the ſtronger ought to aſſiſt the weak and infirm in ſickneſs, and on ſundry other occaſions. 31. That they ſhould love one another, as Chriſt loved us. 32. That their ſpeech be not vain or idle, but edifying and ſuitable on all occaſions. 33. That they ſhould by no means upbraid one another, or any other perſon. 34. That whoever de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fames, or patiently hears his Brother de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famed, be Excommunicated. 35. That they give not way to Malice or Anger. 36. That they ſet their affections on Heavenly and not on Earthly Things. 37. That they neither rejoice nor ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, but when they ſee God honoured or diſhonoured. 38. That they take heed and beware of worldly Cares, and too much Security. 39. That whatever they do, may be done to the glory of God. 40. That they beware of Pride. 41. That by having a low eſteem of themſelves, they may learn Humility. 42. That they may be obedient, and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:46268:10"/>to help and ſerve each other. 43. That no man give occaſion of ſcandal or offence to his Brother. 44. That every one do his duty with chearfulneſs, that reconciliation may be made where it is wanting. 45. That they judge not, leaſt they be judged. 46. That they be truly zealous againſt ſin. 47. That no man do his own will, or ought without leave, ſeeing Chriſt came to do the will of his Father. 48. That they be thankful to God, who has made them capable of partaking with the Saints in light. 49. That they in their duty inſtruct no Vices. 50. That they debar no man from entring their Convent upon trial, nor give them any offence. 51. That in their faſting, they uſe Moderation and Devotion. 52. That none ſcorn to wear a Garment that is given him, though old. 53. That every one obſerve the due hour for repaſt or eating. 54. That they give their Alms with due conſideration, but eſpecially according to the diſcretion of the Superior. 55. That the elder inſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the younger, perform it with reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, and that none preſume to break the Orders of the Monaſtery. 56. That they ſhould be careful of the Utenſils, and other neceſſaries, appertaining to the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſtery. 57. If any one be neceſſarily
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:46268:11"/>detained from Prayer in publick, and ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that then he prayes to God with his heart. 58. That they be reverent and devout in their Prayer, not ſuffering their Eyes to wander. 59. That the Steward and other Officers be prudent, faithful, and frugal. 60. That the Rewards on all occaſions be proportioned to the works. 61. That he who returns to God by Repentance, muſt weep and be ſorry for his miſdoings, and be in hatred with his former actions. 62. That none ſhould be diſmayed, ſeeing they have nothing to give to the poor, becauſe they have leſt all to follow Chriſt. 63. That they muſt not be ſilent, or wink at Offences, but reprove them. 64. They ſhould ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be without compunction and care, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the remainder of ſin is in them. 65. That they endeavour to be poor in ſpirit, which is to forgoe all for the love of God. 66. That they continue in well doing to their lives end. 67. That though in reſpect of themſelves, they ought not to be ſolicitous what to eat or drink; yet that they may be helpful to others, they ought to labour with their hands. 68. That they are not deſirous of meat and drink out of ſeaſon. 69. That in token of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility they wear Sack-cloth, and ſpeak
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:46268:11"/>with moderation, expreſſing therein nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Shame nor Confidence. 70. That the Euchariſt be received with Reverence, Fear, and Faith. 71. That they obſerve when it is convenient to ſpeak, and when to be ſilent. 72. That they have ever the the fear of God before their Eyes, ſhun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the broad way, and chuſing the nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row. 73. That they avoid Covetouſneſs and Vain-glory, as alſo Gayety in apparel. 74. That they abſtain from the defile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the fleſh, and endeavour to be pure in heart. 75. That they hate ſin, and make Gods Law their delight. 76. That they try and expreſs their love to God by their thankfulneſs to him, their obedience to his Commandments, their love to their Neighbour, in proſperity and adverſity. 77. That they ſhould imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate Chriſt in loving their enemies. 78. That they ſhould be angry, but not ſo as to ſin, and ſuffer without reſiſtance, or fly from the perſecution. 79. That they labour for the peace of Conſcience. 80. That none be puffed up with a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit of his own worth, brag thereof, or glory therein. 81. That they implore true Wiſdom of God, acknowledging him the Author of all good. 82. That they ſtudy to know, what it is to be good and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:46268:12"/>holy. 83. That they viſit no Women, but in company, and that by permiſſion, and for Edification, thereby to avoid offence. 84. That reproof be moved with Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, none relying on his own judgment. 85. That they patiently bear each others infirmities. 86. That they pray againſt Temptation. 87. That what they do they do adviſedly, and with mature delibera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. 88. That the Alms be delivered by the hand of him to whom the charge is committed. 89. That they labour not for Faith without Charity, nor hide the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent that is given them to improve. 90. That they diſtinguiſh between Fury, which is to be accounted ſin, and the juſt Indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation againſt ſin. 91. That Satan has no abſolute power to oblige a man to ſin, without his own conſent and yielding. 92. If any man be deſirous to enter into the Monaſtery, and be in debt, he ought firſt to ſatisfie his Creditors, if he be able. 93. That when any of that Monaſtery confeſſes a Nun or Recluſe, he ought to do it with decency in the preſence of the Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beſs. 94. That if the Temptation to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent a Good Work be ſtrong, they ought to deſiſt till they have prevailed againſt it. 95. That they rely not on their own wiſdom nor ſtrength, but upon God in
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:46268:12"/>all emergences, and on all occaſions.</p>
               <p>Thus St. <hi>Baſil</hi> enjoyned this Holy Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, as they more largely appear in his Works, which were religiouſly and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voutly obſerved; and indeed contain in them the whole Body of the Chriſtian Religion. As to the principal Heads pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, and what therein may appear ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonious, was enjoyned, no doubt, for Decency, and the better regulating the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs of the Monaſticks, whoſe tenents were much to be commended: Nay, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing the example of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> they la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured with their own hands, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came ſo induſtrious, that their Monaſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry was called <hi>the place of Exerciſe,</hi> and they the <hi>Exerciſers,</hi> as <hi>Hoſpinian</hi> out of <hi>Budaeus</hi> obſerves; as for the Garments enjoyned them, they were white, plain and decent.</p>
               <p>Subſequent to theſe, St. <hi>Hierom,</hi> after he had lived with divers of his Followers in the Deſart of <hi>Syria,</hi> to avoid his ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thoſe vices, in thoſe that made an external profeſſion of Chriſtianity, which he could not redreſs, betook himſelf, with his Company, to a Monaſtery in <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria,</hi> founded by a Noble <hi>Roman</hi> Lady, near the Stable in <hi>Bethlehem,</hi> where our Bleſſed Saviour was born. There he and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:46268:13"/>his Companions lived divers years, ſpend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the time in Devotion and Meditation Writing and Inſtructing thoſe that cam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to him in the knowledge of the Goſpel truths, ſo that his fame, for Piety and Learning, ſpreading abroad, many No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Youths came and were inſtructed by him. As for the Monks of his Order they were accounted very devout, and diſtinguiſhed from others, by wearing Swart or Brown coloured Garments, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a plaited Cloak over their Coat, a Leathern Girdle with which they girded themſelves, as alſo wooden Shoes; they were called <hi>Hieronimiam,</hi> and flouriſhed after his death, who chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged this life for one more Glorious, in the 91 year of his Age, and of Chriſt 421.</p>
               <p>There was likewiſe an Order-of Ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites of St. <hi>Hierom,</hi> inſtituted by <hi>Charles Granellus,</hi> a <hi>Florentine,</hi> about the year of Chriſt 1365. which flouriſhed chiefly in <hi>Italy</hi> and <hi>Spain,</hi> procuring, by their Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Induſtry, large Revenues from Charitable Benefactors, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:46268:13"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> A Diſcourſe of the Religious Orders of Monks, or Canons-Regular, and Eremits Instituted by St. <hi>Auguſtin;</hi> their Habit, manner of Living, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> with the Opinion of ſome in relation to the Monks, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Shaving their Crowns. A Diſcourſe in general of Religious Orders, and their ſtrict Obſervance.</head>
               <p>ST. <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> that great Pillar of the Church, being miraculouſly Convert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and withdrawn from the debaucheries of his Youth, thought with St. <hi>Paul,</hi> that he ought to labour more abundantly for his former remiſsneſs, and therefore bent his Study to do what might moſt tend to the Converſion of Souls; wherefore be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made Biſhop of <hi>Hippo</hi> in <hi>Africa,</hi> he founded a Monaſtery within the Church, where himſelf reſided with many Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men as in a College, ſending, as he ſaw occaſion, divers Learned men from thence to Preach the Goſpel, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade the people to renounce thoſe Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, or erroneous Opinions that had been Impoſed upon them, or Inſtill'd into them by Falſe-Teachers: And to him is at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:46268:14"/>the Inſtitution of three Orders, <hi>viz.</hi> Eremites, Monks, and Canons-Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular. Yet Authors give but a very ſlen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der account of the two firſt, though ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny have ſince profeſſed to live after his Rules: As the <hi>Scopetini,</hi> inſtituted by <hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phen,</hi> and <hi>James</hi> of <hi>Sena,</hi> and confirmed by <hi>Gregory,</hi> the Eleventh Biſhop of <hi>Rome, Anno</hi> 1408. The <hi>Triſenarii,</hi> otherwiſe called <hi>Lateraneſes,</hi> who had their begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in the Province of <hi>Hetruria</hi> near <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca,</hi> and confirmed by <hi>Eugenius,</hi> the Fourth Biſhop of <hi>Rome.</hi> The Order of St. <hi>George</hi> in <hi>Alga,</hi> inſtituted by <hi>Laurentius Juſtinia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> at <hi>Venice, Anno</hi> 1407. and ratified by <hi>John</hi> the 22 Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> who are ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited in Blew, with many others, of whom I ſhall have occaſion to ſpeak here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.</p>
               <p>The Habit of the <hi>Canons-Regular</hi> is a white Cloath Coat open before, reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down to their Feet, and girded to their Body; over it they wear a White Surplice reaching to their Knees, and over that a ſhort Black Cloak not exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Elbows, with a Hood faſtned to it, having their Crowns ſhaven like Fryers: When they go abroad they wear a broad Hat, or a black cornered Cap.</p>
               <p>After the Example of the Canons-Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſtical,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:46268:14"/>were other Canons erected, ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Eccleſiaſtical Canons, who had no Abbot, but were governed by their Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop. Theſe had ſtill their reſidence near the Cathedral Church, which was fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently called <hi>Monaſtery,</hi> and whilſt they lived up to the ſtrictneſs of their Order, were called <hi>Regular;</hi> but intereſſing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in worldly buſineſs, the word <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular</hi> was changed to <hi>Secular,</hi> as <hi>Volateran</hi> will have it. That there were Monaſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the Order in <hi>Europe</hi> 4555. though now there are many of them converted to other uſes, for of 700. which he af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms to have been in <hi>Italy,</hi> not 70 are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant, or at leaſt that are in poſſeſſion. He further adds, that out of this Order have ſprung 30. Popes, and 300. Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals.</p>
               <p>As for the Order of <hi>Eremites,</hi> the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count in ſhort is, that they wore a Black Coat, with a Hood of the ſame colour, having underneath it a little White Coat, with a Girdle of Leather, at the end of which was a Buckle of Horn. As yet Shaving was not generally uſed, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that of the Beard, though ſome will have it, that many in the Primitive Times did imitate St. <hi>Peter</hi> therein, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſhaven by the <hi>Gentiles</hi> at <hi>Antioch,</hi>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:46268:15"/>gloryed in what they accounted a Shame and deſpight: though <hi>Bellarmine</hi> and others ſeem to refer it to a Decree of the Fourth Council of <hi>Toledo, Anno Chriſti</hi> 631. But the matter in this caſe being of no conſiderable weight or moment, I ſhall wave it, and give the Opinions of ſome, why Monks and Clerks are ſhaven amongſt Chriſtians on the top of the Head; and they hold it as the ſence of thoſe that injoyned it, <hi>viz.</hi> That the hair hanging round their Heads like a Circle, ſhould put them in mind of the Crown of Thorns, worn by our bleſſed Saviour, and to reſemble it. To inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate, That Chriſt's Prieſts are Spiritual Kings: That by ſhaving of the Hair they ſignifie the laying aſide all ſuperfluity of the fleſh, and ſinful luſts: That by the nakedneſs of the Crown of the Head, is ſhewed the mind ought to be free for contemplation, as alſo purity and ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of Life, to ſhew their repentance and converſion, for ſuch were commanded to cut their Hair before they were again admitted into the Church: And further, that in the Primitive times the Chriſtian Monks cut their Hair to diſtinguiſh them from the Jewiſh <hi>Nazarites,</hi> who wore long Hair, as <hi>Moſes</hi> did a Veil, to ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:46268:15"/>the Myſtery of Redemption was not yet revealed: That they cut their Hair likewiſe to ſhew their Contempt of the world, and of thoſe effeminate men who gloryed in long Hair, as an Ornament of Pride.</p>
               <p>As for the ſhaving of the Beard, it is held to be done, that they might look ſmooth like Children, and Angels, who are always repreſented youthful; and by this is meant that they ſhould be harm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs and free from malice as the firſt, and innocent as the latter. Theſe are the Opinions of ſome who have undertaken to give the ſence of the firſt Practiſers, with much more to the ſame purpoſe, which is probable enough, though whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſo or otherways I ſhall not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take to determine.</p>
               <p>Having ſpoken ſomewhat in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar as to the Religious Orders in the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Times, I ſhall now proceed, for brevities ſake, to ſpeak in general, rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to their Exerciſe and Inſtitution, <hi>viz.</hi> They laboured upon ſeveral occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Eat and Drank moderately, went decent in Apparel, Faſted and Prayed often, poſſeſſed their Goods (ſuch as they had) in common, Preached, Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated, read the Scriptures, ſtudied Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:46268:16"/>Obedience, Temperance, Humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Silence. They were divided into Tens and Hundreds, every nine having their <hi>Decurio</hi> or Tenth man, every hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred their <hi>Centurio,</hi> to whom the <hi>Decu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rio's</hi> were ſubject. They lay in diſtinct Beds, and at the ninth hour went to hear Sermons, and to Sing. At the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble they ſat ſilent, and for the moſt part contented themſelves with Bread, Herbs, and Salt; Wine was only permitted to thoſe that were ſtricken in years. In the Night-time they had their ſet hours of Prayer; Dining only in the Summer time without any Supper. Their Chief Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernor they called their Father, and Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bot in the <hi>Syriack;</hi> he generally being a man of great Learning, and Eminent for an Exemplary Life. They wore Hoods and Girdles, went with Staves, and Scrips of Goat-Skins: and ſome again, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thoſe in <hi>Egypt,</hi> wore no Shoes, they ſerved one another by turns, and knew their places, humbling themſelves by waſhing each others Feet, ever moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voutly obſerving the Sixth, Ninth, and Third hour for Prayer: Nor were they admitted till they had given Ten days attendance without the Gate, and pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently ſuffered the Indignities and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:46268:16"/>of the Gentiles; then the Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bot read them a Lecture of <hi>Humility, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, Obedience, Sobriety, Submiſſion, Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification, Self-denial,</hi> and <hi>Confeſsion</hi> of their <hi>Infirmities,</hi> then they received the Habit, and remained a whole year under the ſtricteſt Diſcipline. And if a diſlike in that ſpace hapned on either ſide, they had free leave to take the Cloaths they brought, and depart: No Offences were connived at, but on the contrary puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with publick Humiliation, the offender after having acknowledged his Tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, lying flat on the ground till the Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bot commanded him to riſe; this was the puniſhment of ſmall Offences, but for greater, greater puniſhments were award<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as Stripes and Expulſion. At the Table (to be taken off from idle Talk and vain Imaginations) they were to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to ſuch portions of Scripture as were appointed to be read, that ſo their minds might be fed as well as their Bodies. The ſubjection of thoſe Primitive Monaſterys, was in chief to the Biſhop of the Dioceſs wherein they were ſcituate, nor could they go abroad, or any exceed their bounds without his leave. And thus they lived in a happy contented eſtate, deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing worldly vanities in expectation of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:46268:17"/>being rewarded in the world to come with laſting Joys, which this cannot af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> A Diſcourſe of the Inſtitution of Nuns, and their Monaſteries; what they Profeſs, and how Received. The Manner of Conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Monks and Nuns in the Primitive times, and how they were Received.</head>
               <p>THat Women were no leſs devout than Men in the Primitive Times, it is wonderfully apparent, not only in Holy Writ, but in the writing of the Fathers. Nor amongſt others can we be ignorant of the memories of <hi>Euſtochium, Marcella, Sophronia, Principia,</hi> and <hi>Paula,</hi> who vow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chaſtity, and a contempt of world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things, betook themſelves to a retired Life, and in hopes to gain an immortal weight of Glory, left their Parents, Riches, and large Poſſeſſions, though in thoſe times they were not kept to ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but might return if they ſaw con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient; but moſt of them being raviſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the contemplation of Holy Things, Renounced all Converſe, unleſs
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:46268:17"/>with ſuch as were their Companions, and ſtill imployed themſelves in Holy Duties, and Works of Compaſſion and Charity.</p>
               <p>The firſt Nunnerys we find in the Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of the Fathers, that could be term<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a Settlement for Religious Women, were founded in the Reign of <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine</hi> the Great, when God gave his Church peace. For in the ſtorm of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution, the Condition of the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans was uncertain, their places of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Worſhip obſcure, and remote from Cities and Towns, nay in Caves and Deſarts, as I have already ſpoken: And Religious Women for fear of being ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſhed in deſpite, by the enemies of the Goſpel, rarely made a publick Profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Chaſtity: But when they found they might do it with ſafeguard of their Honour, they made it their Glory, and though born of Noble Parentage, they applyed themſelves in their recluſes and retirements to ſtudy <hi>Modeſty, Frugality, Patience, Obedience, Submiſsion, Silence,</hi> and were enjoyned to go plain and neat in apparel; not to converſe with men, nor to walk alone; not to Bathe, unleſs their Feet and Hands; to Pray and Faſt often; to waſh poor Peoples Feet in to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:46268:18"/>of Humility; not to be idle, but rather Sing, Pray, Read, hear, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form ſome curious Work with the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, or otherwiſe. They were prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſhaving by the Council of <hi>Gangra. Can.</hi> 17. Though ſome of the Nuns in <hi>Egypt</hi> did cut their Hair: And in the Reign of <hi>Jovinian,</hi> becauſe the luſtful <hi>Donatiſts</hi> defloured divers Nuns, it was made Capital for any man to marry or ſolicit a Nun, and ſuch married Couples were excommunicated by the Church, had perpetual Impriſonment, or were put to Death by the Civil Magiſtrate, and the Marriage abſolutely diſanulled.</p>
               <p>As for the Conſecration of Monks in the Primitive Times; the Monk after Prayers and Exhortation made by the Prieſt, was ſigned with the Sign of the Croſs, and his Hair Cut or Shaven, and being ſtripped, the Monaſtical Habit put upon him, and with other holy Men pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, was made partaker of the Divine Myſteries.</p>
               <p>As for Nuns they were uſually Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated by the Biſhop or Prieſt, who co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered them with a <hi>Veil,</hi> the Abbeſs or Abboteſs upon pain of Excommunicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on not daring to attempt it. Twenty five years of age were the years of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:46268:18"/>then held for a Virgin to be <hi>Veiled,</hi> but now Twelve is accounted a ſufficient number. The days for recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Veil and Conſecration, were <hi>Epiphany</hi> and <hi>Eaſter Eve,</hi> or the Feſtival Days of the Apoſtles, unleſs in caſe of death, and then the Virgin to be Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated, was uſually preſented to the Biſhop in her Nuns Attire, ſtanding at the Altar, with Muſique and burning Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, when putting on the Veil he uſed to expreſs theſe words, <hi>viz. Behold, Daughter, and forget thy People, and thy Fathers Houſe, that the King may take pleaſure in thy Beauty,</hi> to which the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſaying <hi>Amen,</hi> the Veil is caſt over her, and the Religious Women and Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins preſent Kiſs and Embrace her; after which the Biſhop bleſſing her, and praying for her, ſhe departs to her place, to be inſtructed by her Seniors in good Works. And thus much may ſuffice as to the Primitive Times <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive we may call them, becauſe Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity was then in a manner in its Infancy, and the ſplendor of the Viſible Church, though in Devotion great, was not ſo Apparent or Conſpicuous as it after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward was by its increaſe of Riches, Power, and the multiplying of Religious
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:46268:19"/>Orders. Wherefore to come nearer to our times, I ſhall in the next place give you an account of the Original and Progreſs of the <hi>Benedictine Monks,</hi> or Monks of the Order of St. <hi>Benedict</hi> or <hi>Benet,</hi> and what other Orders ſprung from them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> A View of the Order of the <hi>Benedictine Monks,</hi> their Inſtitution and manner of Living, and Habit: The Rules enjoyned them by St. <hi>Benet,</hi> and the Council of <hi>Aquiſgran</hi> or <hi>Aix,</hi> with what relates to the Nuns of that Order, and what to their Superiors, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>BEnedict,</hi> or <hi>Benet,</hi> being born in <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>mbra,</hi> a Province or Country in <hi>Italy,</hi> gave himſelf much to the Contemplation of Holy Things; and not having ſuch op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity as he deſired in popular places, by reaſon of the continual Wars and Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mults, he withdrew himſelf into the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarts, where he remained not ſo ſecret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but he was found out and followed by multitudes of people, which made him leave his Solitude, and go to <hi>Caſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinium,</hi> an ancient Town, and there it
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:46268:19"/>was he preſcribed Laws or Rules to his Followers under the ſtile of Monks, and is reported to have Founded twelve Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſteries, placing over them twelve Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bots that had been his Diſciples and Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers. And at <hi>Caſſinium</hi> the principal Monaſtery, which was indowed by <hi>Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullius</hi> a <hi>Roman</hi> Patrician, <hi>Equitius</hi> a Senator, and others who followed their Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, with Caſtles, Villages, and Lands to a great Revenue: And ſo ſucceſsful was this Order, that in a ſhort time it ſpread it ſelf all over <hi>Germany, France, Spain, Sicily, England,</hi> and other Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trys. In <hi>France</hi> the firſt Monaſtery was founded near <hi>Orleance</hi> by <hi>Maurus,</hi> Son to <hi>Equitius</hi> the Senator, who was of the <hi>Benedictine</hi> Order, conſiſting of 140 Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, that Number not to be leſſened or increaſed. <hi>Placidus,</hi> Son to <hi>Turtullius</hi> the Patrician, founded another in <hi>Sicily;</hi> and <hi>Benedict</hi> by the aſſiſtance of <hi>Leobar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus</hi> founded one in <hi>Alſatia</hi> near <hi>Straſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg;</hi> he planted a Monaſtery likewiſe near the <hi>Latteran</hi> Church in <hi>Rome,</hi> in the time of <hi>Pelagius.</hi> And by <hi>Donatus,</hi> a <hi>Benedictine</hi> Convent was erected in <hi>Spain,</hi> in or near the year of Chriſt 590. And by the Encouragement and Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of <hi>Auguſtine</hi> Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury,</hi>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:46268:20"/>this Order began to ſpread in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Anno</hi> 596. As it did in <hi>Germany, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no</hi> 545. by the Influence of <hi>Boniface</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Mentz,</hi> who gave great incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to thoſe of the Order. But in proceſs of time theſe Benedictines divided themſelves into divers Branches or Sects, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Cluniacenſes</hi> Ordained and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulged by <hi>Otho,</hi> an Abbot in <hi>Burgundia,</hi> on whom <hi>William,</hi> Dean of <hi>Aquitain,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed a Village named <hi>Maſtick, Anno</hi> 916. The <hi>Camalduenſes</hi> were erected on the top of the <hi>Appenine</hi> Hills by <hi>Romoaldus</hi> a Benedictine: And thoſe called <hi>Valliſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brenſes,</hi> from <hi>Villis <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>mbroſa</hi> the place of their Scituation, were erected by a <hi>Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentine</hi> named <hi>Gaulbertus, Anno</hi> 1060. The <hi>Montelinetenſes</hi> were erected by <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard Ptolomeus</hi> at <hi>Scienna</hi> in <hi>Tuſcany, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no.</hi> 1047. The <hi>Grandimontenſes</hi> were erected much about the ſame time by <hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phen,</hi> a Noble French man. The <hi>Ciſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians,</hi> who derive their denomination from <hi>Ciſtertium</hi> in <hi>Burgundy,</hi> were not long after erected by <hi>Robert</hi> Abbot of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tismenia;</hi> and of this Order was St. <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard</hi> who was Abbot of <hi>Claravalis,</hi> about the year of Chriſt 1098. and from him, in proceſs of time, his Monks were called Bernardines, though they are the ſame
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:46268:20"/>with the Ciſtertians, ſaving the Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nardines wear a Black Gown over a White Coat, and the other White Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments only. The <hi>Celeſtini,</hi> deriving their Denomination from Pope <hi>Cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi> the Fifth, were founded by him, and by <hi>Gregory</hi> the Tenthconfirmed in the General Council held at <hi>Lyons</hi> in <hi>France.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe were, as I have ſaid, the branches of the Benedictine Order, moſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly following the ſame Rules, yet differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Colour of their Garment, for the Camalduenſes, Montelinetenſes, and Ciſtertians wear White, whilſt the Monks called Valiſumbroſa or Shadow-Valley wear Purple, the Celeſtines Skie Colour or Blew, and the Grandi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>montenſes a Black Cloak over a Coat of Mail.</p>
               <p>As for <hi>Benet</hi> or <hi>Benedict,</hi> he may be properly termed the Author or Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of each reſpective Religious Order, or the dependent Orders from his time, till the Dominicans and Mendicants took place: So that <hi>Trithemius</hi> in the Fourth Chapter of his Fourth Book, reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons no leſs than fifteen thouſand Abbies, which produced a number of Learned men, as Cardinals, Arch-Biſhops, and Biſhops, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> As for the Gregorian
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:46268:21"/>Order, it was a branch of the Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictines, <hi>Gregory</hi> the Great being a Monk of that Order; who, after the deceaſe of his Father, erected ſix Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſteries in the Iſle of <hi>Sicily,</hi> and turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his own Houſe in <hi>Rome</hi> into a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſtery, dedicating it to St. <hi>Andrew,</hi> aſcribing to his Monks, or the Perſons by him convened, the Rules of St <hi>Benet,</hi> which in general were to be obedient to their Superiors, obſerve the appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and ſeaſonable Times for Divine Worſhip, to be induſtrious in ſuch mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters as were enjoined them, and to live in Brotherly Love and Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs one towards another, and in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular much the ſame that was enjoyned by St. <hi>Baſil</hi> before recited. Decency and ſtrictneſs in all Affairs, eſpecially in thoſe of Importance, being neceſſarily required; and briefly what follows as to Religious Rules relating to this Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, were preſcribed and approved by the ſecond General Council of <hi>Aquiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gran</hi> or <hi>Aix,</hi> in the 816. year after Chriſt; which was,</p>
               <p>That the Lay-men or Secular Prieſts ſhould not be received into the Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries, unleſs they would become Monks. That the Monks take an Oath, that in
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:46268:21"/>Preparation week they take nothing but Water and Bread. That before they go to ſleep the Prior ſprinkle them with Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Water, and that of their Alms the tenth part be given to the Poor. That without the Priors leave they bathe not themſelves, and that they ſing pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Pſalms for the Dead. That they bow not their Knees, nor Faſt, but that they ſee in the Ember week they do it; as likewiſe on the Eves of the Apoſtles. That in caſe of neceſſity the Brothers ſupport themſelves with Staves, and when any Theft happens amongſt them that cannot be diſcovered readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that then they be ſuſpended from Supper until the Criminal confeſs the Fact. That at <hi>Chriſtmas</hi> and <hi>Eaſter,</hi> for the ſpace of eight days, thoſe that are ſo minded may feed on the fleſh of Fowl, and that they learn their Rules by heart. That in the Mills, Kitchen, and in other neceſſary Offices, they obſerve at ſeaſonable times to work with their own hands. That in caſe of Offence, the Offendor proſtrate him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf before the Prior or Abbot, and in humility acknowledge his Offence; and that they refrain to Kiſs or Salute Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. That they waſh in <hi>Lent</hi> each
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:46268:22"/>others Feet; and that the Abbot, at the receiving the Lords Supper, Waſh and Kiſs the Feet of the Monks: That it be obſerved at <hi>Chriſtmas, Eaſter,</hi> and in <hi>Whitſon</hi> Week Diſcourſes be refrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Cloiſter, and that they give themſelves up to the hearing of Sacred Things. That the Abbot exceed not the proportion of his Monks in Eating, Drinking, Lodging, Cloathing, and Sleeping; that he ramble not oft abroad, but that he labour with his Hands. That after the refection of the Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, the Servants attendant on the Monaſtery eat by themſelves, but that they ſhould have the ſame Leſſons read to them. That Hallelujah be not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated in the <hi>Septuageſima.</hi> As for the Novices, they muſt neither be Cloath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed nor Shaven as the Monks, till the time of their Probation be expired, and promiſe of Obedience made. That none be the Monks Superior, but ſuch an one as is a Monk. That in <hi>Lent</hi> they work till the ninth hour, and then hear Maſs, and take their refection in the Evening. And theſe are the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Duties enjoined to the Monks of of this Order, who at firſt being Lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, without any Prieſts, but ſuch as
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:46268:22"/>they had from abroad, are now permitted to have Prieſts of their own Order, choſen from amongſt themſelves, and that they ſhould be capable of recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Tythes, Oblations, Donations, and Firſt-fruits as other Prieſts; and this benefit was confirmed to them by <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory.</hi> the Great, <hi>Boniface,</hi> and other Biſhops of <hi>Rome,</hi> as <hi>Gratian</hi> witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth.</p>
               <p>The Habit and Diet of the <hi>Benedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctine</hi> Monks, they are generally theſe, <hi>viz.</hi> A Round Coat, a Hood called <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culla Cappa,</hi> and <hi>Melos</hi> from <hi>Melis</hi> a Brock, of whoſe Skin they were firſt made. A Scapular ſo called from its covering the Shoulders; in <hi>Summer</hi> their Hoods are ſingle, but in <hi>Winter</hi> lined: Nor were they wont to wear Breeches but in caſe of Traveling; as for their upper Garment it is Black, and that under it a White Woollen Coat, and formerly they wore Sackcloth, and went Booted, and indeed in Coarſer Garments than now they do; as like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe in their Diet there is much al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration, as to the quantity and quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. As for thoſe that are deſirous to be better informed herein, let them con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:46268:23"/>
                  <hi>Polydore Virgil, Hoſpinian, Sebeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>As for the Abbots, each Monaſtery chuſeth its own from amongſt the Monks, either by a General Conſent, or the Major Part of Voices; but if any Monaſtery do not find one within it ſelf capable of that Charge, liberty is given to chooſe an Abbot out of another. Nor is it in the power of thoſe that Elected him to Depoſe him when Elected, nor muſt he have more than one Monaſtery under his Charge, being likewiſe prohibited medling with Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Affairs. If he commit any grievous Offence, his Puniſhment muſt be in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Monaſtery, and not in his own, becauſe of the ſtrict Subjection and Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience wherewith his Monks are bound. If an unfit man be choſen, the Biſhop of the Dioceſs, aſſembling the Neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Abbots may depoſe him and chooſe another, whom the Monks muſt accept. Nor is the Biſhop reſtrained from viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Monaſteries, to ſee whether the Rules be obſerved; and that no Imbezlement be made, for the Abbot without his conſent ought to diſpoſe of nothing that may prejudice the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venues;
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:46268:23"/>and if the Abbot ſhall refuſe to ſubmit to the Biſhop in this or the like caſe, he is ſuſpended from the Communion till he acknowledge his Fault and repent. If a Clergy-man be choſen Abbot, he muſt relinquiſh his Function: What is conferred upon the Monaſtery by Benefactors, the Abbot muſt not convert to his own Uſe, nor ought any man to erect a Monaſtery without the Biſhops Conſent; nor muſt the Abbot travel far without his leave; nor ought the Biſhop himſelf to do any thing to the Prejudice of the Monaſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, for if he do, the Abbot may appeal from the Biſhop to the Prince, or to a Council. And indeed there are Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſteries that are only ſubjected to the Pope, as <hi>Caſſinium.</hi> The Monaſtery of St. <hi>Maximinus</hi> near <hi>Trevers</hi> is ſubject to the Pope in Spirituals, and to the Emperor in Temporals, but the Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bots ſwear Allegiance and Fealty to the Pope only, though formerly the power of Electing Abbots was in the Prince of the Country, in which the Monaſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry was ſcituate, and the manner was by putting a Staff and Ferula into his Hand, thereby to mind him of his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoral
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:46268:24"/>Office, as teſtifie <hi>Breſchius, Balae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, and Hoſpinian.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As for the Nuns of this Order they were Inſtituted by <hi>Scholaſtica,</hi> Siſter of St. <hi>Benedict</hi> or <hi>Benet,</hi> who erected an Order of Nuns after her Brothers Rule; but as to what is more particular, they are not permitted to be God-mothers in Baptiſm, nor unleſs in caſe of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity to go abroad, and that muſt be with ſome Ancient Woman. The grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt part of their Divine Worſhip to conſiſt in Singing, Meditation, and Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, obſerving the Canonical Hour; nor muſt they ſpeak with any man unleſs before two perſons who muſt hear the Diſcourſe, nor without a years Proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion muſt any be admitted into the Nunnery. If any be found unchaſt, ſhe receives three Diſciplines or Scourgings, and is to be fed with Bread and Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for the ſpace of a year under a ſtrict Confinement; nor muſt they wear Silks: Their Conſecration and Veiling belongs to the Biſhop only, and being cloathed with the Veſtments of her Order, ſhe kneeleth before the Altar with two Tapers in her Hand, and the Goſpel being read, the Biſhop prayes
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:46268:24"/>for her perſeverance in Patience, Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtity, Sobriety, Obedience, and the like. As for the Abbateſs ſhe ought to be a Woman of Gravity and Diſcretion, Religious and Vigilant over her Charge, not ſuffering the acceſs of men, nor after Sun-ſet till Morning any man to ſpeak with her ſelf or her Nuns, though at a diſtance; nor without the Biſhops leave muſt ſhe go abroad, and that leave obtained ſhe muſt ſubſtitute one to look to her Charge, and be ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy in her return, having ſome Nuns to accompany her in her way: And to be qualified for this truſt ſhe muſt be ſixty years of Age or upwards; no man muſt be permitted to enter unleſs the Prieſt to confeſs the Nuns, and he to ſtay no longer than he is Officia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, a conſiderable diſtance being al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways alotted between the Monaſteries of either Sex, to prevent Scandal and Temptation: Nor by any means muſt the Abbateſs preſume to lay hands on to Ordain a Prieſt, or Veil a Virgin. And thoſe that would be further ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ied in this point, let them peruſe <hi>Gregory</hi> and the Council of <hi>Tours, Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ojulium</hi> the ſixt of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:46268:25"/>that of <hi>Paris,</hi> under <hi>Ludovicus</hi> and <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tharius.</hi> And thus Reader have I given you a ſummary, and, as I hope, an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial account of St. <hi>Benet's</hi> Order, or the Order of the Benedictines, which floùriſhed extreamly in moſt parts of <hi>Europe;</hi> from which I ſhall proceed to give you an account of ſuch other Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, as upon its decay ſprung up in the <hi>Weſt,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:46268:25"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> A View of the Orders, Inſtitutions, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmations, Rules, manner of Living, Habit, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Of the <hi>Cluniacenſes, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maldulienſes, Villaſumbraſenſes, Syl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſtrinii, Grandimontenſes, Carthuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, Ceſtertines, Bernardines, Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liatii, Praemonſtratenſes, Gilbertines, Crucigeri, Hoſpitalarii, Trinitarians, Bethlemites, Dominicans</hi> or <hi>Praedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cants, Mendicants,</hi> their ſeveral Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as <hi>Auguſtines, Carmelites, Minorites,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Franciſcans</hi> or <hi>Minors</hi> and their Diviſion in a Triplicity, with what elſe is convenient or neceſſary to be known.</head>
               <p>THe Benedictines, for the ſpace of four hundred years, having flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the <hi>Weſtern</hi> part of the World, even from the time of <hi>Juſtinian,</hi> to <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radus</hi> the Firſt, which was about 900 years after Chriſt; and having ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what derogated from their Primitive Rules and Inſtitutions, divers perſons undertook to reform that Order, or
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:46268:26"/>rather to inſtitute new ones, confining them moſtly within the compaſs of St. <hi>Bennets</hi> Rules, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Though for the moſt part, if not all of them, making ſome new Additions or Statutes: And the firſt that we find to undertake it, was one <hi>Berno</hi> who founded a Monaſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry near <hi>Cluniacum,</hi> over which, before his Deceaſe, he placed as Abbot one <hi>Odo;</hi> and from the ſcituation of their Monaſtery were called <hi>Cluniacenſes.</hi> By their Rules the Abbot was bound to eat with the Monks; that a revolting Monk returning to his Obedience, might be three times received, or more, at the diſcretion of the Abbot. They re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed the cuſtom of dipping the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated Bread into the Cup, which was before uſed, in caſe of neceſſity, to ſick perſons, and ſometimes to Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and afterwards promiſcuouſly uſed by all the Communion, till by Pope <hi>Julius,</hi> 340. years after Chriſt, it was forbidden; but this Cuſtom again revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved <hi>Anno</hi> 580. but continued not lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger; it was interdicted by the third Synod of <hi>Baracara,</hi> and ſo ceaſed till theſe Monks, <hi>Anno</hi> 920. revived it. In caſe any deſire to be admitted into
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:46268:26"/>their Order, they are brought to the Monaſtery, and there waſhed, clipped, and ſhaved; when as their old Clothes being ſtripped off, they have new Cloathes put on, and are thereupon ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, being enjoyned Piety, Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, Chaſtity, Labour, and Patience, little differing from the <hi>Benedictines</hi> in their Rules and Orders, as witneſs <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Cluniacenſis, Bernard, Sebelicus, Caſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſander,</hi> and others.</p>
               <p>In or about the year 1030. as <hi>Sabe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licus</hi> will have it, one <hi>Romualdus</hi> of <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venna,</hi> obſerving St. <hi>Benets</hi> Rules, not kept up to their Primitive ſtrictneſs, reſolved upon erecting a new Order, and layd his Foundation in the Field of <hi>Camaldulum,</hi> whence the Monks of his Order took the name of <hi>Camaldu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenſes.</hi> After this Foundation he erect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a Monaſtery on the top of the <hi>Appenine</hi> Hills, a place there being granted him for that purpoſe by <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulus,</hi> who was induced thereto by a Dream repreſenting Ladders reaching to Heaven, on which he ſaw men in White Cloathing mounting upwards, fancying he beheld the Ladders on thoſe Hills, and that it ſignified <hi>the climbing
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:46268:27"/>of devout Christians to Heaven by Faith.</hi> And the better to fulfill this Viſion, <hi>Romualdus</hi> having built his Convent or Monaſtery, gave his Monks White Hoods, enjoining them ſilence, unleſs in time of Divine Service; and yet ſome to keep this Rule of Silence more exactly, refuſe to join with the reſt, chuſing to pray by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: Two days in a Week, which they account their Faſt, they ſubſiſted with Bread and Water only, ſitting bare-footed on the ground: About half a mile from this Monaſtery are Wooden Croſſes; the boundaries of Women upon ſtrict penalties, leaſt they approaching the Monks walks, ſhould tempt them to folly.</p>
               <p>Subſequent to theſe are the Monks of <hi>Villa <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>mbroſa,</hi> or Shaddow-Valley, called from thence <hi>Villaſumbrenſes,</hi> and thoſe were inſtituted by <hi>John Gual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert,</hi> by birth a <hi>Florentine, Anno</hi> 1060. as it is generally held; who reſolving to renounce the world, came to this Valley, where he found two Monks, and there he builded himſelf an Houſe of Board; and his Pious manner of living ſoon ſpread his fame, inſomuch
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:46268:27"/>that not only the Layety flocked to viſit him, but many likewiſe of the Clergy: And the Lady of that Soil being an Abboteſs, gave him not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that ground, but other large Poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; and by the Monks that flocked to him being made Abbot, he enjoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them St. <hi>Benets</hi> Rules with additi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; that they ſhould wear no other Cloaths, but what they made of the Wool of ſuch Sheep, as ſhould be brought up for their uſe in thoſe Val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leys; and that they ſhould burn Lights in the Dormitory and Chappel. Nor did he only regard his own, but made a reformation in divers Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſteries; placing Provoſts of his own election over them; building divers Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Places in <hi>Lombardy,</hi> and elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where; and for that and his pious way of living being Canonized, his Order was confirmed by Pope <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> the Second, and <hi>Gregory</hi> the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth. And thoſe that would be fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſatisfied as to this Order, may read <hi>Surius de vitis Sanctorum, Volateran, Sebelicus, Antonius,</hi> and others.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Sylveſtrini,</hi> ſo called from <hi>Syl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſter,</hi> their Inſtitutor, walk much after
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:46268:28"/>the Rule and Habit of thoſe Monks of <hi>Villa <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>mbroſa,</hi> or Shaddow-Valley, taking their beginning in <hi>Italy</hi> in the <hi>Marquiſate</hi> of <hi>Ancona.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Grandimontenſes,</hi> according to Tradition, were Inſtituted upon an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known Voice, uttering three times di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly, <hi>Grandi-Monte,</hi> in a great Hall, where one <hi>Peter</hi> then hearing it was advized by it to build a Monaſtery, he being the Diſciple and Succeſſor to <hi>Stephen,</hi> who <hi>Anno</hi> 1076. erected this Order on the Hill <hi>Muretum</hi> in <hi>Gaſcony,</hi> and gave Rules little inconſiſtent with St. <hi>Benets,</hi> though ſomething was added of the Rules obſerved by the Canons-Regular of St. <hi>Auſtin</hi>'s Monks, and of his Eremites; after which he wandred through divers Deſarts, wearing next his Skin a Coat of Mail, his Bed was hard without Straw or Covering, his Hands and Knees with often kneeling and bearing on the ground to kiſs it, were hard as horn. This Order had an Abbot ſet over them by <hi>John</hi> the Second Biſhop of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Order of the <hi>Carthuſians,</hi> or Charter-Fryers, were inſtituted by one <hi>Bruno,</hi> and as Tradition goes, on the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:46268:28"/>following occaſion, <hi>viz. Bruno,</hi> a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive of <hi>Collen,</hi> and a Profeſſor of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy in <hi>Paris,</hi> about the year of Chriſt 1080. being preſent at the ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Office for his Fellow-Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor, deceaſed, a man in no mean re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute for his holy way of Living: The dead Corps (by the help of what power is uncertain) raiſed it ſelf up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Bier, and with a lamentable voice cried out, <hi>I am in God's juſt Judgment Condemned,</hi> which words were three ſeveral times diſtinctly repeated; at which <hi>Bruno</hi> was in ſo great a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſternation, that if a man reputed ſo pious was loſt, what would become of Him and his Fellows; the terror of which wrought ſo far in his mind, that he concluded that there could be no ſafer way to prevent the like doom, than by forſaking the world; whereupon with ſix of his Fellows or Diſciples, he betook himſelf to a dark place overſhadowed with Woods, high Hills, and Rocks, inhabited before on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by wild Beaſts, which he found out in the Province of <hi>Dolphini,</hi> that place being called <hi>Carthuſia,</hi> from whence his Monks took their Deno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination;
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:46268:29"/>and there obtaining ground of <hi>Hugo</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Grenoble,</hi> they built a poor Monaſtery, which Biſhop af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward beholding their pious man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Life, became one of their Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. By their Rules they ſhould wear Sackcloth, or a Hair-ſhirt next their Skin, and over it a long looſe White Cloth Coat, and when they walk abroad a Hood and a Black Cloak over that; and that the Lay Brothers wear a ſnort Coat reaching but to their Knees. As for fleſh, by their Rule they eat none at all, nor any fiſh unleſs given them; their Bread is a great part Bran, and their Drink Wine mingled with Water. On <hi>Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day</hi> and the fifth day of the Week Cheeſe and Eggs are their only fare, on the third Pulſe, or Pot-hearbs, on the ſecond, fourth and ſixth, they ſubſiſt on Bread and Water. They eat but once a day, and that apart, every one preparing what he eats, unleſs on Feſtival days, and then they eat twice a day, ſitting all toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther at a Table, and then they may talk together; but at other times are enjoyned to keep ſilence, every one be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:46268:29"/>accommodated with a peculiar Cell, in which he Reads, Prayes and Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates, ſometimes writing Books, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> obſerving the Canonical hour; but their Veſpers and Mattins they keep in their Churches, whence Women are exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. On the Saints days and Feſtival days they hear Maſs, nor go they abroad unleſs the Prior and Procurator, and they not unleſs ſome urgent af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs require it, relating to the Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery: Some ſmall parcels of Land they have whereon they feed Sheep, Goats, and the like to give them Milk; not cohabiting above twelve Religious men in a Convent, beſides the Prior, eigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen Lay Converts, and ſome few Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants to fetch in their Proviſion, who are not admitted into the ſuperior Quire, but have one by themſelves; nor will they re-admit any that has revolted: Theſe were their Primitive Rules, but are ſince ſomewhat moderated. Their yearly meeting is at a Chapter annu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally held at <hi>Carthuſia</hi> about their own affairs, two Monks being deputed to repreſent each Cloiſter, being enjoined not to be abſent from their Cells above fourteen days. As for this Order it
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:46268:30"/>was confirmed <hi>Anno</hi> 1178. by Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> the Third, and coming into <hi>England Anno</hi> 1180. ſeated themſelves at <hi>Witham</hi> near <hi>Bathe,</hi> and of them more at large you may read in <hi>Balaeus, Polidore Virgil, Vincentius,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Cestertian</hi> Order began about the year 1098. being founded by one <hi>Robert,</hi> Abbot of <hi>Molismenia,</hi> who by the perſwaſion of one <hi>Robert Harding</hi> an Engliſhman, forſook the ſociety of the <hi>Benedictines,</hi> as not pleaſed with the indifferent regard they had to their Primitive Strictneſs of living; and in the Company of twenty one Monks came to <hi>Ceſtertium</hi> in <hi>Burgundy,</hi> and there erected a Convent, reſolving to revive, as it were, St. <hi>Benet</hi>'s Rules, and ſtrictly to obſerve them; and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing Poverty and Humility, they would not ſuffer their Monks to med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle with Husbandry, or any Secular matters; ordering, as St. <hi>Benet</hi> did, that each Monaſtery ſhould conſiſt of twelve Monks and an Abbot, and are enjoined ſilence, unleſs to the Abbot or Prior, and if any one eſcape, the Biſhop apprehends him, if he can be found in his Dioceſs, and obliges him
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:46268:30"/>to return; two Coats and two Hoods, being all the Garments that are allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them. They are very ſtrict in their Faſts, ſaluting Strangers by declining their Body and Head, and in imitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our Bleſſed Saviour waſh their Feet: and after a third eſcape, no one is to be received into the Convent: And as for the Abbots Table, it muſt be furniſhed for ſtrangers; to relieve them on their journey. Pope <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rbin</hi> the Second confirmed this Order, <hi>Anno</hi> 1100. and thirty two years af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they came into <hi>England</hi> in Grey Habit, wherefore by ſome they were called <hi>Griſei.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Bernardines,</hi> ſo called from St. <hi>Bernard,</hi> Abbot of <hi>Clarivallis,</hi> and differ from the <hi>Ciſtertians</hi> but in that their Habit is Black; nor are they in ſubjection to Biſhops or Advocates; it being ordered by Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> the Third, upon the refuſal of the Biſhop to bleſs the Abbot, one of the Monks of this Convent might beſtow the Benediction.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Humiliati</hi> began their Order, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Year of Chriſt 1164. They were a people brought out of <hi>Lombardy</hi>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:46268:31"/>into <hi>Germany,</hi> as Captives, by <hi>Frederick Barbaroſſa,</hi> who warred upon that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try; and being tired with their long Captivity, they attired themſelves in white; and aſſembling (eſpecially the chief of them) together, they caſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with Tears and Supplications at the Emperors feet, imploring him to give them leave to paſs into their own Country; which moving him to compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion he granted: And having Vowed to turn Recluſes, they built Monaſteries, and moſtly betook them to a Monaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal life; giving themſelves to Faſting, Prayer, Meditation, and Working with their Hands at making Cloth. Their Habit is a plain Coat, a Scapular, and a white Cloak over it; and ſtrictly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve St. <hi>Benet</hi>'s Rules, with ſome ſmall addition. Theſe were confirmed an Order by Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the Third, and others that ſucceeded him. The which, together with a larger diſcourſe of theſe Monaſticks, you may find in <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lydore, Sebelicus, Volateran, Antonius, Trithemius, Crantzius,</hi> and the like Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Praemonſtratenſes</hi> were an Order Founded by one <hi>Robert,</hi> or as ſome
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:46268:31"/>will have it, <hi>Norbert,</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Magdeburgh;</hi> who not reliſhing the Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and Pride of ſome Eccleſiaſticks of thoſe days, betook himſelf, with thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen of his Companions into a Foreſt, in the Dioceſs of <hi>Liege;</hi> and entering upon a ſtrict Life, he went bare-foot, even in the Winter; preaching Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, <hi>Anno.</hi> 1119, and regulated their Actions by the Rules of St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> which they ſay were delivered to them in golden Letters. Their Habit is a white Coat with a Linnen Surplice, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a Cloak; and theſe were confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by <hi>Calixtus</hi> the Second, by the Title of <hi>Canons Regular Exempt:</hi> Their Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bots are denied to wear Gloves, Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and Staves, or Rings: All the Abbots of the Order in their perſons, or by their Deputies, are obliged to be preſent at <hi>Praemonſtratum</hi> once a year, to conſult the good of the Order; and if any of them refuſe, the reſt may inflict ſuch Penalties as none but the Pope can take off. Theſe Abbots have likewiſe power to Excommunicate: If the Dioceſian refuſe to give Ordination, they may require it of any other Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, he (by reaſon of their Exemption)
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:46268:32"/>having no power over them. Theſe and many the like Priviledges Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the Fourth beſtowed on them, after they were Confirmed; they having likewiſe divers Schools amongſt them, for the Education of Youth. Their coming firſt into <hi>England</hi> was about the year of Chriſt 1145. and having liberty from the Pope to have Nunneries cloſe to their Monaſteries, they ſeated themſelves in <hi>Lincoln-ſhire.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Gilbertines</hi> took their deno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination from one <hi>Gilbert,</hi> a Native of <hi>Lincoln-ſhire;</hi> who in the year 1148. inſtituted that Order, and Erected in a little ſpace Thirteen Monaſteries; to whoſe Monks he preſcribed divers Rules, taken out of thoſe of St. <hi>Bennet</hi> and St. <hi>Auſtin;</hi> and had the Order confirmed by Pope <hi>Eugenius</hi> the Third; his chief Monaſtery, or Cloyſter being at <hi>Semperingham</hi> in <hi>Lincoln-ſhire,</hi> in which were ſaid to be Seven hundred Monks, or as ſome will have them Friers, and Eleven hundred Nuns: And of this Order, as to its riſe, <hi>&amp;c. Balaeus, Capgrave, Crezantius,</hi> and <hi>Trithemius, Sigebert's Continuator,</hi> &amp;c. witneſſeth.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Cruciferi</hi> or <hi>Crucigeri,</hi> vulgarly cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led.
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:46268:32"/>Crouched Friers, were firſt ſeen in <hi>England, Anno.</hi> 1244. having their firſt Monaſtery at <hi>Colcheſter;</hi> but are ſaid to be the Inſtitution of <hi>Cyriacus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> in memory of the Croſs which <hi>Helena,</hi> Mother to <hi>Conſtantine the Great,</hi> found by his directions; and therefore were enjoyned when they went abroad to carry a Croſs in their Hands. And in the year 1215. they were Reſtored or Confirmed by <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent</hi> the Third, Biſhop of <hi>Rome;</hi> or rather, as ſome believe, newly Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; and the reaſon they give is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the great Commotions raiſed in <hi>Rome,</hi> were ſuppreſſed by the <hi>Croyſados,</hi> or Army of Chriſtians, who had the Croſs for their Badge, and were then going for <hi>Syria,</hi> againſt the Infidels. This Order was ratified and confirmed by Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the Fourth, and Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> the Third, wearing a skie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colour'd Habit, by the appointment of Pope <hi>Pius</hi> the Second. <hi>Polydore</hi> makes ſome ſcruple to believe, That the <hi>Grucigeri</hi> are the ſame Order with thoſe we have mentioned, becauſe they wear black Cloaks, and carry, not in their Hands, but have fixed on their
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:46268:33"/>Breaſts, a Red and White Croſs, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve St. <hi>Auſtin</hi>'s Rules.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Hoſpitalers</hi> of the Holy Ghoſt took their beginning at <hi>Rome,</hi> about the Year of Chriſt 1201, and were cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Hoſpitalarii</hi> confirmed by Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the Third; having the privilege of the Monks that preceded them. Their chief buſineſs was to ſee the Poor and Sick were well lodged, attended, and carefully provided for; as like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to Bury them when they were dead, and uſe other charitable Offices to the ſame purpoſe.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Trinitarians,</hi> or Monks of the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the Trinity, began <hi>Anno</hi> 1211. and were Founded by <hi>John Manta,</hi> and <hi>Faelix Anachoreta,</hi> who its ſaid were warned in a Viſion to repair to <hi>Innocent</hi> the Third, and to require of him a place for their Order; and he warned by the like means of their coming, approved and confirmed them; cloathing them both in white Cloaks; giving them as a Badge, a red and skie-coloured Croſs upon their Breaſts, calling them Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the Holy Trinity, and Monks of the Redemption of Captives: Their charge being to Collect Money for
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:46268:33"/>the Redemption of ſuch as were ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Priſoners, and held in Bondage by the Infidels. The firſt coming into <hi>England</hi> of this Order was <hi>Anno</hi> 1357. two parts of whoſe Revenues were allowed for their Maintenance, a third for Redemption of Captives. By their Rule Three Clergy-men, and as many Lay-Brothers, were to dwell with one Procurator, who was to be called by the Name of Miniſter: They were to wear Garments of white Cloth, and lodge in Woollen, putting off their Breeches when they went to Bed: They might ride on Aſſes, but not on Horſes; Faſting is injoyned them, and not to eat Fleſh but on a <hi>Sunday,</hi> from <hi>Eaſter</hi> to <hi>Advent-Sunday,</hi> and from <hi>Chriſtmas</hi> to <hi>Septuageſima-Sunday;</hi> like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe on the Nativity, Epiphany, Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cention, Aſſumption, Purification, and on all Saints days; being further in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned to labour with their Hands; and every <hi>Sunday</hi> to hold a Chapter, or Aſſembly, for regulating their Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs in the Convent, and in the Octaves of <hi>Pentecoſt</hi> a General Chapter to be held every Year: As for their Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter he muſt be choſen by the Brothers
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:46268:34"/>in common conſent, being a Prieſt, every Convent having one over all, which muſt be owned Superior; nor muſt any be admitted into the Order till paſt the Age of Twenty, who muſt be ſhaven, though the Lay-men are allowed their Beards, and have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned them Rules for Civility, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinency, Love, Sobriety and other Chriſtian Virtues, according to the Rules of St. <hi>Baſil,</hi> St. <hi>Benet.</hi> and St. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtin,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Bethlemites</hi> are another Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, who came into <hi>England</hi> about the Year 1257. and had their abode near <hi>Cambridge,</hi> and ſoon after in it, and had a red Star on their Breaſt, like a Comet, in Commemoration of the Star that appeared to ſignifie the Birth of our Saviour to the Wiſe-men of the Eaſt: Their Apparel being compara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to that of the Dominicans, or Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicants, of which we ſhall hereafter ſpeak.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Dominicans</hi> were ſo called from the Founder of their Order, <hi>viz.</hi> one <hi>Dominicus</hi> a <hi>Spaniard;</hi> taking their ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal from the <hi>Humiliatii,</hi> and were <hi>Anno</hi> 1205, Inſtituted by <hi>Innocent</hi> the
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:46268:34"/>Third, Biſhop of <hi>Rome:</hi> The main de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of their Inſtitution being to Read, Preach, Write, and Expound the Word of <hi>God,</hi> which gives the occaſion of naming them Praedicants, or Praedicato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. As for the Founder of their Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, by the aforeſaid Biſhop of <hi>Rome, Anno</hi> 1207. he was joyned with Twelve Abbots of the Ciſtertian Order, to preach againſt the Doctrine of the <hi>Albi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genſes;</hi> and profeſſing the Rules of St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> with ſome addition, he had his Order confirmed by <hi>Honorius</hi> the Third, Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> dividing his Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery into Three parts; one he alot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted himſelf, and thoſe Brothers that were Contemplative; the ſecond for Contemplative Siſters, and the laſt for either Sex, if they were given to a ſtirring and active courſe of Life, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the denomination of <hi>Brothers and Siſters of Saint Dominick, or the Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> The Dominicans are bound to renounce worldly Riches; every Year to hold a General Chapter; to Faſt as much as poſſible, from <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly-Rood</hi> Day in <hi>September,</hi> till <hi>Eaſter;</hi> and at other times to eat no Fleſh on <hi>Fridays,</hi> unleſs in caſe of ſickneſs. As
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:46268:35"/>for their lying it is to be in Blankets; nor muſt they lye in Feather-Beds; ſilence is injoyned them, as likewiſe to wear a white Coat under a black Cloak. That they be ſatisfied with the Title of <hi>Friers Praedicants,</hi> to celebrate every <hi>Saturday</hi> the Office of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> unleſs in <hi>Lent,</hi> and on Feſtival Days; and that for the preaching the Goſpel, they diſperſe themſelves through all parts of the World, chooſing them a general Maſter, whoſe ſubordinate Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates ſhould be ſtiled Priors; <hi>Dominicus</hi> himſelf being the firſt Maſter-General, <hi>Anno</hi> 1220. but he enjoyed it not long, dying the next Year. As for the Praedicants they do not faithfully pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to live according to theſe Rules, but to live up to them as well as they can; and by their Preaching and Induſtry, they wonderfully ſpread themſelves in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to moſt parts of the World; inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that <hi>Sebelicus</hi> affirms, That in the Year of Chriſt 1494. there were Monaſteries of this Order, Four thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand one hundred forty three, in which were found One thouſand five hundred Maſters of Divinity, and One hundred and fifty Convents of Dominican Nuns;
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:46268:35"/>and the cauſe of this great increaſe, is thought to proceed from the good O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion the World had of <hi>Dominicus,</hi> who gave himſelf up to a ſtrict Life, and for which he was Canonized by <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory</hi> the Ninth, <hi>Anno</hi> 1233. and at this Day the Order is in high eſteem at <hi>Rome;</hi> and many Priviledges were conferred upon them, as to Preach in any Pulpit of a Roman Clergy-man without asking leave of the Eiſhop, to oblige Nobleman and Ladies to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs to them, and not to their Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates; to Adminiſter the Sacrament when they think ſit, and be utterly exempted from all Eccleſiaſtical Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures; and theſe were confirmed by Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the Fourth; not are any that have taken this Order to change it. And of theſe things teſtifie <hi>Anto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius, Vicentius, Theodoricus</hi> of <hi>Apolea</hi> in the Life of <hi>Dominicus, Matthew Paris, Crantzius,</hi> and others.</p>
               <p>The Mendicant Friers were of Four kinds, and amongſt them the Praedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cants (of whom we have ſpoken were recorded) the reſt were Auguſtinians, Carmelites, and Minorites; and of theſe in their Order.</p>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:46268:36"/>
               <p>As for the <hi>Auguſtinians,</hi> their firſt Founder was <hi>William</hi> Duke of <hi>Aqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain,</hi> about the year of Chriſt 1150. from whom they took the denomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of <hi>Guilebelimites,</hi> and were en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned by <hi>Innocent</hi> the Fourth to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low St. <hi>Auſtins</hi> Rule; and <hi>Alexander</hi> the Fourth reduced theſe and all other Eremites to the ſame Rule, being as Tradition goes warned ſo to do by St. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> who appeared to him and ſubjected them to a grand Prior, diſpenſing with their former Rules and Obſervations, enjoyning them to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake the Deſarts, and live in Cities, Towns, and Villages, there to teach the people, giving them divers privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, which were augmented by <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norius</hi> the Fourth, about the year 1290. Their Habit was a Black Coat with a Hood of the ſame colour, and under them a White ſhort Coat braced with a Leathern Girdle, and a Buckle of Horn, and came into <hi>England, Anno</hi> 1252. and in a ſhort time ſpread ſo faſt, that they were reckoned two thouſand Convents, profeſſing Poverty, Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, Faſting, praying, Meditating, Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty, Charity, Silence, and the like<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:46268:36"/>That their Rules be read once a Week, and obſerved not only by all the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons Regular, and Eremites of St. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtins</hi> Order, but by all Mendicants, except the Minors, as likewiſe by the Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cans and Servants of our Lady, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Monks or Eremites commonly called <hi>Carmelites,</hi> from Mount <hi>Carmel,</hi> from whence they begun or ſprung, were in the beginning a Striped Cloak, or Coat of party colour, in imitation of the Prophet <hi>Elijah,</hi> and ſpread them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves over <hi>Syria</hi> and <hi>Egypt,</hi> living very devout; but Pope <hi>Honorius</hi> the Third, not thinking it fit for a Religious Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, prohibited it, and gave them a White Cloak and Hood, with a Scapu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar of Hair-colour; the uſe of which Garments were confirmed by Pope <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholas,</hi> which ſo diſguſted the Sultan of <hi>Egypt,</hi> that he baniſhed them his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions. Theſe <hi>Honorius</hi> the Fourth call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Brothers of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empting them from the juriſdiction of Princes and Biſhops, and <hi>Gregory</hi> the Ninth enjoyned them not to ſeek Riches or Poſſeſſions, but to ſubſiſt by the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity they ſhould beg from Door to Door. By <hi>Alexander</hi> the Fourth they
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:46268:37"/>were allowed Priſons to puniſh ſuch as revolted, and <hi>John</hi> the Twenty third took them into his own protection; but in time neglecting their former ſtrictneſs, they divided into two Sects, one being called Obſervants, and the other Non-obſervants. In their Cloi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters many of them have the portrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt in the Habit of their Order, and the reaſon they give is, becauſe he was called <hi>Elijah,</hi> and they ſay <hi>Elijah</hi> did wear this Habit; but thoſe called Non-obſervants have changed their Hair-coloured Garments into Black.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Franciſcans,</hi> from which Order the <hi>Minorites</hi> ſprung, or were an inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of the Founder, took their Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal from <hi>Francis,</hi> a Native of <hi>Italy,</hi> who living extravagantly in his youthful days, at length left his Fathers Houſe with a great ſum of mony, with which, as it is ſaid, he repaired divers ruined Churches, and for which his Father caſt him in Priſon and diſinherited him; yet ſtriping himſelf of his Ornaments he greatly rejoyced, and in the end being releaſed from his Confinement, he gathered divers Religious Perſons as his
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:46268:37"/>Aſſociates and preſcribed them Rules, <hi>Anno</hi> 1198. <hi>viz.</hi> That they ſhall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſevere in Poverty, Chaſtity, and Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to Chriſt, the Pope, and their Superiors; that none enter that Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, till they be Examined and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. That in Divine Service the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy follow the Order of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church; and that the Lay-Brothers ſay twenty four <hi>Pater noſters</hi> for their Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tins, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and that they faſt, as much as may be, from <hi>All Saints</hi> till <hi>Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas,</hi> and that upon their coming to an Houſe they enter not till they ſay <hi>peace be to it,</hi> and then what is ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them they may eat: That they keep their vow of Poverty, not med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with Wealth: That they help each other, and that Penance be inflicted on thoſe that have tranſgreſſed: That they have Publick Meetings and Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and that they chuſe their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincial Miniſter over the Fraternity: That their Preachers be Learned men, not preaching abroad without leave of their Biſhop: That they uſe Brotherly Admonition and Correction, and that they give themſelves much to Prayer, Modeſty, Temperance, and the like
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:46268:38"/>commendable Virtues; and that none of them, unleſs authorized, enter into any Nunnery; and that none under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take to convert Inſidels, unleſs by the Permiſſion and Direction of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincial Miniſters: That they all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main ſtedfaſt in the Catholick Faith, not preſuming to tranſgreſs theſe Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders. This Rule or Order, St. <hi>Francis</hi> ſtrengthned by his Will and Teſtament, which he enjoyned to be read as often as the Rules were read, and theſe were confirmed by Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the Third, and again by <hi>Honorius</hi> the Third, and <hi>Nicholas</hi> the Third in his Decretal Epiſtles, which he enjoined to be read in Schools. This <hi>Francis</hi> declined the calling his Order <hi>Franciſcans</hi> by his Name but <hi>Minors,</hi> and ſo ordered the Maſters and Governors of his Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to be called Miniſters, putting them in mind of Humility, and of Chriſt's advice to his Diſciples.</p>
               <p>As for the Claſſes <hi>Francis</hi> divided his Diſciples into, they were three; the firſt was of the Fryers <hi>Minorites,</hi> himſelf being one of them; the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of whoſe life was very ſtrict and poor. The ſecond was of Ladies
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:46268:38"/>and poor Virgins, who taking their denomination from St. <hi>Clara,</hi> were call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Clariſſae,</hi> ſomewhat leſs ſtrict than the former. The third was that of Penitents, intended for Married peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, who were deſirous of Penance, yet permitted to enjoy Goods and Lands. The firſt of theſe were for Contemplation and Action; the ſecond only for Contemplation; and the third only for Action; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is not properly called a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Order. Theſe are called Fry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers <hi>Penitents</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt, and from their wearing Sackcloth, <hi>Saccii,</hi> and <hi>Continentes;</hi> becauſe that certain days in the Week, though married, they abſtained from carnal knowledge of their Wives. The Women of this rank were called Siſters <hi>Penitents,</hi> nor were the firſt Order to permit any of the third to enter their Churches in time of Interdict. This Order af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter its having been condemned in <hi>England Anno</hi> 1307. was again ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced by <hi>Peter Tuxbury</hi> a <hi>Franciſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can</hi> Miniſter, and allowed in the Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>London.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:46268:39"/>
               <p>Out of the <hi>Minorite</hi> Order ſprung many diſtinctions of the <hi>Obſervantes, Conventuales, Minimi, Capuciani, Colecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,</hi> or Collectors of mony, <hi>Amadeani Reformati de Evangelio, Chiachini cum Barba de Portiuncula Pulini Boſtaini Gau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentes de Auguſtinis,</hi> who wore open ſhews, and <hi>Servientes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As for <hi>Francis,</hi> he wore a ſhort Coat undied, and going bare-foot, uſed a Cord inſtead of a Girdle; from whence after his deceaſe, who dyed naked in external poverty, a long debate hapned what Garments ſhould be worn; which being propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to Pope <hi>John</hi> the Twenty ſecond, he referred it to the Arbitrament of their General and Provincial Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter; So that of late they wear a long Coat, a large Grey Hood or Hair-colour, the Coat girded with a Cord, going bare-footed, or in caſe of neceſſity with Sandals: Yet in this Order were ſome Schiſms, and the ſtrict Rules neglected or thwarted, and du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the vacancy of the Popedom, after the deceaſe of <hi>Clement</hi> the Fifth, for almoſt the ſpace of two years, theſe Monks rejected their Habit, and choſe
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:46268:39"/>their own Governor or Maſter, wear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a ſhort Garment; Excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and Impriſoning the Obedient; but afterward a better underſtanding was had, and <hi>Gregory</hi> the Eleventh, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited the power of the <hi>Minorites</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tectors, That none ſhould be under their Cenſure, but thoſe that diſobeyed the Pope and the Church, that apoſtatize from the Faith, and renounce the Rule. And <hi>Honorius.</hi> the Third decreed, that not one of them ſhould change or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake his Order; and they obtained the favour that they might Commence or make Maſters of Divinity amongſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Franciſcan</hi> Order ſoon ſpread it ſelf in all parts; inſomuch that from <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no</hi> 1211. till the year 1380. as <hi>Sebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus</hi> affirmeth, 1500. Monaſteries of this Order were erected in Chriſtendom, and in his time were reputed to be 90000. <hi>Minorites.</hi> And thus much of theſe Orders, from whence we proceed to thoſe of leſſer Note or Antiquity.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:46268:40"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> A Brief Account of divers Orders, and Inſtitutions of either Sex, as the <hi>Clariſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſae,</hi> Eremites of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> Monks of St. <hi>Mary, Celeſtini Jeſuati;</hi> the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of St. <hi>Bridget,</hi> and that of St. <hi>Katharine;</hi> Canons Regular of St. Saviour, and of St. <hi>George Albati,</hi> with many others.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>CLara</hi> was the Daughter of <hi>Ortubana,</hi> born in the Town of <hi>Aſſiſium</hi> in — who from her Infancy, in a manner, was wonderfully given to Devotion, and deſirous to lead a Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Life; ſo that as ſoon as ſhe was able, ſhe undertook two tedious Pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages, one to <hi>Rome,</hi> and the other to viſit the Holy Sepulchre at <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> and ſtole from her Parents (who would have reſtrained it) that ſhe might cut off her Hair, nor by any perſwaſion
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:46268:40"/>could ſhe be brought to renounce her intended courſe of Life: but about the year 1215. She inſtituted at the Church of St. <hi>Damianus,</hi> the Order of the poor Ladies and Virgins, called from her <hi>Clariſſae,</hi> and from that place were ſometimes called Nuns of St. <hi>Damian;</hi> and in a Cottage near to this place lived ſhe 4.2. years, afflicting her ſelf with Watching, Faſting, and all manner of hardſhip, lying on Boards, and wear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing next her fleſh the hairy ſide of a Hogs skin, going bare-foot, and in <hi>Lent,</hi> and on other faſting days, ſubſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on Bread and Water, not taſting Wine but on the Sunday, giving as her Rule that of the <hi>Franciſcans,</hi> and had her Order confirmed by <hi>Innocent</hi> the Third, or as ſome will have it, <hi>Honorius</hi> the Third; nor by Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> could ſhe be perſwaded to reſerve any of her Poſſeſſions, but lived and died in Poverty and was Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonized.</p>
               <p>The Eremites of St. <hi>Paul</hi> were <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no</hi> 1215. Inſtituted in <hi>Hungary</hi> after the Rules of St. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> by one <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſebius</hi> of <hi>Strigonium,</hi> and by <hi>Gentilis</hi> the Popes Legate, confirmed <hi>Anno</hi> 1308.
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:46268:41"/>and ſeated themſelves at <hi>Colcheſter</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> about the year 1310.</p>
               <p>The Order called <hi>Boni Homines,</hi> or <hi>Boni Viri,</hi> Good Men, was inſtituted by <hi>Edmund,</hi> Son to <hi>Richard</hi> Earl of <hi>Cornwal,</hi> who had been elected Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror of <hi>Germany,</hi> or the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire, and wore a Skie-coloured Garment, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing St. <hi>Auguſtine's Rules.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Monks or Servants of St. <hi>Mary</hi> were Inſtituted by <hi>Philip Tuder,</hi> a <hi>Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentine,</hi> after St. <hi>Auſtin</hi>'s Rules; the Garment or Habit of this Order, was a Black Cloak plaited about the Shoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and under it a ſhort Coat, and was confirmed by <hi>Benet,</hi> the Eleventh Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> and by ſeven other Popes or Biſhops ſucceeding him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing permitted to carry a Satchel or Bag to gather Almes, which in <hi>Italy</hi> they beg: The Inſtitution of this Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der was <hi>Anno</hi> 1282. or as ſome will have it 1285.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Celeſtini</hi> were ſo named from <hi>Celeſtine</hi> the Firſt, Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> who before his advancement lived as an Eremite in ſundry Deſarts, and erected this Order, enjoining the Monks St. <hi>Bennet</hi>'s Rules, procuring them to
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:46268:41"/>be confirmed by Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> the Tenth, in the General Council of <hi>Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> ordaining their Habit to be of Sky-colour without a Hood. Theſe Monks came into <hi>England,</hi> 1414.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Jeſuati</hi> was an Order that began at <hi>Senae,</hi> and founded by <hi>John Columbanus,</hi> and <hi>Francis Vincent,</hi> in the year 1365. and were ſo called from their often uſing the Name of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> who being ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved by Pope <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rban</hi> the Fifth, he appointed them to wear White Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, a White Cover for their Heads, a Leathern Girdle, and to go bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>footed, with only wooden bottoms tyed about their Feet, and for their plainneſs of life and ſincerity were af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward called <hi>Apoſtolici.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Order of St. <hi>Bridger,</hi> both Monks and Nuns were inſtituted by a Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of <hi>Sweden</hi> of that Name, <hi>Anno</hi> 1360. who obtained a confirmation of her Order from Pope <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rban</hi> the Fifth, according to St. <hi>Baſil</hi>'s Rules in the general, though with ſome additions: The Monks and Nuns of this Order, are not debarred their Religious Houſes to be far ſeparated the one from the other, and to be preſent
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:46268:42"/>at one and the ſame Church. As for the Brothers it is their buſineſs, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to injunction, to officiate below, while the Siſters do the like above: As for the Cloathing of both Sex, Crey was enjoyned, <hi>viz.</hi> a Cloak-Coat and a Red Croſs thereon. As to Suſtenance or that wherewith they ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted, it ought to be common amongſt them, and their Lodging to be on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly on Straw. The Nuns were en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joined to wear on their Veil, a White Linnen Crown ſpotted or ſtreaked with Red Cloth imitating drops of Blood, and ſo placed that they may appear like a Croſs. As for the Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters they are directed what Prayers to uſe every day; enjoyned ſilence and to avoid conferring with men, except upon urgent occaſions, and that through a Window, but ſhe who opens not her Window at all has the moſt praiſe. As for their Conſecration, it is from the Biſhop, and their Confeſſion through a Lattice, where they may be heard, but not ſeen, unleſs upon receiving the Sacrament. When any one enters the Convent ſhe has her Coffin carried before her by four
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:46268:42"/>Siſters, and in the Convent is a Grave to put them in mind of their mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality; as for their Devotion it is enjoined very ſtrict, as likewiſe are all the other matters relating to the Order. More of which you may ſee in <hi>Antonius, Trithemius, Balaeus, Nau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clerus,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The Order of St. <hi>Katharine</hi> is accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Rules of <hi>Dominicus;</hi> the ſtory going, That ſhe ſaw him with the Founders of divers other Orders in a Dream, and he having a Lilly in his hand, bid her undertake ſome of their Orders, which made her chooſe his. She was born at <hi>Sena</hi> in <hi>Tuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cany,</hi> and vowed Virginity in her Childhood; and after ſhe profeſſed this Order drank only Water, and eat Bread and Herbs, lying in her Clothes upon the Boards, and afflicting her ſelf with an Iron Chain, watching often, and giving her ſelf much to Devotion, chaſtizing her ſelf for her own ſins, for the Dead, and for thoſe that were Alive. The Nuns of St. <hi>Katharine's</hi> Order wore Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of White, caſt over with a Blcak Veil and Head Covering, and is
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:46268:43"/>held to begin <hi>Anno</hi> 1372. or as ſome will have it 1455.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lodovicus Barbus,</hi> a <hi>Venetian,</hi> inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted the Order of <hi>Justinian,</hi> in the year 1409. after the Rule of S. <hi>Benet,</hi> which was by <hi>Eugenius</hi> the Fourth, Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> inlarged, and by <hi>John</hi> the Twenty fourth, Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> confirmed. As for the Monks of this Order they lived very ſtrictly, never eating out of their Convent with Lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, unleſs great neceſſity urged it; and being very charitable to ſtrangers, they often waſhed their Feet, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> As witneſs <hi>Hoſpinian, Polidore Virgil, Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſcus, Modius, Antonius,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The Eremites of the Order of St. <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rom</hi> were enjoyned the Rule of St. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin,</hi> being inſtituted in <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rbinum,</hi> a City of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>mbria</hi> in <hi>Italy,</hi> about the year 1366. during the Papacy of Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> the Ninth, and by <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory</hi> the Twelfth confirmed; and there were of this Order in <hi>Italy</hi> twenty five Convents, and are little different in Habit and other matters from St. <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rom's</hi> Monks, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Canons of St. <hi>Saviour</hi> had their beginning in <hi>Italy,</hi> at a place called
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:46268:43"/>
                  <hi>Seopetum,</hi> whence they took the deno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of <hi>Scopetines,</hi> and follow the Rules of St. <hi>Auſtin:</hi> Their firſt Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution was by <hi>Francis</hi> of <hi>Bononia,</hi> in the Year 1366. during the Papacy of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rban</hi> the Fifth, and were by <hi>Gregory</hi> the Eleveth confirmed, in the Year 1370. wearing a white Cloak and Hood, under the Cloak a Linnen Veſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Abbati</hi> took their Denomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from the white Linnen Veſtments they wore. This Order, in the time of Pope <hi>Boniface</hi> the Ninth, deſcended the <hi>Alpes</hi> into <hi>Luca, Flaminea, Hetru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria, Piſa,</hi> and other <hi>Italian</hi> Countries. Their principal Prieſt, or Conductor being clothed in White, and carrying a Crucifix in his Hand, made a more than ordinary pretence to ſtrictneſs in Religion; weeping for the Sins and Calamities of the Times, eating toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in High-ways, and lying promiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuouſly; and they increaſed ſo faſt, that Pope <hi>Boniface</hi> the Ninth, growing jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous that their Prieſt aimed at the Popedom, apprehended him and put him to death; whereupon his Followers diſperſed themſelves; but theſe, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:46268:44"/>with the Fratricelli and Turlupini, being by many termed Broachers of Heritical Opinions, and ſcarce to be ranked amongſt Religious Orders, I ſhall for brevities ſake paſs them o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Montolivetenſes,</hi> or Monks of <hi>Mount Olivet,</hi> had their beginning 1407. betaking themſelves to a Hill which they called <hi>Mount Olivet,</hi> profeſſed St. <hi>Bennet</hi>'s Rules, and clothed themſelves in white Garments, getting their Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to be confirmed by Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> the Twelfth; and before theſe there were ſeveral of the ſaid Denominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but Pope <hi>Boniface</hi> the Eighth diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>annull'd them, as witneſſes <hi>Fran. Sebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus,</hi> and others.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Canons Regular</hi> of St. <hi>George,</hi> by ſome called <hi>Apoſtolici,</hi> were Found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by <hi>Lawrence Juſtinian,</hi> Patriarch of <hi>Venice,</hi> in the year 1407. Their Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der was confirmed by <hi>Gregory</hi> the Twelfth; their Habit was a Linnen Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plice over their other Cloaths, and a black Hood; but being out of the Cloiſter, they wore a black Cloak and Hat: And of theſe were Two other Orders, the one wearing Blew, and
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:46268:44"/>the other White; and except in time of ſickneſs, they abſtained from Fleſh, nor were they by any Vow tied to the Rules of their Profeſſion.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Mendicants</hi> of St. <hi>Hierom</hi> were inſtituted <hi>Anno</hi> 1407. by <hi>Charles Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentine;</hi> and Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> the Twelfth confirmed their Rule according to that of St. <hi>Auſtin:</hi> As for their Garments they are of a dark coloured Cloth, wearing a plaited Cloak uppermoſt, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving likewiſe a Leathern Girdle and Wooden Shoes.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Canons of Lateran</hi> ſeem to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive their original from St. <hi>Auſtin;</hi> theſe by Pope <hi>Calixtus</hi> were expulſed with Saint <hi>John Lateran,</hi> but were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain ſeated there by Pope <hi>Paul</hi> the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond; their Hoods, Scapulars, and Cloaks are black.</p>
               <p>The Monks of the Order of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> were, <hi>Anno</hi> 1407. Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by <hi>Gabriel</hi> of <hi>Spoletum,</hi> at <hi>Venice;</hi> uſing the like Habit as the Canons Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular.</p>
               <p>The Brothers of St. <hi>Ambroſe ad Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi> had their inſtitution at <hi>Millan;</hi> and were Confirmed <hi>Anno</hi> 1433. pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing St. <hi>Auſtin</hi>'s Rules, and wearing dark-coloured Cloaths.</p>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:46268:45"/>
               <p>The <hi>Minimi</hi> of <hi>Jeſu Maria,</hi> were the Inſtitution of <hi>Francis Paula,</hi> a <hi>Sicilian, Anno</hi> 1471. who made Three Rules, one for the Brothers, another for the Siſters, and the third injoyned to both Sexes. They were injoyned to obſerve the Ten Commandments and the Church Laws, to be obedient to the Pope, to perſevere in their Vows of Poverty, Chaſtity, and Obedience, as alſo to Faſt: This was allowed by <hi>Jalius</hi> the Second, <hi>Innocent</hi> the Eighth, <hi>Alexander</hi> the Sixth, <hi>Sixtus</hi> the fourth, and <hi>Leo</hi> the Tenth; they altogether abſtaining from Fleſh, wandring up and down in courſe Linnen, bare-footed and bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed: more of which you may ſee in <hi>Surius, Tom.</hi> 2. <hi>de vit. Sanct.</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>In the Year 1500. came out of <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many</hi> a ſort of people, who ſtiled them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves <hi>Poor Pilgrims,</hi> bare-headed and bare-footed, clad in Linnen, or grey Cloth, having a Wooden Croſs in their Hands, drinking neither Beer nor Wine; their Food all the Week, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept <hi>Sunday,</hi> being Herbs ſeaſoned with Salt, altogether abſtaining from Fleſh, Fiſh, Milk, Butter, Cheeſe, and Eggs; ſtretching their Arms out
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:46268:45"/>in Churches croſs-wiſe, in imitation of a Croſs; and in Prayer fell flat on the ground; no where ſtaying above the ſpace of Twenty hours at once, going from door to door begging by couples: And amongſt them were divers Prieſts, Deacons, and Sub-Deacons; which Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance they voluntarily undertook, for what number of Years they thought convenient, and the ſet time expired, they returned home to follow their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Imployments; and only excluded from their Pilgrimage Women and Monks.</p>
               <p>The Order of <hi>Indians</hi> were Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the time of Pope <hi>Julius</hi> the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond; being of the Carmelite Race; and are thought to be called <hi>Indians,</hi> for that they intended to Convert the <hi>Indians</hi> to the Chriſtian Faith; the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dias</hi> being about that time diſcovered: As for their Garments they wore a black Cloak over a white Gown.</p>
               <p>The Society of <hi>Divine Love,</hi> was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed of a People that met in obſcure and remote places with much Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, where they Prayed, ſung Pſalms, and Adminiſtred the Sacrament; and were called <hi>Theatini,</hi> from the Biſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:46268:46"/>of <hi>Theatinum,</hi> which was rejected by <hi>John Peter Caraſſa,</hi> that with leſs trouble and incumbrance he might profeſs a devout Life, and give him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf up more ſeriouſly to Contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the ſtudy of Divine Myſteries; nor would he accept of the Biſhoprick of <hi>Brunduſium,</hi> which <hi>Charles</hi> the Fifth <hi>Roman</hi> Emperor, would have conferred upon him, and Inſtituted his Order un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Pope <hi>Clement</hi> the Seventh: This Man was afterward made Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> by the Name of <hi>Paul</hi> the Fourth, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Order of <hi>Paulini</hi> was Inſtituted by a Noble Matron, called <hi>Gaſtalia, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no</hi> 1537. at <hi>Mantua,</hi> whence thoſe of the Order were ſometimes called <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtalini;</hi> and their chief buſineſs was to mortifie the Concupiſcence and Luſts of the Fleſh: But for ſome Inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences that accrued by ſuch Temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons as they gave themſelves up to, the Order was, not long after its In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, extinguiſhed or ſuppreſſed.</p>
               <p>Thus have we brieſly run through moſt of the Religious Orders that held of, or were confirmed by the See of <hi>Rome.</hi> Some there are that yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:46268:46"/>which being rather Military than Eccleſiaſtical Orders, I ſhall ſay ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of them and their Founders in due place; and conclude the Religious Orders with that of the Jeſuits, or thoſe of the Society of Jeſus, Founded by <hi>Ignatius Loyola.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <pb n="80" facs="tcp:46268:47"/>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> A Deſcription of the <hi>Society of Jeſus,</hi> or the Order of the Jeſuits, in what relates to their Inſtitution, Confirmation General Rules and Offices; being a brief Abſtract of a Book publiſhed by the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periors of the Order, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE Order Called the <hi>Society of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> ſo much talked of through the Chriſtian World, was Inſtituted about the Year 1540. by <hi>Ignatius Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ola,</hi> a Native of <hi>Cantabria;</hi> who ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been a Souldier, and received ſome Wounds in the <hi>French</hi> Wars, they occaſioned a years ſickneſs or more, which made him ſo ſenſible of his own Infirmites, that he reſolved upon his Recovery to renounce the World, and devote himſelf to the advancing the Name of Jeſus; and accordingly in the Twenty ſixth Year of his Age tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velled to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> where having paid his Devotion at the Holy Sepulchre,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:46268:47"/>he returned to <hi>Spain,</hi> and gave himſelf to Study at <hi>Complutum</hi> and <hi>Salamanca,</hi> preaching Mortification by his Doctrine and Poorneſs of Habit; and from thence going to <hi>Paris,</hi> where he ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>died Ten Years, he was made Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of Arts, and in the Year 1536. came again into <hi>Spain,</hi> with Ten Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, who had undertaken to follow his directions; and ſo to <hi>Rome</hi> to get leave of the Pope to travel to <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem.</hi> But the Peace being broken be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the <hi>Venetians</hi> and <hi>Turks,</hi> they held it not ſafe; but choſe to go to <hi>Venice,</hi> and there (as occaſion required) to dreſs the Wounds of Poor Perſons, and look after the Sick, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Seven of his Companions, undertook to preach about the Territories of <hi>Venice,</hi> though they had nothing to ſubliſt on but Charity; and by this time being bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter improved, they again returned to <hi>Rome,</hi> where the Clergy moleſted and oppoſed their proceedings; yet they increaſed, and by applying themſelves to Pope <hi>Paul</hi> the Third, had their Order confirmed, and ſince ratified by <hi>Julius</hi> the Third, <hi>Paul</hi> the Fourth, <hi>Pius</hi> the Fourth, and the <hi>Council of Trent;</hi>
                  <pb n="82" facs="tcp:46268:48"/>being injoyned at firſt not to have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove <hi>Sixty</hi> of the Society, but after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward that Limitation was diſannulled, permitting all that were capable to become Members of the Society, if they could be admitted by the Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors. Their Chief or General of the Order they have, who commonly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides at <hi>Rome:</hi> Likewiſe their Coadju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors in Spiritual Things; ſuch as are their Prieſts, Profeſſors of Divinity, Philoſophy, and Inferior Arts and Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences: Their Coadjutors alſo in Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porals, whoſe buſineſs it is to have a regard to their Cloaths, Dict, and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſtick Affairs; and for the better ſupply of their Order, maintain their Scholars and Novices, who without diſputing what is injoyned, are bound to obey their Superiors. This Order differs from others, for that beſide the three uſual Vows of Poverty, Chaſtity and Obedience, they bind themſelves to the Pope readily and chearfully, to undertake whatever he gives them in charge, without being chargeable to him; nor muſt they refuſe any jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney he ſhall injoyn them for, the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagation of the Roman Catholick Faith:
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:46268:48"/>Amongſt them the Title of Profeſſer is in higher eſteem than that of Prieſt, the latter being frequently obtained long before the former. Inſtead of a Hood they wear a Philoſophical Cloak long and black, their Cap is called <hi>Bareta,</hi> reſembling a Croſs, which they do not wear abroad; their Caſſocks are called <hi>Solannas,</hi> tied about them with ſilken Girdles: And ſo faſt they ſpread, That about Sixty or Seventy Years ſince, they had Two hundred fifty ſix Colleges, beſides Houſes: More of which you may ſee in <hi>Chriſtianus Franken, in Coloqu. Jeſuit,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Surius Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpinian,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The general Rules of this Order are twice a day to examine their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, to be diligent in Meditation, Prayer, Reading, and daily to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent at the Divine Service, at the times appointed to Confeſs their Sins, twice every Year to renew their Vows, and on <hi>Fridays</hi> to be abſtinent, without the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periors leave not to Preach; that they keep no Money by them, nor have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny valuable matter in Property; not to read any Book without leave, nor to meddle with any thing that is not
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:46268:49"/>their own; to learn the Language of the Country where they are, and not keep their-Chamber-door or Cheſts un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Lock and Key, nor in the night to ſleep with their Windows open, or go Naked, nor to go out of their Chambers without their Clothes, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to teach or learn without their Superiors leave, nor to drink between meals, nor to eat abroad without the like leave, which muſt alſo be had for their taking Phyſick, or conſulting a Phyſitian: They muſt obſerve the Ring of the Bell, keeping their Chambers neat, and their Beds clean; and when they find themſelves under any great tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to acquaint their Superiors there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with: They muſt be Obedient, Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and Reſpective to their Superiors, uncovering their Head when they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach; not to complain of one Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior to another: To keep ſilence, or briefly to ſpeak to the purpoſe, with Submiſſion and Moderation; to avoid Contradiction, Contention, and ſpeaking evil of each other, or their Countries, he being only to reprove who is Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorized ſo to do. Whilſt two are in a Chamber let the Door ſtand open:
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:46268:49"/>Let no man at the Table put off his Hat unleſs to his Superiors, nor talk with Strangers, or have converſation with them by Letters without leave; report idle Tales, or tell abroad what is done at home they muſt not; nor without leave meddle with Secular af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs; nor write any thing of Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction or Conſolation; every one is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired to inſtruct his Brother to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, as likewiſe exhort him to it. Without leave none muſt go abroad, and when he does, he muſt ſhew the reaſon, and upon his return give an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the effect it took; ever ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving to write down his name, and to acquaint the Porter whither he goes; and muſt return before night, unleſs he has leave to travel, and then he muſt lodge in Jeſuits a Colledge, if any offer in the way, and there to be as obedient to the Superior as to his own. As for theſe Rules, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> they muſt every one have them in being, that once a month they may read them, or hear them read; but the Co-adjutors are bound to read their Rules every week. Their Conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons likewiſe they have, wherein is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:46268:50"/>that the main end of their Society is to do good to their own Souls, and thoſe of their Neighbours, and Relations; wherefore they are bound to travel up and down, and every ſix months to confeſs their ſins to the Prieſt; then to receive the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, and caſt off all inordinate af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of Kindred, Friends, and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral matters; to deny themſelves, to ſtudy humility, to take up the Croſs of Chriſt and follow him; to aim at Perfection and all other Virtues, but chiefly at Charity; to be careful of the inward man; to embrace Poverty with alacrity; to diſpence freely their Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual gifts, as they have freely recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved them; to ſtudy Chaſtity, Purity, and to be watchful over their Senſes, but eſpecially their Eyes and Tongues: To be temperate, decent, and modeſt, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally at the Table; not in any thing to diſobey the Superiors command, nor to conceal any thing in Confeſſion; to ſtudy Unity and Conformity in judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, in affections; to avoid idleneſs, and Secular aſtairs; to avoid all exceſs that may impair health, and rather uſe what means he can to preſerve
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:46268:50"/>it; to intreat the Superior that once a year he would enjoin a Penance for the paſt failings, in not duly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving their Rules and Conſtitutions as they ought.</p>
               <p>Theſe are their Rules in general, according to their Book of Rules and Inſtitutes, Printed at <hi>Lyons</hi> in <hi>France, Anno</hi> 1607. But to come nearer to particulars, there are divers others ſet forth in the ſame Book: As the Conſtitutions and Rules of Provinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als, Rules for Provoſts, Rectors of Colledges, and the Examiner, Rules for the Maſters of the Novices, and their Councellors, Rules for Trave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors, Rules for their Miniſter or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troler, for the Admonitor, the Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeer of the Church; Prieſts their Rules, Rules for Preachers, the General Proctor his Rules, Readers their Rules, as alſo for the <hi>Infirmarius Librarii,</hi> as they are ſet down in their Book, for the better inſtruction of every Officer and Member of the Society; which Book, by the Order of the Superiors, was Printed in the Year and Place before mentioned; to which for brevities ſake the inquiſitive Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:46268:51"/>is referred. As for the Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges and Immunities granted them by ſeveral Popes, they are very great, and have been very much Improved.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:46268:51"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> A Deſcription of the ſeveral Military Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, or Orders of Knighthood in moſt Chriſtian Kingdoms, Provinces, and Countries, as they have been, and are at this day found, with their Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Confirmation, Rules, Habit, and Collars or Badges of their reſpective Orders: To what end they were Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and by what Kings, Princes, No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble-men and Prelates they were Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged and Confirmed; with the Decay of ſome, and Riſe of others, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe enſuing Orders being rather looked upon as Military ones, than confined to the ſtrictneſs of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Worſhip, we ſhall but lightly mention them; yet that the Reader may be benefited thereby, eſpecially in reading of Hiſtory, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:46268:52"/>
               <p>The Knights <hi>Hoſpitalers,</hi> or Knights of the Order of St. <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> firſt obtained leave to build a Monaſtery at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> of the Calypha of <hi>Egypt,</hi> which they dedicated to the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> and employed themſelves in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending Pilgrims; as alſo in entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and relieving them in Hoſpitals and Houſes built for them, ſquaring their matters as to Devotion, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to St. <hi>Auguſtines</hi> Rules; and ſo well behaved themſelves, upon the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans taking <hi>Jeruſalem, Anno</hi> 1099. that they were held in high eſteem with <hi>Godfrey</hi> of <hi>Bulloigne,</hi> and other Kings; ſtoutly defending with their Swords the Chriſtian Religion, till the Princes of the <hi>Weſt</hi> failing, by reaſon of their own inteſtine Diſcords, to ſend them ſuccour, they were by the Infidels quite beaten out of <hi>Syria, Anno</hi> 1308. at what time, with a great Fleet they invaded <hi>Rhodes,</hi> took it from the Turks, and maintained it 214. years, but loſt it in the Reign of <hi>Solyman</hi> the Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificent, after a bloody ſix months ſiege, from whence they were called the Knights of <hi>Rhodes,</hi> but ſince the Knights of <hi>Malta;</hi> which place their
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:46268:52"/>Poſterity at this day poſſeſs and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend againſt all oppoſition, Governed by a great Maſter, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Order of the Knights <hi>Templers</hi> was founded by <hi>Hugo de Paganis,</hi> and <hi>Gufrid de St. Aidemaro,</hi> who with their followers undertook to ſecure the Roads, for the ſake of Pilgrims, from all Robbery and Outrages; and from their being aſſigned a reſidence near the Temple in <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> by King <hi>Bald<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>win,</hi> were from thence called <hi>Templers,</hi> and did great ſervice under the lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of their Great Maſter againſt the Infidels in the Holy War; but having loſt <hi>Syria,</hi> upon their return into <hi>Europe,</hi> they were hardly treated, and the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der quite extinguiſhed; as for their manner of Religious Obſervance, it was much according to the Rule of the Canons Regular.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Teutonick</hi> Order was Inſtituted or Erected before the Walls of <hi>Prolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mais,</hi> by the King of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> in the preſence of divers Princes and Prelates, who approved it, and was confirmed by the Emperor <hi>Henry</hi> the Sixth, and Pope <hi>Celeſtine</hi> the Third, and enjoined St. <hi>Auſtin</hi>'s Rules: They were alſo called
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:46268:53"/>
                  <hi>Marinii</hi> or Knights of St. <hi>Mary,</hi> and did great ſervice in the Holy War, and ſince that time upon ſundry occaſions, under their Superiors or Great Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, being moſtly <hi>Germans</hi> and <hi>Polo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians</hi> that are admitted into it, and at this day are very Powerful and Rich, having many Lands and Poſſeſſions.</p>
               <p>The Order of the Knights of St. <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarus</hi> were Inſtituted, <hi>Anno</hi> 1119. but being almoſt extinct, Pope <hi>Pius</hi> the Fourth renewed them. The Habit of this Order is a dark-coloured Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, with a Red Croſs on their Breaſts, and were alſo Inſtituted the Knights of the <hi>Annunciada,</hi> in memory of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuntiation of the Bleſſed Virgin, and held an Annual Feaſt on her day.</p>
               <p>The Knights of <hi>Calatrava,</hi> who took their Denomination from a Town of that Name in <hi>Spain,</hi> were Inſtituted by <hi>Sanctius,</hi> or as ſome will have it, <hi>Alphonſo</hi> King of <hi>Spain,</hi> in the year 1121. or as others ſay, 1160. who being of the <hi>Ciſtertian</hi> Order, undertook to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the Frontries againſt the Incurſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Turks and Saracens, which the <hi>Templers</hi> were too weak to do, and live very ſtrict in the obſervance
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:46268:53"/>of their Rules; and had many Fovours conferred upon them by Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the Third.</p>
               <p>The Knights of St. <hi>James</hi> in <hi>Spain,</hi> had their Inſtitution from Pope <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> the Third, who confirmed them, and enjoyned them the Rules of St. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin;</hi> whoſe firſt grand Maſter was <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Ferdinand,</hi> who for the ſupport of himſelf and his Order, had yearly 150000. Crowns, being Inſtituted, <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no</hi> 1170. the Great Maſter taking place next the Blood Royal; wearing in Peace and War a Purple Croſs on their Breaſts, reſembling a Two Handed Sword Han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, called <hi>Spatha,</hi> whence the Knights of the Order are called <hi>Sancti Milites Jacobi de Spatha,</hi> and from <hi>Compoſtella, Compoſtellanos.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Knights of the <hi>Holy Sepulchre</hi> were likewiſe called Knights of the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of St. <hi>James;</hi> their buſineſs being to guard the Sepulchre: But when the Chriſtians loſt footing in <hi>Syria</hi> it expi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, their Charge being given by the <hi>Soldan</hi> to the <hi>Franciſcans</hi> that were found in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The Order of the <hi>Gladiators</hi> began in <hi>Livonia, Anno</hi> 1204. and were ſo
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:46268:54"/>called for carrying on their Cloak two Red Swords a-croſs; their Inſtitutor was <hi>Albert,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Riga,</hi> who gave to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards their Maintenance the third part of his Church Revenues; their Habit, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs the two Bloody Swords worn there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, was White, to ſhew their Innocence and Reſolution to maintain war againſt the Enemies of the Croſs of Chriſt, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting many Unbelievers to Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, not only in <hi>Riga,</hi> but in other places of <hi>Livonia;</hi> for which good ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> aſſigned them what Lands in thoſe parts they ſhould win from the Infidels. But in the end by the Popes perſwaſion, both this, and the Order of the <hi>Cruciferi,</hi> became one in conjunction with the Teutonick Order: To ſee which more at large, read <hi>Crantzi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, l.</hi> 7. <hi>Funcius, l.</hi> 10. <hi>Munſter</hi> in his Geography, <hi>Balaeus,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The Knights of St. Mary <hi>de Mercede</hi> or Redemption, were Inſtituted by King <hi>James</hi> of <hi>Aragon,</hi> who in the year 1212. ſubdued the Iſles of <hi>Baleares,</hi> and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led this Order about the year 1232. which was confirmed by Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> the Ninth; their buſineſs was chiefly to redeem Chriſtian Captives taken by the
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:46268:54"/>Infidels: Their Garments were White, with a Black Croſs, and profeſſed the Rules of the <hi>Ciſtertian</hi> Order.</p>
               <p>The Knights of <hi>Monteſia</hi> were Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the ſame King of <hi>Aragon,</hi> and confirmed by Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> the Ninth, and were ſo called from a place in <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentia;</hi> the Badge of their Order being a Red Croſs, and hold the <hi>Ciſtertian</hi> Rules.</p>
               <p>The Knights of St. <hi>Maurice</hi> were In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted by <hi>Amadeus</hi> the Seventh, Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> in honour of St. <hi>Maurice, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no</hi> 1490.</p>
               <p>The Order of the Golden Fleece was inſtituted by <hi>Philip</hi> the Good, Duke of <hi>Burgundy,</hi> and Father to <hi>Charles</hi> whom the <hi>Switzers</hi> overcame and ſlew; he In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituting it on his Wedding day with <hi>Iſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel,</hi> Daughter to the King of <hi>Portugal,</hi> in memory of <hi>Jaſon</hi>'s fetching the Gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Fleece, as ſome will have it.</p>
               <p>The Order of the <hi>Moon</hi> was Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by <hi>Reiner,</hi> Duke of <hi>Anjou,</hi> upon his obtaining the Kingdom of <hi>Sicily, Anno</hi> 1464. and as a Badge the Knights wear a Silver Half-Moon on their Arms, and were in all dangers bound to ſtand by, and defend each other, not at any time
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:46268:55"/>preſuming to fall at variance amongſt themſelves.</p>
               <p>The Knights of St. <hi>Michael</hi> the Arch-Angel, were Inſtituted by <hi>Lewis</hi> the French King, <hi>Anno</hi> 1469. The Badge of their Order being a Gold Chain, at which hangs the Image of St. <hi>Michael,</hi> trampling on the Infernal Dragon; and of this Order he appointed 36. Knights, himſelf to be the Chief.</p>
               <p>The Knights of St. <hi>Stephen,</hi> were the Inſtitution of <hi>Coſmo,</hi> Duke of <hi>Florence,</hi> and were confirmed <hi>Anno</hi> 1561. by Pope <hi>Pius</hi> the Fourth, wearing Red Croſſes ſet in Gold; their Seat is in <hi>Ilua,</hi> an Iſle of the <hi>Liguſtick</hi> Sea, and were Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted in imitation of the Knights of <hi>Malta,</hi> taking their Denomination from <hi>Stephen,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Florence,</hi> or as ſome are of Opinion, from <hi>Stephen,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Knights of the <hi>Holy Spirit,</hi> were Inſtituted by <hi>Henry,</hi> the French King, <hi>Anno</hi> 1579.</p>
               <p>The Knights of St. <hi>George</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> were Inſtituted by King <hi>Edward</hi> the Third, commonly called Knights of the Garter.</p>
               <p>The Knights of the <hi>Star,</hi> were Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:46268:55"/>by King <hi>John</hi> the Firſt of <hi>France,</hi> in memory of the Star that guided the Eaſtern Magi to the place where Chriſt was born.</p>
               <p>The Knights of the <hi>Genets,</hi> held to be the firſt Order of Knighthood in <hi>France,</hi> was inſtituted by <hi>Charles Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel,</hi> in memory of the ſignal Victory he obtained over <hi>Abdiramo,</hi> in whoſe Camp he found many of thoſe Creatures, whoſe skins are excellent Furrs.</p>
               <p>The Order of the <hi>Crown Royal,</hi> was In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted by <hi>Charles</hi> the Great, in honour of the <hi>Friſons,</hi> who had done him great ſervice in his wars again the <hi>Seſnes,</hi> or antient <hi>Saxons.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Order of the <hi>Star</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> was Inſtituted by King <hi>Robert, Anno</hi> 1022. the whole Order conſiſting of thirty Knights, of which the King was the Principal; the Garb they wore were Cloaks of White Damask, and a Star of Gold imbroidered with five pointed Rays on the left ſide.</p>
               <p>The Order of the <hi>Broom-Flower,</hi> was inſtituted by St. <hi>Lewis,</hi> the French King, who in the Collar of his Order wore Golden Broom-Husks or Cods, inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mingled with Flower <hi>de Ly's,</hi> by which
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:46268:56"/>he ſignified that from a Law Eſtate or Humility he had been exalted to the Throne.</p>
               <p>The Order of the <hi>Ship</hi> was likewiſe Inſtituted by the ſame King, to encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage the Nobility of <hi>France,</hi> either in Perſon or Eſtate, to ſet their helping hand to the improvement of Navigati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or to attempt the Seas with him to reſtore the Poſſeſſions of the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans in the Holy Land. The Collar of this Order was interlaced with Scallops double, imitating or Emblematically ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifying the Sandy Shoar, and double Creſcents or Half-Moons, which with the figure of a Ship at the Collar or Chain in Cipher, might ſignifie his intentions to ſight againſt <hi>Mahumetans;</hi> wherefore the Knights were daily obliged, to hear things to incite them to the vindicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and promoting of the Chriſtian Faith, to protect Widows, Orphans, and thoſe that were oppreſſed.</p>
               <p>The Order of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> in <hi>France</hi> was Inſtituted by <hi>Henry</hi> the third, in memory of his Nativity, Election to the <hi>Polonian</hi> Kingdom, and his coming to the Poſſeſſion of the Crown of <hi>France,</hi> all which hapned on <hi>Whitſunday.</hi> This
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:46268:56"/>Order conſiſted of the King, and one hundred Knights, amongſt whom were four Cardinals, five Prelates, the Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor, Provoſt, Maſter of the Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, the High Treaſurer and Regiſter, all the Knights being bound to wear the Croſs on their Garments.</p>
               <p>The Order of <hi>Chriſtian Charity</hi> was In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted by the ſame King, enjoining thoſe to uſe their diligence in relieving Captives, and have regard to maimed Souldiers, and other Objects of Charity; And to that end he aſſigned them Rents and Hoſpitals; they wore on their Cloak as their Badge, an Anchor'd Croſs, em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broidered with White Sattin.</p>
               <p>The Order of the <hi>Virgin Mary</hi> in Mount <hi>Carmel,</hi> was inſtituted by <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth, French King, the number ordained being one hundred Gentlemen, Natives of <hi>France,</hi> and was confirmed by Pope <hi>Paul</hi> the Fifth, <hi>Anno</hi> 1607.</p>
               <p>The Order of <hi>Orleance</hi> was Inſtituted by <hi>Lewis</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> Duke of <hi>Orleance, Anno</hi> 1393. called the Order of the <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupine:</hi> Becauſe the Knights wore a <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupine</hi> of Gold at the end of three Chains for their Badge.</p>
               <p>The Order of the <hi>Golden Shield</hi> was In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:46268:57"/>by <hi>Lewis</hi> the Second, third <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Bourbon,</hi> ſirnamed the Good; in the Shield was a Bend of Pearls, and written thereon the word <hi>Allon,</hi> which is much at one with <hi>Allons</hi> in French, by which ſome ſay he meant, <hi>Let us go all together to the ſervice of God, and Defence of our Country.</hi> He likewiſe Inſtituted the Order of the <hi>Thiſtle,</hi> called alſo the Order of <hi>bourbon, Anno</hi> 1370. conſiſting of Twenty ſix Knights, who wore Belts, on which were embroidered the word <hi>Eſperance,</hi> and a Thiſtle of Silk and Gold hanging as a Taſſel; the like word was on their Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar of Gold, interwoven with Flower-<hi>de-Lys's,</hi> and the Virgin <hi>Mary's</hi> Picture Crowned with Rays, and Stars hanging at it in an Oval, with a Thiſtle-Head at the bottom.</p>
               <p>The Order of St. <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> was Inſtituted <hi>Anno</hi> 1614. by <hi>John Cheſnel,</hi> a Noble French-man, Inſtituted to reſtrain the French Nobility from Duels and Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels; and of this Order were uſually five hundred Knights, who had a Houſe aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned them near <hi>Paris,</hi> and were enjoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be Charitable, Obedient, to avoid Quarreling, to obſerve conjugal Chaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and had a Great Maſter over
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:46268:57"/>them, more of which you may ſee in the Hiſtory of <hi>Andreus Favine Pariſian,</hi> an Advocate in the Court of Parliament, as alſo of the Order of <hi>Bretagne</hi> or <hi>Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine,</hi> and Ears of <hi>Corn,</hi> Inſtituted by <hi>Francis,</hi> Duke of <hi>Bretagne, Anno</hi> 1450.</p>
               <p>The Knights of the <hi>Bath,</hi> were Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted by <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth, King of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> who conſtituted ſix and forty of that Order, appointed them their Chambers in the Tower, and to this day the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der flouriſhes, being conferred, as the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of the Prince, upon worthy Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of known Loyalty and Integrity.</p>
               <p>The Order of the <hi>Thistle,</hi> or St. <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew,</hi> was Inſtituted in <hi>Scotland</hi> by King <hi>Achaius,</hi> who made a League Offenſive and Defenſive with <hi>Charles</hi> the Great, <hi>Anno</hi> 809. The Collar be compoſed of Golden Thiſtles and Rue, with this Motto, <hi>Nemo me impane Laceſſit,</hi> and at the bottom of it hung the Image of St. <hi>Andrew</hi> with his Croſs.</p>
               <p>The Order of the <hi>Lilly</hi> or <hi>Navarr,</hi> was the Inſtitution of Prince <hi>Garcia</hi> the Sixth, <hi>Anno</hi> 1048. in the City of <hi>Nagera,</hi> to the honour of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> conſiſting of Thirty eight Knights, himſelf being the Chief; and the main end of their
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:46268:58"/>Inſtitution was to expel the <hi>Moors</hi> out of that Kingdom; each of them wore on his Breaſt a Silver Lilly, and a double Chain of Gold, interlaced with the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter M. ſtanding for <hi>Mary,</hi> at the end of the Chain hung a Flower-de-lys with the like Letter Crowned.</p>
               <p>The Order of St. <hi>James,</hi> or the Sword, was Inſtituted under the Reigns of <hi>Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinand,</hi> King of <hi>Leon,</hi> and <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> the Sixth King of <hi>Caſtile,</hi> in the year 1158. The Knights of this Order, on their Breſts and Left Sides wore a Scallop-ſhell, and about their Neck a Chain of Gold, with a Sword, or the ſhape of a Sword made of Red Sattin imbroidered, and a Scallop-ſhell upon the Sword; the Red Sword ſignifying their Victory over the <hi>Arabians:</hi> This Order was alſo eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed in <hi>Portugal,</hi> encreaſing to above Six hundred, inſomuch that many Lords of <hi>Spain</hi> held it an Honour to be of the Order of St. <hi>James.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Order of St. <hi>Julian,</hi> commonly called that of the <hi>Pear-Trees,</hi> had its In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution in the Kingdom of <hi>Leon, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no</hi> 1179. being allowed and approved by Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> the Third, <hi>Lucius</hi> the Third, and <hi>Innocent</hi> the Third. Theſe
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:46268:58"/>Knights had a Pear-tree for their Arms; but <hi>Alphonſo</hi> the Ninth, taking the City of <hi>Alacantara</hi> from the <hi>Moors;</hi> he beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it upon the Great Maſter of <hi>Calatra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> who beſtowed it upon the Maſter of the Pear-tree, whence they ſtiled themſelves Knights of <hi>Alacantara,</hi> and changing their Arms, wore the Green Croſs, ſet with Flower-de-lys's on their Breaſt; and as to Religious matters un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertook to ſquare themſelves by the Rules of St. <hi>Bennet,</hi> and ſtrictly profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Chaſtity; but Pope <hi>Paul</hi> the Fourth diſpenſed with that, and gave them leave to Marry, and the Great Maſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip was united by Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> the Sixth, to the Crown of <hi>Caſtile.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Order of the <hi>Band</hi> or <hi>Red Scarf,</hi> was Inſtituted by <hi>Alphonſo</hi> the Eleventh, King of <hi>Leon</hi> and <hi>Castile, Anno</hi> 1330. The Knights of this Order wearing a Red Scarf or Riband, and were enjoined to accompany the King in his wars, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Order of the Dove was Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at <hi>Segobia</hi> in <hi>Caſtile,</hi> by <hi>John</hi> the Firſt, <hi>Anno</hi> 1379. The Collar of this Order was linked with Sun-beams, and to it was faſtned the figure of a Dove of Gold, enaml'd with White, in a flying
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:46268:59"/>poſture, but it continued not above a year.</p>
               <p>The Order of St. <hi>Saviour</hi> of <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treal,</hi> commonly called the Order of <hi>Aragon,</hi> was Inſtituted in <hi>Aragon, Anno</hi> 1120. by <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> the Eighteenth King of <hi>Navarr,</hi> and the Firſt of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragon;</hi> the Knights of this Order wear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Red Robes, and on their Breaſts an Anchored Croſs, and had leave given them to Marry.</p>
               <p>The Order of the <hi>Dragon,</hi> was In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted by the Emperor <hi>Sigiſmond</hi> in <hi>Germany, Anno</hi> 1418. The Knights of this Order on Feſtival days wore a a Scarlet Cloak, with a double Golden Chain, at the end whereof hung a Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon overturned, and her Wings broke, and moreover a Croſs Flower-de-lys'd; which grew and were held in high eſteem.</p>
               <p>The Order of <hi>Auſtria</hi> and <hi>Carinthia,</hi> or of St. <hi>George,</hi> was Inſtituted by the Emperor <hi>Frederick</hi> the Third, who was Firſt Duke of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> in the Year 1470. the Garments of the Knights were white Coats, with red Croſſes, and by their Rule were bound to guard the Fron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers of <hi>Germany, Hungary, Auſtria, Sty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria,</hi> and <hi>Carinthia.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="105" facs="tcp:46268:59"/>
               <p>The Order of <hi>Poland,</hi> or of the <hi>White Eagle,</hi> was Inſtituted by <hi>Ladiſlaus</hi> the Fifth, King of <hi>Poland,</hi> in the Year 1325. the Kings wear a triple Chain, at which hangs an Eagle crowned.</p>
               <p>The Order of the <hi>Elephant,</hi> or of <hi>Denmark,</hi> was Inſtituted by <hi>Chriſtiern</hi> the Firſt, King of <hi>Denmark, Anno</hi> 1478. the Collar of this Order being com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed of Elephants with ſilver Caſtles on their backs, at the end whereof hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Effigies of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norned with Rays, and a Creſcent un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der her Feet.</p>
               <p>The Order of <hi>Sweden,</hi> or of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> or of the <hi>Seraphims,</hi> was Inſtituted <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no</hi> 1334. by <hi>Magnus</hi> the Fourth, King of <hi>Sweden;</hi> the Collar is compoſed of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarchal Croſſes and Cherubims, and the end of the Collar hangs an oval Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blet, with theſe Letters, <hi>J. H. S.</hi> ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifying <hi>Jeſus Hominum Salvator,</hi> with four Nails enamel'd white and black.</p>
               <p>The Order of the <hi>Swan,</hi> or of <hi>Cleve,</hi> is at this day held up by the Princes of that Houſe, who have the <hi>Swan</hi> for their Order Supporters, and Creſts of their Arms.</p>
               <p>The Order of <hi>Livonia,</hi> or the <hi>Sword,</hi>
                  <pb n="106" facs="tcp:46268:60"/>was Inſtituted by <hi>Albert</hi> a Monk of <hi>Breme;</hi> who drawing to his Party di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers rich Men, perſwaded them to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce the World, and vow Chaſtity and Obedience, and to be conformable to the Rules of the <hi>Ciſtertian</hi> Order: They were clothed in long white Caſſocks, with black Hoods; near the Shoulder the figure of a red Sword, and two red Swords a-croſs on the Breaſt, with their points downward: The chief end of their Inſtitution being to fight againſt Infidels, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Order of St. <hi>Gall</hi> was Inſtituted in <hi>Switzerland,</hi> by <hi>Frederick</hi> the Second, Emperor, <hi>Anno</hi> 1213. upon his coming to viſit the Abbey of that Name: He like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe Inſtituted the Order of the <hi>Bear,</hi> giving the chief Lords Collars and Chains of Gold, at the end of which hung a golden Bear: And theſe two Orders he Inſtituted in the memory of St. <hi>Gall,</hi> ſaid to be the Converter of the <hi>Germans,</hi> to the Chriſtian Faith, and Saint <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſus</hi> who ſuffered Martyrdom before the Temple of the Sun at <hi>Soleverre.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As for the <hi>Italian,</hi> or rather <hi>Roman</hi> Orders, they were many; the moſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial of which we ſhall briefly mention,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:46268:60"/>though moſt of them at this day are ceaſed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 1320. Pope <hi>John</hi> the Two and twentieth, Inſtituted the Order of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt,</hi> at <hi>Avignon;</hi> thoſe of the Order wearing Croſſes of Gold en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amel'd with red, incloſed with another Croſs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 1468. Pope <hi>Paul,</hi> at <hi>Rome,</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted the Order of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt;</hi> the Badge of the Order being a white Croſs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 1498. Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> the Sixth Inſtituted the Order of St. <hi>George;</hi> thoſe of the Order carrying a Croſs of Gold, adorned with a Wreath, made in the form of a Crown.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 1520. Pope <hi>Leo</hi> the Tenth In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted the Order of St. <hi>Peter;</hi> conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuting thoſe of the Order to wear, within an Oval of Gold, the Effigies of that Saint, at the end of a Tortois of Chains of Gold: Their Office being to guard the Sea-coaſts, againſt the <hi>Turks;</hi> who at that time committed many Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racies and Outrages.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 1540. Pope <hi>Paul</hi> the Third eſtabliſhed, or rather Inſtituted the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of St. <hi>Paul.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="108" facs="tcp:46268:61"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 1560. the Order of <hi>Pies,</hi> whoſe charge was to carry and guard the Pope when he went abroad, was Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted by Pope <hi>Pius</hi> the Fourth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 1587. Pope <hi>Sixtus Quintus</hi> or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained the Knighthood of <hi>Lauretto,</hi> to whom he erected our Ladies Church at <hi>Lauretto</hi> for a Cathedral.</p>
               <p>There are likewiſe at <hi>Rome</hi> ſome Church-men that have taken upon them the Order of Knighthood, as thoſe of St. <hi>Anthony,</hi> whoſe General is ſtiled the Abbot of St. <hi>Anthony</hi> of <hi>Vienna:</hi> Their Garments are black Caſſocks, Cloaks and Gowns, a double St. <hi>Anthony</hi>'s Croſs, <hi>viz.</hi> two <hi>T T's</hi> made of blue Sattin, though the inferior fort wear but one T.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 1233. the Knights of St. <hi>Mary,</hi> or the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> were Inſtituted by <hi>Bartholomew</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Vienna,</hi> and confirmed by Pope <hi>Urbin</hi> the Fourth, and are bound to St. <hi>Dominick</hi>'s Rules; the Knights wore a white Caſſock, with a red Croſs and two Stars on the Breaſt, their Cloak of a grey colour, and had charge to take care of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phans and Widows, and to their power on all occaſions reconcile differences, and had liberty to live at home with their Wives and Families.</p>
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:46268:61"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 1618. An other Order of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> was erected at <hi>Rome,</hi> by three Brothers; <hi>Bernardo, Pedro,</hi> and <hi>John Baptiſta,</hi> and was Confirmed by Pope <hi>Paul</hi> the Fifth; who with thoſe that Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded him, where to be great Maſters thereof; their Convent being in the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace of <hi>Lateran,</hi> and are bound to defend the Catholick Faith, and fight againſt the <hi>Turks,</hi> and other Infidels, and to be of Noble Extraction. The Knights-Laicks, and Knights-Prieſts of this Order, the latter being Beneficed, are to wear Blew Ribands about their Necks, and a Golden Croſs with Blew Enamel, and on their Cloaks a Croſs of Blew Sattin; but the Knights Chaplains are to wear only a Blew Croſs on their Cloaks, and within the Croſs is a round Circle, wherein are <hi>M. S.</hi> ſtanding for <hi>Maria Sancta,</hi> with a Crown; Twelve Silver Beams or Rays being about the Circle, and Four Lillies at the four ends of the Croſs as alſo Four Stars.</p>
               <p>At <hi>Venice</hi> is the Inſtitution of the Order of St. <hi>Mark,</hi> Inſtituted in Honour of that Evangeliſt, his Body being brought thither, from <hi>Alexandria</hi> in <hi>Egypt;</hi> and is in great eſteem at this day; the <hi>Venetian</hi> Nobility generally coveting to be of that
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:46268:62"/>Order. And at <hi>Genoa</hi> is the Order of St. <hi>George</hi>'s Knights; and ſo in other Cities in <hi>Italy</hi> are peculiar Orders: But ſeeing ſome of them, as indeed of what has been already mentioned, have long ſince ceaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; thoſe that are deſirous of a larger Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, I refer them to the Hiſtories of thoſe Countries; and ſo conclude the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary Orders that are, and have been in divers Countries, highly in eſteem with Princes and Prelates, and were not the leaſt, to whoſe ſignal valour and prudent conduct, Chriſtendom ows her Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance, from the Incroaching Sword of the Infidels; in repelling whom their Blood was ſo freely ſhed. And ſo hop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that what has been ſaid, will not be conſtrued to any Siniſter end, but remain a laſting Monument, to the Memories of ſuch as have done well: I conclude this part of the Book, and proceed to what is Material to be known, by thoſe that are Studious in Curioſity, and not much Inco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herent, if at all, with what has been ſaid.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="part">
            <pb n="111" facs="tcp:46268:62"/>
            <head>THE SECOND PART, CONTAINING <hi>A Survey of the Court of</hi> Rome, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> A Brief Account of the Sacred Colledge, or Colledge of Cardinals; and of thoſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending on it, Relating to Offices and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HAving entertained the Reader thus long, with the ſeveral Religious, and Millitary Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, that are and have been in <hi>Europe</hi> and <hi>Aſia,</hi> ſince that flouriſhing Cedar of Chriſtianity took Root, and ſpread its Branches to the ends of the Earth; and delivered them (as we hope) Imparti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally,
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:46268:63"/>without comment or Gloſs: We ſhall from thence proceed to ſpeak of other things, curious in themſelves, and perhaps not Vulgarly known; and will be found in the following Survey of the <hi>Roman</hi> Court, which for Magnificence, exceeds all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; as in the multitude of great Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Officers, ſplendid Receptions, large Revenues, pompous Ceremonies, and the like, and of theſe we ſhall treat in their Order; and the firſt to be obſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed is the Colledge of Cardinals, called the Sacred Colledge; <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In this Cafe the Pope, or Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> for his Collaterals, has Cardinals to the Number of 70. and theſe are Six Biſhop Cardinals, Fifty Prieſt Cardinals, and the remainder Deacon-Cardinals; as the number was determine and confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by <hi>Sixtus Quintus,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> and theſe compoſe the Sacred Colledge: Amongſt them, there is one that is Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berlain of that Colledge, differing in Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice from the Pope's Chamberlain, and is but for a year, whereas the other is for Term of Life; the Cardinals Reſidenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries in the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſucceeding to it by Order of Seniority, have by the ſpace of a year, the Charge of the Revenues; at the end of which they diſtribute to each
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:46268:63"/>Cardinal his Portion, which they that are not reſident, enjoy no longer then Six Months, after they have left the City: And for the exacter Computation and Management of Affairs, have a Secreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Clark, and Caſter up of Accounts, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the Colledge; yet the Clark continues his Truſt but a year; the Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary is ever an <hi>Italian,</hi> but the Clark may be a <hi>German, French man,</hi> or <hi>Spaniard,</hi> &amp;c. Each of them by vertue of their Office, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires of the Heir of every Cardinal that Deceaſes, 25. <hi>Ducats</hi> of the Chamber, and have their Maintenance from the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace.</p>
               <p>The Secretary's Office, is to write in the Conclave, the Letters in the name of the Colledge, which are ſubſcribed and Seal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Principals of the Orders, <hi>viz.</hi> The firſt Cardinal Biſhop, Cardinal-Prieſt, and Cardinal-Deacon: He aſſiſts likewiſe in the General Congregation, and in the Congregation of the Heads of the Orders, ſetting down the Decretals and Orders that in them are made, and keeps a Regiſter of the Reſolutions of the Secret Conſiſtories, given him by the Cardinal-Chamberlain of the Colledge: In the Conſiſtory he Officiates in a Red Habit, reaching to his Feet, with a Hood of the
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:46268:64"/>like upon his Shoulders, but upon the <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra omnes,</hi> he likewiſe departs.</p>
               <p>The National Clark is the Secretary's Subſtitute, or Deputy, to ſupply his room, or Buſineſs in his Abſence.</p>
               <p>The Caſter up of Accounts is enjoyned to keep a due and juſt Account, in what relates to the Revenues of the Colledge, and make the Cardinal-Chamberlain ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible thereof.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> An Account of the Maſters of the Ceremonies, Maſter of the Palace, the Lord Veſtry Keeper, the Popes Secretary, their Office and Dignity, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE Pope or Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> has Four Maſters of the Ceremonies; two of which are ſtiled participants, and have large Incomes as Fifty Ducats of the Heir of every Cardinal that deceaſes, and a Hundred and Twelve of every new cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated Cardinal; with many other Perqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſits; inſomuch that their Office yields them Annualy 700. Ducats each: The other Two are called Supernumeraries, to each
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:46268:64"/>of them every new Cardinal gives Twelve Ducats of the Chamber; and though both the former have their entertainment from the Apoſtolical Palace, yet of theſe the moſt Antient only is ſo favoured, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding their Authority is equal in ordaining the Pontifical Functions, advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the Lords Cardinals what they are to do, and have a great Command. They are all likewiſe preſent in the Congregations of Rites, and one alone in the Ceremoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Congregation; all of them entering the Conclave; and when the Pope ſends any Cardinal <hi>Legat de Latere,</hi> he propoſeth to him one of theſe Maſters, who is attired in Purple, and whilſt he is in that Habit give place to none, but the Maſter of the Chamber, or the Pope's Cup-bearer.</p>
               <p>The Maſter of the Palace has his abode there, <hi>viz.</hi> In the Palace of the Vatican, with 2. Attendants. And this place belongs properly, to the Fathers of the Religion of S. <hi>Dominick:</hi> His Charge it is, to peruſe the Works that are Printed in <hi>Rome,</hi> and to take a Copy, after he has approved them; and when by the Lord Vice-gerent they are Subſcribed his Reverend Paternity ſets likewiſe his hand to them, or one of his Aſſiſtants, who are Maſters and Fathers of no mean Quality. This Maſter is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:46268:65"/>in the Congregation of the Judge; and in the Pope's Chappel, has a place un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Lord Deacon, or the moſt Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Auditor of the Exchequer, called <hi>Della Ruota,</hi> and has his own Entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and his followers, dayly from the Pope.</p>
               <p>The Lord Veſtry-Keeper, inhabits in the Palace, and muſt be a Father of the <hi>Auguſtine</hi> Order, and under his Charge are Garments, and other things of great Value: He ever attends the Pope at Maſs in Pontifical or Private Celebration, and his Office it is to provide the Wine, the Water, and the Wafer; and when he is a Titular Biſhop, he takes his place in the Chappel among other Biſhops Aſſiſtants; and though he be not a Biſhop, he goes in the Habit of a Regular Prelate, ſitting in the Chappel above the Dean and the Auditor of the Exchequer, waiting upon the Pope's Mytre; who gives him Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment, as he does the Maſter of the Palace.</p>
               <p>The Pope's Secretary is ever a Cardinal, ſtiled the Cardinal-Nephew, and hath ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Secretaries under him: His chief Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs is to write and ſubſcribe Letters by the Pope's Order, to Princes, Nuncios and others; to Sign the Patents of Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours,
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:46268:65"/>Podeſtates, Provoſts-Marſhals, and other officers of the Church: Likewiſe all the Embaſſadors of Princes at their Departure, give an Account of their Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotiation to this Cardinal-Nephew; and the like grand Obſervance he has from all the Miniſters of <hi>Rome;</hi> and was wont to have the Title of Superintendent Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral of the State Eccleſiaſtical, which the Pope gave to him by his <hi>Breve,</hi> and by the like means, gives him the Title of Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretary.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> An Account of the Officers and Servants, imediately Officiating, and attending on the Pope, and in his Palace, their Places and Dignities, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AS for the Maſter of the Pope's Houſe, or <hi>Major Domo,</hi> he is always a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late; and divers others there are, who are properly called Domeſticks, as the Maſter of the Chamber, the Cup-bearer, the Sewer, Carver, chief Harbinger, Under-Maſter of the Chamber, Under-Cup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearer, Under-Sewer, and Under-Maſter
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:46268:66"/>of the Houſe; alſo, the Secret Chamber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lains, of which there are frequently ſeven or eight Participant Chamberlains; one of the Secret-Chamberlains, being always Secret-Treaſurer, and beſtows the Popes Donation or Alms; an other Secret-Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berlain there is, who is the Ward Robe Keeper, under whoſe Charge are Jewels, Gold, Reliques, and the like; there are likewiſe Adjutants: Nor does the Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment of a Secret-Chamberlain amount to leſs than 1000. Crowns <hi>per Annum;</hi> and the Participant Chamberlain more, and all the reſt proportionable to their Degree in Office. There are alſo ſix Secret Clarks of the private Chappel, who have great In-comes by Perquiſits and Stipends; and when the Pope Pontifically proceeds to his Chappel, it is the Duty and Office of his Chaplains to carry his Triple-Crown and Mytre, going before the Croſs in Red Habit.</p>
               <p>There are beſides theſe, Palfrey-Men, who commonly are called Chaplains, and Chaplains of the Guards, Secret-Adintants of the Chamber; and beſides them, Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berlains of Honour, deſcended of Noble parentage, and of good Education. There are alſo, three other Chamberlains, <hi>viz. Della Buſſola,</hi> the Chamberlain <hi>Extramu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ros</hi>
                  <pb n="119" facs="tcp:46268:66"/>and the <hi>Scudiere,</hi> who by turns keep the Watch, and have their Office diſtinct; except the Chamberlains of Honour, who do not appear in the Palace, but when it pleaſes them, and by them the Pope fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently ſends the Hats to the new Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals.</p>
               <p>There are likewiſe, a Sewer, and a Carver of the Sacred Colledge, whoſe places are very advantagious. A Carver, and a Sewer, there are likewiſe for Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, and the Poor that daily feed in the Palace, at the Pope's Charge, who were Inſtituted by Pope <hi>Clement</hi> the Eighth: he Ordaining, that the Father Rectories of the Penitentiaries of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> of the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> ſhould obſerve to bring in every Morning twelve Pilgrims to eat in the Palace, at the Pope's Charge. All theſe Officers are attired in Purple, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their Degree. For the Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly there are two Phyſitians, and a third is entertained by the Secret-Chamber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lain.</p>
               <p>A Perſon of Quality there is, who is entertained by the Pope, in the Nature of Maſter of the Stable, under whoſe charge the Horſes, to the number of two hundred or upward, continually are; yet, he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nages his place by Subſtitutes, and is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:46268:67"/>to wear a Cloak, and Sword, his place being of conſiderable value; nor do any beſide himſelf, and the Chamber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lains of Honour, wear Cloaks, and Swords; his Charge is alſo of the Mules, Litters, and Carriages. And Pope Leo the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth, gave the Title of Maſter of the Horſe, to Signior <hi>Pomponeo Frangipanii,</hi> a Valiant <hi>Roman,</hi> who had well deſerved in the Wars.</p>
               <p>Other under Officers there are, in whoſe Cuſtody is the Pope's Furniture, and Houſhold ſtuff, whoſe Care it chiefly is to ſee the Rooms, and other Places kept in order, and accomodated when there is a Conſiſtory Signature of Grace and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation. There are likewiſe Secret and Publick Sweepers, whoſe upper Garments are Purple, and formerly were the Pope's Coach-men, <hi>viz.</hi> when he was a Cardinal, as alſo <hi>Palfrey-men,</hi> more then forty; which are uſually ſuch as belong to the Deans of the Cardinals, and Ambaſſadors, who reſide in <hi>Rome,</hi> when the Pope comes to his Dignity: Their Clothing is Red or White, as themſelves ſhall chooſe, with a Purple Cloak, and a Guilt Sword.</p>
               <p>Twelve Mace-bearers there are, and the like number of Vergers, both of them ſalable Offices, and neither worth leſs then
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:46268:67"/>ſix hundred Crowns a piece, yielding fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Crowns or upward Yearly. Theſe and many others, are the Officers immediately attending on the Pope, who are plentiful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly provided for.</p>
               <p>As for the Pope's Palace, the Gate thereof ſtands but half open, for the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception of any Ambaſſador or Miniſter of State; but when the Pope, or his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren paſs it, it ſtands wide open.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> An Account of the Pope's Secretary of State; The Secretaries of the Breives, their Office and Dignity, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE Secretaries of State are account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Superiour Officers, and have great Entertainment from the Pope, depending upon the Cardinal-Nephew, and wearing Purple attire, taking their Directions from that Cardinal, though they negotiate with the Pope, ſending to him their Letters to be ſubſcribed; and have diſtributed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them the Nuntiary Provinces, one of them being Secretary to the Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers, or dark Significations; yet his place
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:46268:68"/>is but half the value of the others: They all co-habit in the Pope's Palace, and are well provided for.</p>
               <p>There are belonging to the Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Affairs, three Secertaries of the Brieves, and of thoſe Brieves that go under Taxa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, of which hereafter more will be ſaid.</p>
               <p>There are alſo two other Secretaries, one of the Councils, and an other of the Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rials, the latter being uſually Maſter of the Pope's Chamber, and Secretary of the Congregations, <hi>de Bono Regimine,</hi> and <hi>ex gravi;</hi> and under each of them, two or three others ſerve: Every one of them o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver and above Emoluments, have large Entertainments from the Pope; all his Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers being appareled in Purple, but their habits made different according to their Place and Office, either of Silks, Cloth or Stuff.</p>
               <p>The Secretaries of the Breives under Taxation are 24. and every Secertary's Place, is worth no leſs then a Thouſand Crowns; and of theſe by the Pope's De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration, one is conſtituted Superior, whoſe Habit is that of a Referendary, or Domeſtick Prelate, and has his Lodging in the Palace. All Breives, diſpatched by this Secretary, do pay; (Indulgences <hi>ad Tempus</hi> excepted,) and thoſe Breives be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:46268:68"/>taxed by one of theſe Secretaries, tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it by turns, the Original of the Breives, being viewed by the Cardinal Praefect of the Breives, they are Sealed and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patched.</p>
               <p>The Secretary of the Secret Breives is ordered either by the Cardinal Nephew, or Secretary of State, to make them: The Originals of which are not expoſed, nor Subſcribed by the Cardinal Praefect; and after theſe Breives are Sealed with the Seal of the Principal Secretary, they are Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined by the Originals, and then Signed by him; one of which Breives is always accompanied with a Letter of the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal-Nephew's. Of the Original of theſe Brieves, great care is taken, being upon the Death of the Pope, carried into the Caſtle of St. <hi>Angelo;</hi> as likewiſe all Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of things, and ſuch Letters as the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretaries have in their hands.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="124" facs="tcp:46268:69"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> An Account of the Pope's Guard, and the Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Officers and Forces, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Dependent upon the See of <hi>Rome,</hi> by Sea and Land, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE General of the Pope's Guards is made ſo by Vertue of a Breive, and has each Month 200. Crowns Salary: Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him there is a Lieutenant, whoſe Office is computed at Fourſcore Crowns a Month; the Money is payd by the Chamber: In this Guard, are generally two Troops of Light-Horſe, whoſe Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains and Cornets, are as the Lieutenant before mentioned, made by the Pope's Breive; a Company there is conſiſting of <hi>Switzers,</hi> Commanded by Officers of the ſame Nation; and Twelve Demy-Laun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, all Captains Reformadoes, having each Fifteen Crowns a Month: All the Captains and Military Offices, are payed after the manner of the Wars, befides which by Vails and Perqueſits much does accrue, in the Apoſtolical Palace, where is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually a Guard of 50. <hi>Switzers,</hi> Twelve Light-Horſe, and Four Demy-Launces;
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:46268:69"/>and theſe are divided into two Bodies.</p>
               <p>The General of the Holy Church is Conſtituted by the Pope's Breive, and his Staff, and Oath, being privately given him in the Chamber. In time of War he has Three Thouſand Crowns a Month; and in time of Peace, but One Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand; and of him about 500. Officers hold their plaee by Patent; moſt of them Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary men, officiating within the Territo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the Church. Under him he hath a lieutenant-General, whoſe place is worth 3000. Crowns a year; and a Serjeant, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor-General, whoſe Salary is 500. Crowns a year; but theſe laſt places are not at his diſpoſe, but the Pope's, and are granted by his Breives; who in like manner, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutes the General of the Artillery, with a 100. Crowns a Month. Nor can any Souldier be Impriſoned without a Licenſe or leave, under the General's hand, and the Souldiers inroeled through the Territo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the Church are computed 80000. Foot and 3500. and Horſe, yet have no pay, but ſerve when occaſion requires, upon certain Exemptions, and priviledges and enjoyment of things, whereby benefit does accrue; and theſe are called the Bands, or Batoglias, and are ready upon the firſt notice, and very well diſciplined; and the
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:46268:70"/>better to furniſh them upon Occaſion, divers Armories and Magazines are plac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed throughout the Territories of the Church, erected by precedent Pope's and Generals: The Praefectſhip of <hi>Rome,</hi> is ever beſtowed upon an honorable Perſon, being held in great Eſteem by the Biſhops, as it was of old by the <hi>Roman</hi> Emperors; and hath many great Priviledges belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to it, it being the proper Office of the Praefect, to carry before the Emperor in Solemn Riding, the Imperial Sword.</p>
               <p>The Governour of the Caſtle of Saint <hi>Angelo,</hi> is Conſtituted by the Pope's Breive; his pay is each Month 500. Crowns, and has under him of his own making, a Deputy Governour, who looks to the charge of that Important Caſtle, whoſe entertainment is fifty Crowns a Month, beſides many Perquiſits: The Providitor holds his Office, by Patent from the Governour. Another there is, who looks to the Armory, having divers under him; beſides there are two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Souldiers, together with their Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, who are payed according to the manner of the Wars: All the Officers, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the Maſter-Gunner, are made by the Governour; except the Corporals, who together with the Souldiers, and
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:46268:70"/>Chaplains, are conſtituted by the Deputy Governour; and by him the Adjutants of the Caſtle are inrolled, which are uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally five hundred, and are priviledged to wear Arms.</p>
               <p>The General of the Gallies, is made by the Pope's Breive, and take an Oath, as do all the great Officers, before the Lord Treaſurer General; and his enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment is three hundred Crowns a Month, and pay for twelve Demy Laun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; he conſtitutes his Lieutenants, and all his Subordinate Officers; the Providitor Pay-maſter, Patron of the Gally, Muniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on-Maſter, Apothecary, being exempted, who hold it by the Lord Treaſurer General's Patent; and though the General cannot by right, free any one from the Chains, without a Council of War, yet he often does it without being contradicted.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="128" facs="tcp:46268:71"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> An Account of the Pope's Vicar, and many other great Officers and Offices reſting in the Perſons of Cardinals: with their Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, and Valuable Conſiderations, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HAving diſcourſed briefly, of many Offices and Officers in the Court of <hi>Rome;</hi> as well immediately dependant upon the Pope, as the Colledge of Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals; we ſhall now proceed to the great Offices, wherein the Cardinals are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately concerned; and firſt of the Pope's Vicar.</p>
               <p>The Pope's Vicar, ſince the time of <hi>Pius</hi> the Fourth, has been choſen out of the Colledge of Cardinals, who before was a Biſhop: His Duty is to obſerve, that all things are kept in good Order, and has Juriſdiction over the Prieſts, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulars inhabiting <hi>Rome;</hi> as likewiſe the Companies of Lay-men, Hoſpitals, and Pious places, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> within the precincts thereof; and has for his entertainment 100. Crowns a Month, out of the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber: Under him are four Notaries, who
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:46268:71"/>Exerciſe their Office apart; each No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary, having under him eight or nine Clarks. This Office has likewiſe two Lieutenants, the one for Civil matters, who commonly is a Referendary Prelate, and the other for Criminal Cauſes; as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo a Vice-gerent, who for ſome years paſt, haſt been a Titular Biſhop, to the end he may not be abſent, but perform his Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copal Function in <hi>Rome;</hi> and his Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>intendency, or more peculiar care, is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Monaſteries of Nuns; yet is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent with the other Officers in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations, which are made before the Cardinal-Vicar, relating to matters and cauſes of that Tribunal; and under him hath a Provoſt-Marſhal, with Serjeants, and the like.</p>
               <p>The charge of the Chief Penitentiary, is undertaken by a Cardinal, conferred on him by the Pope, and is worth 8000. Crowns a year; and under him is a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, ſtiled the Regent of the Penitentia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, whoſe Juriſdiction is over the Caſes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred to the Pope, of granting Abſolutions <hi>Gratis, Ubique,</hi> directed to approved Confeſſors in Parliament; Sealed with the Seal of the Penitentiaries.</p>
               <p>The Cardinal Penitentiary, ſits in three Cathedral Churches, <hi>viz.</hi> St. <hi>John d'Late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ran,</hi>
                  <pb n="130" facs="tcp:46268:72"/>St. <hi>Peter</hi> in the <hi>Vatican,</hi> and that of <hi>Sancta Maria Maggiore;</hi> upon a Seat rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed four Degrees, in the Nature of a Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunal, with a ſtaff of his Office in his Hand, from whence he gives <hi>Audit</hi> to Confeſſions of Caſes reſerved: He like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe makes his Congregations with the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tervening of his Regent of the Prelate, who is the Seal-bearer, and two other Divines with a Canoniſt; many Offices of Profit are at his diſpoſal.</p>
               <p>As for the Vice-Chancellor, he is at this day an Eminent Cardinal, and the place is gueſſed to yield him, between 15. or 16000. Crowns a year; his Juriſdiction is over the Diſpatches of Apoſtolical Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, concerning any matter, whereof the Supplication is ſigned, except ſuch as are diſpatched by <hi>Breve ſub Annulo Piſcatoris.</hi> On <hi>Tueſday, Thurſday,</hi> and <hi>Sunday,</hi> every Week the Officers of the Chancery Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolical Aſſemble in his Palace, which are the Regent; and the Abreviators <hi>de Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co Magiore,</hi> being in number twelve Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates, beſide the Regent, attired in Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, made in the ſhape of that of Prelates: And theſe Offices are to be ſold at a great value, being at the diſpoſal of the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, Vice-Chancellor. As for theſe Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates, thirteen in number, they take place
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:46268:72"/>in the Pope's Chappel; but the Regent declines it, in reſpect to the precedency with other Prelates. They likewiſe are Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferendaries, both of the one, and the other Signature, and the Regent has Power to commit the Cauſe of Appeals in <hi>Rome,</hi> which he generally does to the Auditors of the <hi>Ruota,</hi> and to the Referendaries, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtributing them, that every one may have a part.</p>
               <p>The Office of the Abbreviators is to make the Original of the Bulls, upon the Supplications ſigned by the Pope, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>view them, when fairly Written on Parch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and is aſſiſted by Inferiour Officers, who have their Fees out of Taxing the ſaid Bulls, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As for the Cardinal-Chancellor's fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Office, it is to take the Collations of the Cardinal's Tythes, and Declarations of Promotions in the Secret Conſiſtory; as alſo of the Biſhopricks, which the Pope makes <hi>pro tempore:</hi> Likewiſe, of the Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorial Abbies, giving out the Schedules of ſuch Proviſions.</p>
               <p>The Cardinal-Chamberlain's Place is in high Eſteem, and proves worth, between 12. and 14000. Crowns yearly; his Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction being to take notice of the Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, that appertain to the Apoſtolical Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:46268:73"/>as alſo of the Clarks thereof, when he is not detained by the Conſiſtory, he ſits in the Chamber, moſt part of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpatches paſſing there under his Name, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they be ſubſcribed and diſcuſſed by the Clark. His likewiſe Judge of the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peals, from the Sentence given by the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the Streets: Taking Cognizance of the Reaſon of Building, as alſo of the Bridges, Streets, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And during the Vacancy of the See, takes Poſſeſſion of the Pope's Lodging, and has a Guard of <hi>Switzers;</hi> Coining Money, with his Arms ſtamped thereon, and is in a manner Pope till one be Elected.</p>
               <p>The Praefect of the Signature of Juſtice, is always a Cardinal; his place yielding him 200. Ducats a Month, and has a Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction in Reference of Supplication, and Commiſſions of Cauſes, which are delegated for Juſtice; and unleſs it be in Vacation time, ſits every <hi>Thurſday</hi> of the Week in his own Palace, to decide Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters between the Commiſſioners and their References, where there are Officiating twelve voting Prelates; the Ancienteſt Refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendaries, with the Auditor of the <hi>Ruota,</hi> and the Cardinal-Vicar's Livetenant Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, who are there to defend the Juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of their Courts, and are permitted
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:46268:73"/>to Vote, and ſince many of the Cauſes delegated, are diſpatched by Breive, or the Cardinal Praefect's Letter; two Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers are purpoſely appointed, one of which is call'd the Praefect of the Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals of the Breives, who conſigns them when made; the other Officer, called the Maſter of the Breives, which he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns to the Secretary of the Breives, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Taxation, that he may get them Seal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: The firſt of theſe Offices is worth 12000. Crowns, and the latter between 12 and 1300. Crowns; and to theſe in a manner is joined the Office called the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſor of the Commiſſions of Signature of Juſtice, and all of them are attired in Purple Robes.</p>
               <p>The Office of Praefect of the Signature of Grace, reſts in the Perſon of a Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, and procures him a hundred Duc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ates of the Chamber each Month; his Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs being chiefly to aſſiſt at the Signa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of grace made before the Pope, and to Seal each Supplication, where alſo the twelve Voting Prelates are preſent, which are commonly the ſame that Vote in the Signature of Juſtice; and there likewiſe officiate the Cardinal Prelates of the Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nature of Juſtice, the Cardinal-Vicar, and Cardinal-Praefect of the Breives, the
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:46268:74"/>Lord <hi>Datary,</hi> and more or leſs of the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals, as the Pope-ſhall appoint, twelve being ever the leaſt, and interuening at that Signature, are likewiſe the Lord Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditor of the Chamber, his Civil Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant; the Lord Treaſurer General, the Auditors of the <hi>dela Ruota:</hi> the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Vicars Lieutenant Civil, a participant Pronotary, a Clerk of the Chamber, an Abbreviator <hi>de Parco Maggiore,</hi> with the Lord Regent of the Chancery; and their buſineſs there, is to defend the Juriſdiction of their reſpective Offices: It is held eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Week upon <hi>Sunday</hi> or <hi>Tueſday</hi> before the Pope, unleſs in Vacation time.</p>
               <p>The Praefect of the Breives has as the reward of his Office 100. Crowns each Month, out of the Chamber, his Buſineſs being to Review and Sign the Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal of the Breives that are under Taxa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>The Library Keeper is generally a Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal; whoſe Charge is to ſuperviſe the Printing, and look to the Vatican Libra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and thoſe that Work in it, and where Claſſical Works in the Original Tongue are Printed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="135" facs="tcp:46268:74"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> An Account of the ſeveral Congregations held at <hi>Rome,</hi> the end for which they were held, the Nature of the ſeveral Offices thereto belonging, with the Dignity of the Reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive Offices, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AS for the Congregations of Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals, they are many and different in their Effects, of which I ſhall ſpeak in their order; and in the firſt place, of that called the Congregation of the Holy Office.</p>
               <p>This Congregation Aſſembles on <hi>Wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſdays</hi> and <hi>Thurſdays,</hi> every Week; the firſt Aſſembly is in the Conuent of the Dominicant <hi>Alla Minerva,</hi> and the ſecond before the Pope, about Matters to Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Where many Cardinals inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vene, and by him twelve at leaſt are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, together with divers Prelates, other Divines, and Religious Orders, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And have in Conjunction the Title of Conſultors of the Holy Office; the Seal of this Office is kept by a noted Cardinal, who is allowed a Priſon, and Officers to
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:46268:75"/>puniſh Offenders, as likewiſe Miniſters, amongſt whom is the Commiſſary, who is a Father of the Dominican Order, and the Aſſeſſor a Prelate, or one of the Pope's Chamberlains of Honour, whoſe Buſineſs it is to make report of the Cauſes in the Congregation.</p>
               <p>The Congregation relating to the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs of the Biſhops, and Regulars, whoſe Juriſdiction is in Caſe of Differences ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing between the Biſhops and their Subor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinates, and the like; as to the Regulars alſo, to take Care in providing for the Occurrences of Biſhops, which require Conſultation, and is held in the Houſe of a Cardinal, who is the Principal every <hi>Fryday.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Juriſdiction of the Congregation of the Counſel, is to interpret the Text of the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> and is kept in the Houſe of the Eldeſt Cardinal, who is the chief therein, though a ſecond Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal keeps the Seal, and is held once a Week on the day the Chief Cardinal ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>points.</p>
               <p>The Eccleſiaſtical Immunity Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation was erected, for that ſome in ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry Caſes injoyed not Eccleſiaſtical Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity; and becauſe through Diverſity and Mixture of Offences, the Determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:46268:75"/>reſted many times doubtful; Pope <hi>Urban</hi> the <hi>8th.</hi> erected this Juriſdiction, which is held in the eldeſt Cardinal's Houſe, every <hi>Tueſday;</hi> divers Cardinals aſſiſting, as alſo the auditor <hi>della Ruota;</hi> a Clark of the Chamber, a Voter of the Signature, and the Secretary who fie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently is a Referendary of either Signa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; as alſo the Cardinal-Praefect, in whoſe Cuſtody the Seal is, and hath from the Cardinal, the Entertainment of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Crowns <hi>per Annum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Another Congregation is, <hi>viz.</hi> That of the State, which is often held before the Pope, but oftner before the Cardinal Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phew, whereat all the Cardinals that have been <hi>Nuntios</hi> Apoſtolical ought to be preſent, as likewiſe the Pope's Secreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of State. Another Congregation was erected by <hi>Gregory</hi> the Fifteenth, for the Propagation of the Catholick Faith, from whence it takes its Denomination.</p>
               <p>In this Congregation, divers Cardinals, together with an Apoſtolical Protonotary ſit; as alſo the Pope's Secretary of State, the Judge who uſually is a Referendary of both Signatures; and further, the Aſſeſſor of the Holy Office and Secretary of the ſame Congregation.</p>
               <pb n="138" facs="tcp:46268:76"/>
               <p>The Congregation of Rites, is likewiſe held in <hi>Rome,</hi> and the end of it is to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe differences, and ſee the opinions concerning Rites, Precedencies, Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And the Antienteſt Cardinal deputed by the Pope to attend this Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice is the Judge, and in his houſe it is held once every Month, or oftner if the head Cardinal thinks fit to appoint it; or if the reſt of the Cardinal's Aſſiſtants re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire it.</p>
               <p>There is a Congregation for Water, of which the Cardinal in whoſe houſe it is held, is Chief; and the chief buſineſs is to inquire into matters, relating to Rivers, Brooks, Bridges, Water-Courſes, Aquae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducts, and Conveyances; and is not conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned unleſs occaſion require it: And much to the ſame purpoſe, is the congregation held for Inſpecting matters, relating to the Fountains, Water-Conveyances, and Streets for the Commodity, and advantage of the City.</p>
               <p>The Congregation for Printing, and Correcting Books, is headed by a Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, and Conſtituted to be held at his houſe; but there being Perſons deputed to that end, they ſeldom meet unleſs com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints are made.</p>
               <pb n="139" facs="tcp:46268:76"/>
               <p>The Council of the Government of the State of the holy Church, is managed in chief, by the Cardinal-Nephew; in whoſe Palace it is held, <hi>Frydays</hi> and <hi>Tues<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>days;</hi> where five or ſix Cardinals, and ſeven or eight Prelates, with other great Officers, hear and determine matters re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating to the Church Affairs, ſetling buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in all Countries, in which their Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction extends; by ſending Directions and receiving anſwers from their <hi>Legats, Nuncios,</hi> Governours, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in Princes Courts and in the Churches proper Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritories.</p>
               <p>The Congregation for eaſing the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and of <hi>Bono Regimine,</hi> conſiſts of the Pope's Nephew <hi>Protempore,</hi> as chief, to whom the people apply themſelves, for the eaſing of Grievances; and the one held on <hi>Saturday</hi> in the Council Room, and the other in the next Room to it, and tend to one and the ſame purpoſe at which five or ſix Cardinals, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven or eight Prelates are Generally a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting.</p>
               <p>The Congregation relating to the Mint, is managed by four Cardinals, and four Chamberlains, who take an Account of the Coin, and what is Minted; and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve that it may when Coined, be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:46268:77"/>of to the uſe of the Church, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And this is held at the Eldeſt Cardinals Houſe, as often as there is Occaſion for it.</p>
               <p>A Congregation there is held, in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to Examine the Perſon, on whom the Pope intends to beſtow the Dignity of Biſhop; or thoſe on whom he has beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it, and is held before the Pope, conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of nine or ten Cardinals, and half the Number of Prelates; yet it extends for the moſt part, no farther then to thoſe that are to have thoſe Dignities con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered on them. In <hi>Italy,</hi> the party to be examined continues kneeling on a Cuſhion, before the Pope; it being in the power of every Member of the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, to put Interrogatories to him; when he is approved, he is Regiſtred in a Book, kept by the Secretary of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation: If he be once examined, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he change his Biſhoprick, he is not to be a ſecond time examined; but if he was never Examined, it is in the power of the Congregation, to convene him, but the Cardinals are not ſubject to this Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</p>
               <p>The chief Cardinal-Deacon <hi>pro tempore,</hi> is head of the Congregation, relating to conſiſtorial Affairs; the Pope appointing the day, the main buſineſs being the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignation
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:46268:77"/>of Biſhopricks, the Intereſt of Taxations of the Church, of conſiſtorial Abbies, and things of the like Nature; it being generally held in the houſe of the firſt conſtituted, or head Cardinal, though many Aſſiſtants were allowed and Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies uſed in the performance; the heads of every Congregation having their Secretary to draw up the Letters, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> according to the decrees, that are eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed in a full Congregation; every head ſubſcribing the Letters of his own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, which the Secretaries Seal, with the Seal of him that Subſcribed them, the Regiſter remaining in the hands of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective Secretaries.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="142" facs="tcp:46268:78"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> An Account of the three Arch-Prieſt-hoods, the Apoſtolical Chamber, Lord Governour of <hi>Rome,</hi> Lord Treaſurer, Lord Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, Lord Preſident, Advocates of the Exchequer and Poor; the Proctor of the Exchequer, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Their Offices and Digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THere are redounding to particular Cardinals, three Arch-Prieſthoods; that is to ſay, of the three noted Churches in <hi>Rome.</hi> Theſe Arch-Prieſts, have the ſole power, within the Juriſdiction of their Church, to confer all the Benefices, Livings Chaplain ſhips, and other Vacancies de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending thereon: And theſe Churches are St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s, in the Vatican, <hi>Santa Maria Maggiore,</hi> and <hi>Santa Johannes de Lateran;</hi> and as to the latter of theſe, the Arch-Prieſt has power in Criminal and Civil Caſes, to Inquire and Examine, thoſe within the Juriſdiction of his Church; and in the year of Jubilee: Every Arch-Prieſt, goes Pontificaly to his Church, with a ſplendid retinue, in order to open
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:46268:78"/>the Holy Gate; and to the Church of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> the Cardinal-Deacon takes his way, and takes the ſame Order, in opening the Holy Gate; but that of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> is open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Pope; in which Church, the Fathers of the Society of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> are Peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiaries; in that of St. <hi>John de Laterand,</hi> the Fathers of the Order of St. <hi>Francis;</hi> and in <hi>Sancta Maria Maggiore,</hi> the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the Order of St. <hi>Dominick;</hi> and are well provided, with all neceſſaries; hearing Confeſſions in divers Languages, and one of them for each place, is Rector of the Penitentiaries.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Ruota,</hi> is properly the Apoſtolical Exchequer and is managed by Twelve Prelates Auditors; every Auditor having Four Notaries, and aſſemble in the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolical Palace, twice a week, <hi>viz.</hi> On <hi>Monday</hi> and <hi>Friday;</hi> unleſs the firſt week of <hi>July,</hi> and the firſt of <hi>October,</hi> the <hi>Ruo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta operus;</hi> and then the Auditors, with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Cardinals, and Prelates, ride in a Triumphant manner to Congratulate the Pope; to whom the youngeſt Auditor makes an Oration.</p>
               <p>The Apoſtolical Chamber ſits every, <hi>Monday</hi> and <hi>Friday,</hi> and upon ſuch days, as the Conſiſtory is held; there ſits the Cardinal-Chamberlain; the Lord Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:46268:79"/>of <hi>Rome,</hi> a Vice Chamberlain, the Lord Treaſurer General, the Lord Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditor of the Chamber, the Lord Preſident, the Auditor of the Poor, the Fiſcal Advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, the Commiſſary, and twelve Clarks of the Chamber, four of which are, <hi>viz.</hi> the Praefect of Fleſh and White-meats, the Praefect of Corn and Victuals, the Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of the Priſon, and the Praefect of the State. And the Juriſdiction of this Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, is over Writings, and Deeds, relating to the Praefects, the Revenues of the See Apoſtolical, Treaſures of the Provinces of the State Eccleſiaſtical, over Cauſes of the Commonalty, Eccleſiaſtical Feuds, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſals, Accompts of Officers, Miniſters of State, Coinage of Money, Appeals, Building, and the like; and have nine Notaries, who hold their Offices ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately, with many Clarks under them, and are places of great profit. This Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber gives over ſitting as the <hi>Ruota,</hi> and then the Pope makes the Miniſters and Officers a great Feaſt; and on the firſt of <hi>Auguſt</hi> another is made by the Cardinal-Chamberlain, and on St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Eve, all the Tributes of the Feudatories of the Church are payed with other Matters.</p>
               <p>The Lord Governour of <hi>Rome,</hi> in civil Cauſes, has uſually two Lieutenants to
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:46268:79"/>take Cognizance of Wages, Sallaries, and the Condition of poor People. And in Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal Caſes he hath uſually but one, and his Juriſdiction is over all the City; as likewiſe Prevention with all the Tribunals, having divers Judges, and a prime Notary under him, all whoſe Emoluments are diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to Charitable uſes, ſo that he is called the Notary of Charity: Further he has under him a Provoſt-Marſhal, and 300. Serjeants: When this Lord paſſeth the Streets of <hi>Rome,</hi> he has a Guard of <hi>Hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berdiers, Italians,</hi> and over them a Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, which together with himſelf are maintained out of the Chamber.</p>
               <p>The Lord Treaſurer General takes Cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizance of the Repriſals of Eccleſiaſtical Perſons, as Prieſts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of unwholſom Fruit, of the Fountains, of unlawful Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotiation, exacting the Rents of the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and See Apoſtolick, he gives Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dates to thoſe appointed to receive them; overlooking the Accompts of Miniſters, Officers, and Fathers, and is diligent in all things, wherein the See, and Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, are intereſſed, or concerned; and is a place diſpoſed of by the Pope, yielding between a 11 and 12 Thouſand Crowns a Year.</p>
               <pb n="146" facs="tcp:46268:80"/>
               <p>The Lord Auditor of the Chamber, has a large Juriſdiction, as being the ordinary Judg of the <hi>Roman</hi> Court, and of all the Merchants, Strangers, and Courtiers, that reſide in the City; as alſo of the Princes, Barons, Ambaſſadors, Biſhops, Patriarchs, and Cardinals; being likewiſe, ordinary Judge of the Appeals, as well thoſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, as within the State Eccleſiaſtical, that are within the Juriſdiction of the Court; and is <hi>Executer privative quod omnes</hi> of the Chamber, Obligation, and Cumu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lative of all Letters Apoſtolical, and of all Writings upon Oath, and otherwiſe, and the like of Sentences, <hi>de partibus Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minata Cenſura,</hi> and hath a large power over Criminals, having under him two Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil-Lieutenants, being Prelates, and one Lieutenant Criminal, with many Judges, and ten Officers for Notaries, keeping their Offices ſeparate: And this Auditor's place is ſold for 10000. Crowns, which accrews to the Pope; and further he has a Provoſt-Marſhal, with many Serjeants.</p>
               <p>The Buſineſs of the Lord Preſident of the Reverend Chamber, is to make a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>view of all the Accompts of the Treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the Chamber, and See Apoſtolical; his Habit is Purple, and his place valued at 30000 Crowns,</p>
               <pb n="147" facs="tcp:46268:80"/>
               <p>The Advocate of the Exchequer, is bound to defend its Rites, in all Courts, and before all Tribunals, if they are inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red or brought in Queſtion.</p>
               <p>The Advocate for the Poor, writes Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications, and other matters for indigent Perſons, without Fee or Exaction.</p>
               <p>The Commiſſary of the Chamber has his Charge to defend, and as much as in him lies, to ſupport its Intereſts in civil Matters; and as Occaſion requires, to be aſſiſting to the Lord Treaſurer General, in reviewing the Accompts of the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues, and Rents of the Chamber, of Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſsments, Cuſtoms, Proviſion of Corn, and Coinage.</p>
               <p>The Proctor of the Exchequer in <hi>facto,</hi> defends all its Rites before Tribunals as Cauſe requires.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="148" facs="tcp:46268:81"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> An Account of the Marſhal-Senator, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervator, Prior of the Caporioni, Maſter of the Streets, Chamberlain of the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-Bank, Referendaries, Governour of the Burroughs, with many other great Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE Marſhal of <hi>Rome</hi>'s Dignity, is of a long ſtanding, and is generally conferr'd upon a Noble-Man of <hi>Rome;</hi> his Office is to take Cognizance of many Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, not amounting to the Effuſion of Blood, and for a time hath the Cuſtody of the Conclave, on which he placeth the Guard of Soldiers, commanded by him; as alſo the Charge of a Priſon.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Rome,</hi> there is a Senator, whoſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidence is in the Capitol, conſtituted by the Pope's Breive, and hath under him two Judges in civil Matters, as alſo a Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal Judge of Malefactors, and diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces Juſtice to the Citizens, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Cauſes of Appeal only devolving from him, and his Judges to the Captain of Appeals, who is likewiſe a Magiſtrate, reſident in the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitol.
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:46268:81"/>This Senator upon publick Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, is apparelled like the Antient <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans;</hi> with a Cloth of Gold Garment, reaching to the Ground, long Sleeves li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with Crimſon Silk, and a great Chain of Gold, and is commonly a Doctor of the Law; he holds his place at the Pope's pleaſure, and frequently gives him an Account of his proceedings.</p>
               <p>In the Capitol, as the former, are the Conſervators, conſiſting of three <hi>Roman</hi> Gentlemen; and the Prior of the <hi>Caporio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni pro tempore,</hi> Which <hi>Caporioni</hi> are in the Nature of Aldermen, in Number 14. and with the Conſervators, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are every three Months renewed and the Choice <hi>de novo,</hi> made before the pope, Cardinal Chamber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lain, and Cardinal-Nephew; and the day after Election, they take their Oath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Pope, and have by the Order of the Senator, the firſt Month, their pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces aſſigned them in the Capitol: Their Office and Juriſdiction, moſtly relating to the conſervation of the Cuſtoms and Antiquities of the City, and inſpecting Weights, Meaſures, and Prices of Victu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als, adminiſtring Ordinary Juſtice; and are Ordinary Judges, in caſe of Appeals, brought by the Conſuls of Trades and Husbandry; granting alſo Freedoms, and
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:46268:82"/>other things of the like nature; taking place above the Secret Chamberlains, and going on high days, in Senators Habit; as for the Prior, he is choſen by the <hi>Caperioni,</hi> and is equal with the Conſervators, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Maſter of the Street, has his place likewiſe Aſſigned him in the Capitol; and has an Aſſiſtant with an Aſſeſſor, and a Notary, and they imploy themſelves in Surveying the Streets, and Bridges, as occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion requires, to keep them in good Order; determining controverſies ariſing on that Occaſion, and amerceing Offenders: As for the Maſter, his Office is conferred on him by the Pope's Breive, and continues during his pleaſure.</p>
               <p>The Chamberlain of the Water Bank, an Officer ſo called; exerciſeth his Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction amongſt Marriners; and what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates to Maritine affairs, and from him there is an appeal to the Clark of the Chamber Apoſtolical, whoſe lot is to have the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident ſhip of the Water-Bank; and h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> has a Judge, who adminiſters Juſtice to Mariners, Barge-men, and the like, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Trade upon the River, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> where the Cardinal Chamberlain appoints by hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Pattent, a Commiſſary over the Wood, to prevent frauds.</p>
               <pb n="151" facs="tcp:46268:82"/>
               <p>The Referendaries of both Signatures, are a Colledge of Prelates, without any ſetled number; and their Juriſdiction is to propound the Commiſſions, and both the Contentions, and Gracious Supplications in the Signature of Juſtice, and Grace; and to take Cognizance, of all Cauſes commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to them, under twenty five Crowns; for if any Exceed, they are to be Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the <hi>Ruota.</hi> When any of theſe are Created, he is obliged to viſit the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Cardinals, and the Twelve Vot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Prelates.</p>
               <p>The Governour of the Burrough at <hi>Rome,</hi> is impowered by the Pope's Breive, and maintains a Judge, and an Attorney-General; a formal Court, a Palace, and a Priſon, a Head Notary; with divers Clarks under him, a Provoſt-Marſhal, and fifteen Serjants under him, to adminiſter Juſtice throughout the Burroughs; his Juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in that caſe, extending as far as <hi>Settig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ana;</hi> his Judge having Weekly Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the pope, to render him an Account of the Affairs of his Tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal.</p>
               <p>The Datary, and Under-Datary are two <hi>Roman</hi> Officers, through the hands of the former paſs the Vacancys of Beneefices, not valued at above 24. Ducats a year, and
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:46268:83"/>cauſes ſupplications even without the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipation of the Pope to be ſigned; and in caſe of Benefices of greater value as Dignities, Canons, places, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in carrying the Supplications to the Pope<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and expoſing the Concurrents; it ſtand<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in his power by favouring the Merits o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> one more then another, to procure ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to his Friends; as alſo to pardon that part of the Compoſitions, wherein ſome ſorts of Graces are Taxed; he and his Under-Datary, have daily Audience of the Pope, by carrying the Supplications to be ſigned: The latter or the Under Datary, is to conſider all diſpatches which paſs through the Datary; the Vacancie of the Benefices that happen by Death excepted; and his place is worth a thou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſand Crowns a year, as the forme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is worth two thouſand; theſe two<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> have many Officers under them, to manage Affairs all very advantage<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ous.</p>
               <p>Beſides what have been mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; there are Venial Offices whoſe Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſors exerciſe no Juriſdiction, ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> are of a conſiderable value; as th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Writers of the Penitentiaries, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Apoſtolical-Writers, Apoſtolical Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berlains,
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:46268:83"/>Apoſtolical Squires, and Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries, Writers of Breives, Knights of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> and thoſe of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> Knights of the Flowr'd-de-lys, Pious Knights, Lauretan-Knights, the Rolls, the Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent.</p>
               <p>Other Offices there are of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace, whoſe value is not inconſiderable, as the firſt Chain, the ſecond Chain, the Iron-Gate, the Keeper of the Pictures, the Vergers, the Mace-Bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers; which Offices are for Life, and when Vacant diſpoſed of by the Pope, though the Praemium of ſome of them, appertain to the Cardinal Vice-Chance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="154" facs="tcp:46268:84"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. X.</hi> An Account of the Summiſt, Participant No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries, Conſiſtorial Advocates, Praefects of Proviſion, General-Viſitor of Priſons, Judge of Confidence, Auditor of Contradictions, Apoſtolical Subdeacon, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> their Office and Dignity.</head>
               <p>THE Office of Summiſt is of a great value, and is generally poſſeſſed by a Cardinal, who has in his Gift, one of each of the Offices before mentioned.</p>
               <p>The Participant Protonotaries, is a Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of twelve Prelates, inſtituted by Pope <hi>Clement</hi> their Firſt, and the principal Buſineſs is to Write the Lives of the Saints, the place of each being valued at 7000. Crowns: They go attired in Purple, and preceed all the Prelates that are not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated, they make requeſt for the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonization of Saints; and when the Pope intends any great Action, he cauſes one of them, to rebueſt of him the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance, and have reſpectively power to Create Doctors, and Notaries; but it ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends not without the Walls of <hi>Rome;</hi> and
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:46268:84"/>commonly theſe Protonotaries are Refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendaries of either Signature.</p>
               <p>The Conſiſtorial Advocates are Twelve, being made by the Pope, and are Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to make publick Orations, in publick Conſiſtories, and to be Advocates: The Orator who ſpeaks, having for his Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion 12. Ducats out of the Chamber, and enters into the Secret Conſiſtories, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire the Palis for the New Arch-biſhop, and he that does it is paid Twelve Ducats of the Chamber, by him for whom he moved; and have power, within the Walls of <hi>Rome,</hi> to create Doctors of the one and the other Law; with many other privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges: The Habit they wear upon pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Occaſions, is a Purple Robe, of Wooll with Red Silk Lining, a Hood of the like Purple Wool about their necks, lined with Ermins; but uſually they paſs up and down, with a black Caſſock, and Cloak, reaching to the Ground; their Arms coming out; and if any one of theſe be a Referendary Prelate, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> he may be a Conſiſtorial Advocate.</p>
               <p>The Praefect for the Proviſion of Corn, is given by the Pope to a Prelate moſt commonly, and he continues that Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, <hi>durante Placitum,</hi> which extends over the whole Patrimony of St. <hi>Peter,</hi>
                  <pb n="156" facs="tcp:46268:85"/>even to the confines of the State of <hi>Siena</hi> through <hi>Tuſcany,</hi> as far as <hi>Marni,</hi> through <hi>Latio; Savina Campagna,</hi> and <hi>Maritina,</hi> to the Borders of the Kingdom of <hi>Naples;</hi> and under him are ten Offices, that offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciate in Buying up Corn, and taking an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of what comes into the City; and has a Tribunal, a Notary, a Provoſt-Marſhal, and his Men, and is Judge in all Matters concerning the Office of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion of Corn, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Praefect of Fleſh, and White-meats, is commonly one of the Clarks of the chamber, drawn by Lot, who has the prices ſtated, and continues in that Office the ſpace of a Year; ſtrictly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving, that the prices appointed be not exceeded by Exaction, and that no unwholſom Proviſion is vended; and in ſcarcity, can alter and moderate the prices, <hi>&amp;c</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The General Viſitor of the Priſons, is a Clark of the Chamber, who has the Title of Praefect of the Priſons; and is to take care that the Priſoners be not oppreſſed, nor ſtarved; and in his Viſitation, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve their neceſſities; and there is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe a courſe frequently taken for their delivery, for the Pope being once made acquainted that any poor perſon is in Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:46268:85"/>for debt, and not of Ability to pay it, will not ſuffer him long to lye there, and the Viſitation is made every <hi>Thurſday,</hi> till they all are viſited; and then they begin again, upon <hi>Eaſter</hi> and <hi>Chriſtmas</hi>-Eve: The Viſitation is called Gracious, becauſe at that time many are delivered, and ſmall Offences pardoned.</p>
               <p>The Judge of Confidence, is attired in Purple in the Habit of a Prelate, wearing a Rocket, and has a place in the Pope's Chappel, under the participant Protonota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries; his Office is to enquire whether there be any Simonical Practices, or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence in the reſignation of Benefices, or Permutation in Caſes Beneficial.</p>
               <p>The Corrector of Contradictions, wears the Purple Habit of a Prelate; as alſo a Rocket, and has a place aſſigned him in the Chappel; his Buſineſs being to Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect the Bulls, that paſs through the hands of the Auditor.</p>
               <p>The Auditor of the Contradictions, in the Pope's Palace wears a Rocket, and the Purple Habit of a Prelate; his Office is to ſet his hand to the Bulls; wherein is found the Clauſe <hi>vocat is,</hi> that is in the Bulls <hi>ſi in Evidentiam.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="158" facs="tcp:46268:86"/>
               <p>The Apoſtolical Sub-deacons, otherwiſe called Participants, are five, one of them ever carrying the papal Croſs before the Pope, when he goes abroad on Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>back, or on Foot; and two of them aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt the Deacons-Cardinals, to attire the Pope in his Pontifical Veſtments; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Croſs and the Pope, none but the Cardinals, and ſuch as ſit on the Seat, are to go: The two Maſter Door-Kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers attending it, with their Silver Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges on either ſide, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe are the Offices, and great pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> as well in Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral as Eccleſiaſtical Matters; and if there be any other then have been men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, they are not of any moment; ſo that paſſing them over as Inſignificant, we now proceed to ſpeak ſomething of the Management of Religious Matters, Cuſtomes, and Ceremonies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <pb n="159" facs="tcp:46268:86"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XI.</hi> An Account of divers Offices done by the Pope, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating to the <hi>Agnus Dei,</hi> Golden Roſe, Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, Waſhing poor Mens Feet, and Creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Cardinals, Canonization of Saints, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE Pope, or High-Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> by antient Cuſtom and Appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, was wont Solemnly to bleſs the people, three times in the year, <hi>viz.</hi> On <hi>Maunday Thurſday, Eaſter day,</hi> and <hi>Aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion-day;</hi> the places of performance be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Church Porches of St. <hi>John de La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teran;</hi> that of St. <hi>Peter</hi> in the Vatican; of St. <hi>Peter</hi> in <hi>Vincola,</hi> and of St. <hi>Mark;</hi> and ſince the firſt Inſtitution, Pope <hi>Ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ban</hi> the Eighth, added the Porch of the Squirinal palace; where he gave his firſt Benediction, <hi>Anno,</hi> 1639. and every Pope in the firſt year of his Papacy, is wont to celebrate the Benediction of the <hi>Agnus Dei,</hi> and every Seventh year re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new it: The <hi>Agnus Dei,</hi> being the ſhape or Figure of a Lamb, in Virgins Wax; which is conſecrated and ſent to Princes, and Potentates, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And much in the
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:46268:87"/>ſame manner the Pope uſes a Roſe of Gold, on the fourth Sunday in Lent; which is ſent as a great Preſent, and the Bearer of this, as the former, receives great rewards.</p>
               <p>In the popes Waſhing poor mens Feet, this Order is obſerved, <hi>viz.</hi> Upon <hi>Maunday Thurſday,</hi> after the ſolemn Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, the pope accompanied by the Cardinals, and carryed in his Chair by the Palfrey-men, into the Ducal Hall; he there puts off his Papal Ornaments, when aſſiſted by the Cardinal-Deacon, he puts on a purple Stole, a Red Pluni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate, and a plain Myter; and ſits down in the pontifical Chair, ſeated on purpoſe for him; then putting Incenſe in a Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer, he Bleſſes the Cardinal Deacon, who reads the Goſpel, and then kiſſes the Text, which is held to him by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolical Subdeacon; and ſo being cenſed by the ſaid Cardinal-Deacon, the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>them of <hi>Mandatum novum</hi> is ſung, at the begining of which, he lays aſide his Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niate, and with an Apron before him, Waſhes the Feet of Twelve poor men. Unto each of them, cauſing to be given by his Treaſurer-General, certain Medals of Gold and Silver, and by the maſter of the Houſhold the Towel, wherewith
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:46268:87"/>their Feet was wiped, which ended, he returns to his Seat, where he puts off his Apron, waſhes and dries his Hands; the Baſon being uſually held to him by a No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble-Man, or Prince, and his Hands being wiped by the chief Prieſt-Cardinal, his Red Pluniate is again put on; when lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aſide his Mytre, he ſays a <hi>Pater Noſter,</hi> together with the Verſes and Prayers: Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that, taking his Seat, he puts on his Mytre, and ſo goes on foot to his Dreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Chamber, and putting on his Ponti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fical Veſtments, returns to his Palace.</p>
               <p>The Pope in making Cardinals has di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers ways, to the ſame effect; eſpecially two, <hi>viz.</hi> When he has a mind to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote any Perſon, reſident in <hi>Rome,</hi> to the Dignity of a Cardinal, he ſends word to the Cardinal-Nephew at the uſual hour; and when the Secret Conſiſtory is ſhut, he Pronounces whom he intends to Create, cauſing the party to be called in, upon whoſe Head, kneeling at his Feet, he puts on the Red Hat; and on it makes the ſign of the Croſs; ſaying, <hi>Eſto Cardina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and wear this Red Hat in Token, that without Fear, thou wilt expoſe thy ſelf even unto Death; and the Effuſion of thy Blood, for the Exaltation of the Holy Faith, for the Peace and Tranquility of the Chriſtian People,
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:46268:88"/>and Augmentation of the Eſtate of the Holy</hi> Roman-<hi>Church; In the Name of the Father,</hi> &amp;c. Then the New-Cardinal, taking his Hat off, kiſſes the Pope's Feet, and ſo riſes up.</p>
               <p>The other way is after this Manner: the Pope having Pronounced the Party in the Secret-Conſiſtory, and certified the Cardinal-Nephew with his Intentions, he ſends his Maſter of the Chamber, with his own Coach to fetch him to his Lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, where he has his Crown Shaved; for which as a Fee, he gives the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal-Nephew's Barber 25. Ducats; and having Dined, he is conducted by the Cardinal-Nephew to the Pope, kneeling before whoſe Feet, he has the Red Hat put on his Head by him; and being Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced as the former, after returning many Grateful Acknowledgements, he departs, and proceeds to viſit the Pope's Kindred; but neither appear out of their Houſes in the Red Habit, until the Publick Conſiſtory. Another way of Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ating a Cardinal, is by notifying it to him in his own Country where he reſides, and ſending him a Hat, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Which is carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by one of the Pope's Chamberlains, accompanied with his Breive.</p>
               <pb n="163" facs="tcp:46268:88"/>
               <p>In Canonization of any Perſon, at the requeſt or intreaty of a Prince, People, or Relations; he ſends to ſome Prelate, who is reſident in the Country, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire into the Life and Converſation of the party, and to ſignifie what they can learn by Letter, grounded upon the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination of Witneſſes; which is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded to the Sacred Colledge, or Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Cardinals; who if they find ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient cauſe, for further inquiry, and the which, if they adjudge meet; then the ſame or ſome other Prelate, has further Orders to examine Witneſſes, and exactly inquire into the Matter; and for the better Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination, Articles, and Interrogatories, are ſent under the Pope's Bull, or Bull Apoſtolical, to the Prelate or Prelates; wherewith they are to examin Witneſſes upon Oath, concerning the Excellency, Purity of Faith, and Sanctimony of the party deceaſed, of which if the Colledge approve, as ſufficient ground to believe the party is in Bliſs, and that by his good ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, many are incouraged to lead a Holy Life; he is Canonized according to the Rules, or Ceremony of Canonizati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; if not the Suit is rejected.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <pb n="164" facs="tcp:46268:89"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XII.</hi> The Manner of the Pope's entring the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, and Secret-Conſiſtories; and the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that is obſerved there on frequent Occaſions, and a Deſcription of thoſe Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IN the Publick-Conſiſtory, or Place for the Reception of kings, and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces Ambaſſadors in the moſt Splendid manner, at the upper end is a Pontifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Throne, erected almoſt four ſquare, and four-foot broad; in the midſt of it, is a Seat faſtened to the Wall, with a great and leſſer Foot ſtool, all the Floor of the Throne being covered with Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let-Cloth, as is the great Foot ſtool: The Wall is ſpread with Cloth of Gold, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the Seat, over which hangeth a Cloth of State of the ſame; on the Right-hand within the Throne, are the Seats of the Biſhops, and Prieſts-Cardinals, two hands breath from the Wall, with a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniency to lean on, as high as their Shoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and a ſtep to ſet their Feet on; unto which is adjoining another Seat, ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:46268:89"/>croſs the Hall, facing the Pope's Seat; on the Pope's leſt Hand is the Seat of the Deacon Cardinals, between which, and the Seat that goes croſs the Hall, is about Eleven hands breadth, which ſerves for a Door of Entrance. Theſe Seats are hung and adorned with Cloth of Arras and Tapeſtry, and are of an equal breadth; all the Room beſides, being hung with Green Cloth.</p>
               <p>To the Publick-Conſiſtory, the Pope proceeds in Rich Ornaments, with the Croſs, the Cardinals going before him; and theſe takes his Place, as do the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals, after they have done their Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence; as for the Arch biſhops, Biſhops, Protonotaries, and all the prelares, they place themſelves upon the three ſteps of the Pontifical Throne; and laſt of all the Subdeacons, Auditors, Clarks of the Chamber. As for the long robed Courti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, they ſit on the Ground, between the Cardinals Seats. The Chamberlains and Secretaries, doing the like betweem the Preiates Seats, and the long robedl Courtiers; and if it happen that thee Pope's Nephews, or ſome great Frinces, are there, which are not to ſit on the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals Seats; they take their Places, ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding near the Pope; the Ambaſſadors of
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:46268:90"/>Kings, Princes, and great Men ſtand on his right hand, between the ſreps of the Throne, and the Wall, whilſt his Dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticks, and Courtiers, ſtard on his left. The Conſiſtorial-Advocates ſtand behind the Prieſts and Deacon Cardinal's Seats; as for the procurators of Kings, Princes, and thoſe of the Religious Orders, their Place is to ſtand behind the Biſhops-Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals Seats. In the ſpace between the Prieſt, and Deacon-Cardinals Seats ſtand the Serjeants at Arms; and through them thoſe that are to come to the Pope enter, and before them ſtands the Maſter of the Houſhold; and in the head of the Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con-Cardinals Seats, are the Maſters of the Ceremonies, and in this Order Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of great moment are heard, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bated; and the Cauſe of the Aſſembly being ended, they return in the manner they came, every one knowing his Place and Order.</p>
               <p>The Secret Conſiſtory is held in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient Room in the Apoſtolical Palace, called the Papal Chamber, in the midſt of which is a Throne, raiſed from the Ground without ſteps, only little foot-ſteps to remove at pleaſure, not having any degrees as the former: The Cardinals Seats in their order are placed on the right and
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:46268:90"/>left hand, in the Front of the Throne, which is adorned with Cloth of Gold, but their Seats are only painted Red with the Pope's Arms on them; but between the Throne and the Cardinal's Seats, Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſtry is uſually ſpread. When any Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtorial Buſineſs begins, all the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates, except the Cardinals, with draw into another Chamber, and without the Door, wait two Secret Chamber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lains; who upon the leaſt Ring of the Silver Fell, carried by the <hi>Junior</hi> Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal-Deacon, enter to know the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the Conſiſtory. In this place it is, that the Pope propounds ſuch matters as are to be handled in the <hi>Senate,</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires their Opinions, which he takes by Vote, and declares according to the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jority, which is called a Decree.</p>
               <p>The Conclave, is the Place where the Cardinals affemble in the vacancy, to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect a new Pope; and is ſeated in the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolical Palace, containing two Halls, and a Chappel, with ſome other Houſes, for the conveniency of Servants; the place of Election is very unlightſom, as having but a few Lights, and thoſe very high, ſo that in the out-ſide they can hardly be ſeen; the Gate, or Entrance into the firſt Hall, has a Wicket, through which
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:46268:91"/>the Cardinals that are ſhut up receive Neceſſaries; Neceſſary-Houſes there are, and other things Neceſſity requires. In the leſſer Chappel, the Fathers convene to Celebrate Divine Service, and to make the Election. In the greater Chappel, or Hall, are as many Cells, as there are Cardinals qualified to give their Voi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and are divided with Linnen-Cloth very Artificially, and an Alphabet ſixt on them; ſo that at the firſt Entrance, they are choſen by Lot, and afterwards ſtrictly Poſſeſſed; and as ſoon as the Cells are ſo choſen, the Servants of the Cardinals make Proviſion of Beds, Curtains, and other neceſſary Furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; and when the Conclave is cloſed, Order is taken, that no Perſon may go, ſtand, or tarry, above, below, or on any ſide, or part of it; nor may ſee, ſpeak to, or caſt in any Paper, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to thoſe that are ſhut up, leſt by ſuch means, any might be capable of diving into their counſels; and for the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention of this, or any Diſturbance that may happen, there are four ſeveral Guards, a diſtance from each Other, ſet upon the place Day and Night, till the Cardinals come to a Concluſion, and are under the Command of Prelates,
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:46268:91"/>and Captains of great. Truſt; and the firſt Hall is made faſt with four Locks, two on the out ſide, and two on the in ſide; thoſe that guard next the Door, keeping the outward Keys, and thoſe within them of the inward Locks; ſo that none can get in nor out, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a mutual Agreement. But pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding from this, and waving other Elections, and Funerals of ſmaller note, We now go on to thoſe of the Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifical Prelate, or the Pope himſelf, as we find them in a Brief Abſtract; and of the Election of Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the Tenth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <pb n="170" facs="tcp:46268:92"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XIII.</hi> An Account of the Manner of Proceeding to the Election, Creation, and Corona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Pope, or High Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> with the many and ſplendid Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, Proceſſions, and what elſe is Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable.</head>
               <p>UPon the Death of Pope <hi>Urban</hi> the Eighth, the See of <hi>Rome</hi> being Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant, care was immediately taken for the Election of a High Biſhop, to ſupply his place; ſo that the Cardinals having put an end to the ninth days Solemnity, and celebrated his Interrment with much pomp and Grandeur; the uſual Maſs was ſung before them at St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Church, by Cardinal <hi>Latini,</hi> Dean of the Colledge, and an Eloquent Oration, made by <hi>Jaco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo Accareſſio;</hi> after which, the Maſter of the Ceremonies taking up the Papal Croſs, marched on with the Gentlemen of the Chappel, ſinging the Hymn <hi>Veni Creator Spiritus,</hi> &amp;c. And the Cardinals in their Degree and Order followed him to the number of fifty four, who were then at
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:46268:92"/>
                  <hi>Rome,</hi> and entring the Conclave went directly to Pope <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>xtus</hi> the Fourth's Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, where the Cardinal Dean repeated Prayers, and after that each Cardinal took his proper place; all perſons elſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſhut out of the Chappel, except the Secretary of the Colledge, and five Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Ceremonies: Then were the Bulls for the Election of a New Pope, read and allowed by the Secretary, and the Maſters of the Ceremonies; then the Cardinals took an Oath, to obſerve them, and retired into their Cells; and having finiſhed their eating, they went to the Chappel, where the Prince <hi>Savelli,</hi> Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual Marſhal of the Holy-Church, and others were appointed to keep the Guards on the Doors and Avenues, during the time of the Election; and to that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe took their Oaths before the Cardinal-Dean.</p>
               <p>The proceedings having been thus far, the Cardinals returned to their Cells, and gave Audience to the Lords Ambaſſadors, and Titular Perſonages of the Court, till about three hours within night; at which time, upon one of the Maſters of the Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies Ringing a Bell, they fell to Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muring and doing all that was neceſſary for the Cloſure of the Conclave: the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:46268:93"/>Dean, and Cardinal-Chamberlain, having the Charge to ſee all places ſecure, which in Writing was certified by the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the Ceremonies; at which time all but the Cardinals, and ſuch as were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed to attend them, withdrew: The Principal of their Attendants, being the Lord Veſtry-Keeper, and his Adjutant; Five Maſters of the Ceremonies; the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretary with an Adjutant; the Confeſſor, two Phyſicians a Chirurgeon, and an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecary with two Adjutants, two Work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, <hi>viz.</hi> A Maſon, and a Carpenter, and ſixteen Labourers, and were Elect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Secret Votes incluſive; which were held in St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Veſtry, every morning before they entered the Conclave; and over and above Orders given for the good Government of the City, during the Recluſeneſs of the Cardinals, prime Magiſtrates. And now the Guard being ſet at the four Gates, under the command of the Marſhal-Captain of the <hi>Switzers,</hi> and divers Prelates; the Conclave was walled up, and every little Craney, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the great and leſſer Windows cloſed, leaving on the top only an over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn of four of five hands in breadth, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered with a Linnen Cloth, of which part was faſtened and part not; yet there
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:46268:93"/>were ſeven paſſages, by which proviſion was brought; and in this order came it in: Firſt came two of that Cardinals Palfrey-men, for whom the Diet was deſigned, with two purple coloured Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and on them that Cardinals Arms; next him the Silver Mace-bearer and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Gentlemen; after whom came the Sewer with a Napkin, followed by two Palfrey-men, carrying Cups, and a Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Chaſing-diſh, ſucceeded by two others, with Manchets, and they by two more, with Glaſs Bottles of Wine and Water; and all theſe had a purple wooden-Mace borne before them; whilſt the Deputy Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates had the charge to ſee what entered, the which were changed at every ſeveral Meal, aſſiſting at each paſſage, and nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly ſearching every thing that was car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried in: The diet being entered, an Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paritor in his purple Robe, with his Silver Mace, cloſed the paſſage; where upon the aſſiſting Prelates took a view, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they were well ſecured, and with a paper Sealed up the key hole of the door within, and the Maſter of the Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies did the like without.</p>
               <p>In the morning ſucceeding the ſhutting up, the Cardinal Deacon celebrated Maſs, and adminiſtred the Communion to the
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:46268:94"/>reſt of the Cardinals: making a brief Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation, for the Election of a new Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop; ſo that after may debates for the ſpeace of thirty ſeven days (for ſo long they continued there nominating and Scruti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizing) on <hi>Thurſday September,</hi> 15. 1644. Cardinal <hi>Pamphilio,</hi> was agreed upon; he upon the Scrutiny, having fifteen Votes and upon the Acceſs thirty three: After-wards the Chappel being open, the Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry Keeper, with the Maſters of the Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies and Secretary, entered it, and burnt the Schedules: Then the firſt Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal Deacon, and firſt Prieſt-Cardinal, and in the Room of the Prince Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal <hi>D' Medici</hi> who was abſent, by reaſon of his Indiſpoſition; the ſecond Deacon-Cardinal made Humble Suit to the moſt eminent Cardinal <hi>Pamphilio,</hi> that he would accept of the Papacy, according to the Election, that had been made by the Sacred Colledge; which he accepted, and aſſumed the Name of <hi>Innocent</hi> the Tenth: Whereupon the two Deacon-Cardinals conducted him to the back ſide of the Altar of the Chappel; and there by the aſſiſtance of the Lord Veſtry kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and Maſter of the Ceremonies; he was deveſted of his Cardinals Habit, and attired in the Papal Veſtments: Then
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:46268:94"/>they placed him in the Pontifical Chair before they Altar; when as the Cardinal-Deacon, kneeled and kiſſed his Feet, and his right Hand; who raiſed him up, and gave the <hi>Oſculum pacis,</hi> or Kiſs of peace on either Cheek, and this upon the like reverence, he obſerved to all the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals in their Order: Then the two Principal Maſter of the Ceremonies took up the Croſs, whilſt Muſick of the Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel Ecchoed, <hi>Ecce Sacerdos Magnus,</hi> &amp;c. and ſo going out in Order, to the Lodging of Benediction, where ſo much of the Wall of that place being broken down, as would give them convenient paſſage with the Croſs; the Cardinal ſhewed it to the people, who ſtood with eager ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation, to know the event; ſignifying thereby there was an Election made, and with a loud voice, declaring as much in <hi>Latin,</hi> which in <hi>Engliſh</hi> was thus: <hi>I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce you great joy, we have a moſt Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, and moſt Reverend High Biſhop, the Lord</hi> John Baptiſt Pamphilio; <hi>who has taken to himſelf the Name of</hi> Innocent <hi>the Tenth.</hi> Upon this great Acclamations of joy enſued; every one haſtening to give notice to their Friends, and ſpread it through the City; which was more effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually done by the Ordnance, that
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:46268:95"/>breathed the news in Flame, from the Caſtle of St. <hi>Angelo;</hi> as alſo by the Bells, Drums, Trumpets, and volleys of ſmall ſhot from the Guards; and all that day, and night, was ſpent in Rejoycing. Whilſt the new Pope &amp; Cardinals refreſhed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with a Collation; the Maſons un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>walled and uncloſed the Conclave: when the repaſt being ended, the Cardinals a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain entered the Chappel to make their ſecond Acknowledgement; and the Pope being feated in his Chair, the Cardinal-Deacon began as before, and the reſt did the like in their Order; which ended divers Anthems were Sung to the Muſick of the Chappel, and the Pope with the Croſs before him, was carried to St. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi>'s Chappel in a pontifical Chair, and pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced on the high Altar, where whilſt he ſat he was a third time Reverenced as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, whilſt <hi>Te Deum, &amp;c.</hi> was Sung with Muſick; after which the Deacon-Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal read <hi>in cornu Epiſtolae</hi> divers verſes and prayers, relating to the Pope, who deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cending from the Altar, where he had all that while fat, turned himſelf to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and gave them his Benediction, and going out of the Chappel, after he had faluted the Cardinals, he entered a cloſe pontifical Chair, and was carried to his
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:46268:95"/>Lodging, with a ſplendid retinue; at night the Cannon was again diſcharged, and the Streets ſhined with Torches and Fires; and thus finiſhed the Ceremonies of Creation, when as great preparations were made for his Coronation, the Ceremony of which take as followeth.</p>
               <p>The Elected Pope, a <hi>Roman</hi> by Birth, having ſung the ſolemn Maſs, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed other Ceremonies, precedent to his Coronation, he paſſed on <hi>Tueſday</hi> the Fourth of <hi>October,</hi> 1644. about ſeven in the Morning, from his own Lodgings, to Pope <hi>Sixtus Quartus</hi>'s Chappel, ſupported on either ſide by the Maſter of the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and the Cup-bearer, habited in red Cloaks, with red Hoods lined with Taf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feta, or Sarſenet of the ſame colour; and in the ſame Attire went all the other ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Chamberlains of Honour and Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lains, precedent to whom, in long red Robes, went the Chamberlains, <hi>extra mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ros,</hi> though without Hoods, as alſo the Pope's Eſquires: Before the Pope, went the Emperors Embaſſador, General of the Holy Church, the Embaſſador of <hi>Bologna,</hi> and the Governor of <hi>Rome;</hi> on either hand were the great Officers of his Horſe, and Foot Guard; then followed the Cardinals in their Habits: And in this
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:46268:96"/>manner, the Pope arriving at <hi>Sixtus</hi> his Chappel, enter'd with the Maſter of the Chamber, Cup-bearer, Ambaſſador, and Governor of <hi>Rome,</hi> going into a Retire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the Veſtry, where a long Table ſtood cover'd with a purple Cloath, inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woven with Gold, upon which, by the Wardrobe-keeper, was laid a large plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Garment of Taffeta; which by the Aſſiſtance of the Maſter of the Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies the Pope put on, and girded about him, and put a red Sattin Night cap on his Head; and ſo with his Attendance he paſſed into the Chappel, at whoſe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, the Cardinals ſtood up and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered themſelves, making their Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, whilſt he returned them a kind Salutation: Such as attended the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals, being the mean while on their Knees. Then the Pope Leaning on the Altar, the two Deacon-Cardinals took from him his Cap, and put on a white Taffeta one, whilſt the Cardinals circled him round, and by the prime Maſter of the Ceremonies, were bidden to put on their Hats. Then from the Apoſtolical Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deacons, the Deacon-Cardinals received an <hi>Amite,</hi> an <hi>Albe,</hi> a Surplice, Girdle, Stole, a Red Rocket Imbroidered and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe adorned with Gold, and with
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:46268:96"/>theſe they attired the Pope; after which the Chief Deacon putting on his Head a rich Mitre, the <hi>Maeſtra</hi> of the Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies cryed <hi>Extra,</hi> at which word the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolical Subdeacon took up the Croſs, uſually carryed before the Pope; at the paſſing of which the Cardinals put off their Hats, before this Croſs went the Pope's Squires, after whom followed the Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers Richly Habited, then the Chamber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lains, <hi>Extra mures,</hi> with other Courtiers, and after them the Conſiſtorial Advocates, the Popes Secret Chamberlains of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, the Referendary Prelates of the Chancery, the Biſhops, Arch-Biſhops and Patriarks, and ſeven of the Pope's Chaplains, each in his Hand carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a rich Mitre; then came the Croſs the Deacons, Prieſts and Biſhops Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals, having at parting from the Pope, who all this while leaned againſt the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, made a reverend Bow; theſe march<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed two and two, their Servants going be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them; next after them paſſed on the three Conſervators of <hi>Rome,</hi> and the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or of the <hi>Caporioni,</hi> in Gowns of black Vel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vet; then the Ambaſſadors, Princes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and next the Pope, placed in his Pontifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>al Chair, over which was a Cloth of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tate, ſupported by the two Deacon Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals,
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:46268:97"/>and the Maſter of the Ceremonies, the Chair being carried by his Palfrey-men, who were attired in long Roſe-co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loured Garments, paſſing through a Guard of <hi>Switzers,</hi> who ſtood on either ſide with drawn Swords and Halberts, making way with their Launceſpezzadoes through the numerous Crowd; and in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner was he carried to St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Church.</p>
               <p>The Proceſſion aforeſaid arriving at the Church-porch, near to that Door called the Holy Door, was a Throne e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected, under a Cloth of State, railed round to keep off the Crowd, and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with Seats for the Cardinals. Being on his Throne, the Chapter, and Clergy of St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Church, were admitted to kiſs his Feet, which being performed, he entred the Church at the great Door, and being come before the Hoſt, he knee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led on a Carpet, and Pray'd; after which, he went to St. <hi>Gregory</hi> the Great his Chappel, otherwiſe called the <hi>Clementine;</hi> and ſeated himſelf in a Rich Chair, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a Cloth of state, with the Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors of <hi>France,</hi> and of the Emperour on the right Hand, and the Conſervators of <hi>Rome,</hi> and Prior of the <hi>Caporioni</hi> on th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> left; all the Cardinals, and other Prelat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> rendring their Obedience; the Cardina<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="181" facs="tcp:46268:97"/>by kiſſing his Hand, and the Biſhops his Knee; and from thence he gave ſolemn Benediction to the People.</p>
               <p>The Ceremony thus far advances, the Cardinals, Biſhops, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> put on their White Ornaments, whilſt the Pope read the Prayers, and Preparation for Maſs; the which when he had ended, and the Muſick reſounded, <hi>Benedicamus Domino,</hi> he waſhed his Hands, the Conſervators holding the Baſon the firſt time, and the General of the Church the ſecond, the Ambaſſador of <hi>France</hi> the third time, and the Emperor's Ambaſſador the fourth; and then he put on White-Garments, and a Rich Mitre bedeckt with Pearls, and pretious Stones: Then the Prince Cardinal of <hi>Tuſcany,</hi> ordered the manner of the proceeding, in Proceſſion; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, the Pope's Chaplains carried the My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tres in their Hands, and the Acolite bore a Cenſer, and an Incenſe Pan in his Hand before the Croſs; after the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion, paſſed the Dean of the <hi>Ruota,</hi> then the Maſter of the Chamber, Cup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearer, the Secret Chamberlains, the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonotaries, and other Prelates, in Copes, and in the ſpace between this Chappel and that of the Apoſtles, the uſual Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remony of the Blaze was performed three
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:46268:98"/>times diſtinctly, by one of the Maſters of the Ceremonies which is done by hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a bundle of Flax upon a Staff, and ſetting it on Fire, and whilſt it blazes, theſe words are expreſſed by him; <hi>viz. Pater Sancte ſic tranſit Gloria Mundi:</hi> Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly-Father, ſo paſſeth away the Glory of this World. Which is done to put him in mind of Humility and Mortality.</p>
               <p>The Pope coming near to the Altar of the Apoſtles, kneeled down on a Cuſhion, and prayed, having his Mitre taken off; then riſing up, he made his Confeſſion for Maſs: In the following Order, on his right hand ſtood Cardinal <hi>Latini</hi> the Dean, as the Aſſiſtant-Biſhop on the left, Cardinal <hi>Barbarino</hi> Deacon of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, and aſſiſting to them, behind were the Deacons Cardinals: In the mean while the Gentlemen of the Chappel, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to ſing the <hi>Introit</hi> of the Maſs; the Confeſſion ended, the Pope having again his Mitre on his head, ſate down in his Chair, wherein he was brought thither; whereupon the Cardinals <hi>Latini, Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma,</hi> and <hi>Ceneva,</hi> read each of them a prayer for the Pope, who coming out of his Chair, and his Mitre taken off; the Prince Cardinal of <hi>Tuſcany</hi> aſſiſted by the firſt Deacon, with the help of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:46268:98"/>Deacon, put upon him the Pall; ſaying, <hi>Accipe Pallium Sanctum,</hi> &amp;c. Which done, the Cardinal of the Goſpel ſtuck in the three Labels of the Pall, as many pins, each of them faſtning a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Jewel, <hi>viz.</hi> on the Breaſt and ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Shoulder; and ſo the Pope without a Mitre, went to the Altar and kiſſed it, as alſo the Book of the Holy Evangeliſts; and putting Incenſe into a Cenſer per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fumed the Altar, and then gave it to the Deacon of the Goſpel: After this the Prince-Cardinal put on the Mitre, and thrice perfumed him with incenſe; then that Cardinal and the two Deacon-Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals kiſſed his Breaſt and Left Cheek; when ſeating himſelf on his Throne all the Cardinals, and Prelates in their Veſtures, together with the Penitentiaries of St. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> in their Veſtures, did him Reverence; &amp; the Cardinals were admitted to kiſs his Feet, Hands, and Mouth, but the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops only his Feet, and Knees; the Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bots, and Penitentiaries, his Feet only; when ſtanding up, he read the <hi>Introit,</hi> and <hi>Kyrie eleiſon,</hi> and after that, the <hi>Gloria in excelſis Deo,</hi> with the Prayer of the Maſs, <hi>de Die Coronationis,</hi> being ſung, he ſat him ſelf again in his ſeat; then the Prince-Cardinal of <hi>Tuſcany,</hi> aſſiſted by the Sub-Deacons-Apoſtolical,
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:46268:99"/>the Auditors of the <hi>Ruota,</hi> the Conſiſtorial Advocates, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther prime Officers, deſcended to Ranks to St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Confeſſion place, where ſome Latin Expreſſions, and Reſponſes paſſing, the Latin Epiſtle was Read by the Apoſtolical Subdeacon, and the Greek Epiſtle, by the Greek Subdeacon; with ſome other Ceremonies, which for bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vities ſake are omitted.</p>
               <p>Maſs ended, and the Pope being in his Chair, the Cardinal-Arch-Biſhop of Saint <hi>Peter</hi>'s, and the chief Canons of the Church, preſented him with a Purſe of white Taffeta, with Gold Taſſels, Imbro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered and purled with Gold, and in it twenty <hi>Giuliis,</hi> or the coin of Pope <hi>Julius,</hi> as the reward of his ſinging Maſs, and he as freely beſtowed it on the Prince-Cardinal, who had read the Goſpel: This done, he was carried in the uſual proceſſional manner, to the Benediction-Hall, under a Canopy ſupported as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; where a Throne being placed upon a high Stage he ſat him down, and after the Verſe <hi>Corona aurea ſuper caput ejus</hi> was ſung, with other Verſicles and Anſwers: Cardinal <hi>Lenti</hi> ſaid a Latin prayer for him, and Cardinal <hi>Barberino</hi> took off the Mitre, and the Prince-Cardinal of <hi>Tuſcany,</hi> chief
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:46268:99"/>Deacon placed the Triple Crown on his Head, withtheſe words, <hi>Accipe Tiraram, Tribus Coronis ornatum, &amp; Scias te eſſe Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trem Principum, &amp; Regum Rectorem orbis, in terra Vicarium Salvatoris noſtri, Jeſu Chriſti, cujus eſt Honor &amp; Gloria, in ſecula ſeculorum, Amen.</hi> This done the Pope read the Benediction; which began <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cti Apoſtoli,</hi> and when he came to the words <hi>Benedictio Dei Patris omnipotentis,</hi> he ſtood up three times and Bleſſed the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and gave Plenary Indulgences; and once more repeating the Benediction, he went to his Lodging, after his Pontifical Ornaments were taken off, in Pope <hi>Sixtus</hi>'s Chappel; where from Cardinal <hi>Capone,</hi> in the name of the Colledge of Cardinals, he received the uſual wiſh of <hi>Ad multos Annos;</hi> then upon ſign given, the Cannon of the Caſtle let fly, as did the Guards from St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s <hi>Piazzo.</hi> And ſo in ſum, have you heard (Reader) of the Creation and Coronation of Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the Tenth, nor have any ſince him, much varied in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars, as to the Manner of Performance; from whence we ſhall proceed, to give an Account of his riding in State, to take poſſeſſion of the Church of St. <hi>John de La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teran,</hi> and of the Ceremonies performed there.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <pb n="186" facs="tcp:46268:100"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XIV.</hi> An Account of Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the Tenth, his Riding in Proceſſion, to take poſſeſſion of the <hi>Lateran</hi> Church, and the Ceremonies uſed in <hi>Rome</hi> on that Occaſion.</head>
               <p>POPE <hi>Innocent</hi> the Tenth, being raiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the higheſt Eccleſiaſtical Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, to compleat the Ceremony on the twenty third of <hi>November,</hi> 1644. he went to take Poſſeſſion of his <hi>Lateran</hi> Church; ſetting forth from his Palace about ſeven in the Morning, with a very Splendid Train; the Order being thus.</p>
               <p>After the Trumpets, and a Vant-Guard of Horſe, rode two and two; many of the Cardinal's Servants, each carrying his Lords Valiſe of Scarlet, imbroidred with Gold, and after them the Mace-bearers, with their Silver Maces, on Horſe-back, having the reſpective Cardinal's Arms, Engraven on each; then the Cardinal's Followers, with thoſe of the Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors, and Princes, with the Nobility of <hi>Rome,</hi> Richly Habited, and well Mount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed;
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:46268:100"/>after them, came divers Lanſpez za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dos, who kept off the Crowd, and after them, four of the Pope's Squires in Red; alſo two Valiſe-bearers in Red Jackets, with Crimſon Valiſes embroidered with Gold; after them, clothed with Red Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dilions, the Palfreys whereon the Pope was wont to ride, were lead by the Grooms of the Stable; and theſe are the yearly Preſents of the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> for the Kingdom of <hi>Naples,</hi> by way of Tribute; and were adorned with Foot-Cloths, and Trappings, imboſt with Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, and imbroidered with Silk, and Gold; and ſome of them led the Mules, with Trappings of Red Velvet: After theſe came the Pope's Litters, ſome Scarlet, and others Crimſon-Velvet, imbroidered, and fringed with Gold: Then rode a great many of the <hi>Roman</hi> Nobility, ſplendidly accoutred, waited on by Foot-Men in Rich Liveries, without obſerving any or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Precedency: Next theſe, came five of the Pope's Mace-Bearers, in Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple Gowns, bearing Silver Maces: After them, Fourteen Drummers, in Red Sattin Jackets, on Foot, trimmed with Gold, and Feathers in their Hats, beating a March, having on their Drums the Pope's Arms, as likewiſe thoſe of the People of
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:46268:101"/>
                  <hi>Rome:</hi> Then the Pope's Trumpets, with Crimſon-Banners, whereon his Arms were imbroidered in Silk, and Gold; after them, came the Chamberlains, <hi>extra Muros;</hi> and a conſiderable number of Secret-Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berlains, followed by the Conſiſtorial Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocates, and the four Participants, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying the Pope's four Crimſon Hats, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Maces: After theſe, followed on Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>back 40. <hi>Roman</hi> Magiſtrates, Habited in Black Senatorian-Velvet Gowns, reaching to their Feet, with Horſe Coverings, and Bonnets of the ſame: Next them, came the Abbreviators <hi>de Parco Maggiore,</hi> Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors <hi>de Ruota,</hi> and the Maſters of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace, who were followed by Fourteen <hi>Roman</hi> Marſhals, in White-Sattin, under-Garments Purple, Sattin-Jackets, and Caps of Velvet: After them, followed the Fourteen Caporioni, habited in Crimſon Velvet-Gowns, imbroidered with Gold, and Velvet-Caps, enriched with Jewels.</p>
               <p>Theſe were ſucceeded by the Senators, and Conſervators of <hi>Rome</hi> in ſplendid Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parel, and they by the Lord Governour, and the Emperor's Ambaſſador. Then the chief Maſters of the Ceremonies, and Apoſtolical Subdeacon, bearing Croſſes between the two Red Vergers, ſo called, from the Crimſon Vergers they carry;
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:46268:101"/>then Fifty Noble Youths, in Garments of White-Sattin, with Gold imbroidery, who went near the Pope's Litter, bare-head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, which was likewiſe imbroidered with Gold, and wherein the Pope was; when immediately after him, came the Maſter of the Chamber, Cup-bearer, Phyſician, Secretary, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Whilſt on each ſide ſtood the Guard of <hi>Switzers,</hi> with Halberts: And laſtly, in order followed the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal-Arch-Biſhops, Patriarks, Aſſiſtant-Biſhops, Protonotaries, Referendaries, and as the Rear, the Horſe Guards, in Red Caſſocks, and their Officers richly at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tired.</p>
               <p>In this manner, the great Proceſſion came to the Church porch of St. <hi>John de Lateran,</hi> where the Pope alights from his Litter, Cardinal <hi>Colonna,</hi> who was Arch-Biſhop of that Church, gave him the Croſs to kiſs, which he did kneeling on his Knees; after that, ſitting a while in the Porch, the Canons and Clergy kiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed his Feet; then the Cardinal-Arch-Prieſt made an Oration, and preſented him with a Silver-Baſon, and in it two Keys, one of Gold, and the other Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, ſpread with Flowers, being the Keys of the Church, and <hi>Lateran</hi> Palace; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which, he went from the Porch to
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:46268:102"/>the great Gate of the Church, where the Aſperſorio, or ſprinkling Bruſh, was put into his Hand by the Cardinal-Arch-Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, with which, having ſprinkled him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and others, he returned it again, and by that Cardinal, was three times cenſed; Then in his Chair, under a Canopy, he was carried to the Altar of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> and St. <hi>Paul,</hi> where all the Cardinals did Obei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſance to him; upon which he went to the High-Altar, and gave the Benedicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſaying theſe Words, <hi>viz. Sit Nomini Domini Benedictum;</hi> and then again a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcending his Chair, he was carried into the great Hall of the <hi>Lateran</hi> Palace, where ſeating himſelf at the upper end, he gave each Cardinal a Medal of Gold, and another of Silver; and to thoſe that had Offices, for every Office a Medal of Gold; then ſtanding on his Feet, he took handfuls of Coin out of the Aſſiſtant's Lap, which was made of a mixed Mettal; but neither Silver nor Gold; and ſaying, <hi>Gold and Silver I have none, but ſuch as I have, I give unto you,</hi> he threw it amongſt the Spectators; then went he in Proceſſion to the Lodge of Benediction, where he gave a ſolemn Benediction, and cauſed the Prince Cardinal <hi>d' Medici,</hi> to publiſh a Plenary Indulgence in Latin, and the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:46268:102"/>
                  <hi>Antonio,</hi> the like in <hi>Italian;</hi> then he gave a ſecond Benediction, and ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s, accompanied by the Train he brought. And thus much of Triumph, from whence we ſhall proceed, to a ſadder part, which is, the Concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all Wordly Pomp and Glory, and ſo put an end to this Work; which is an Account of the Proceedings at <hi>Rome,</hi> upon the Sickneſs, Death, and Funeral-Solemnities of the Pope, or High-Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <pb n="192" facs="tcp:46268:103"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XV.</hi> An Account of the Pope's Behaviour, on his Death-Bed, and of the Ceremonies of his Burial, and Solemn Obſequies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IF the Pope fall Sick, and the Phyſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans find he will Dye of that Sickneſs, they are not to hide it from him; but ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe him to be mindful of his Immortal State; yet to give him ſome Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, by promiſing not to be wanting in any thing, that may contribute to his Recovery. After which, they muſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint his Confeſſor, what they think as to the nearneſs of his end, who thereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on haſtens to him, and makes him more ſenſible of his approaching Fate, by let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting him know he is but Duſt, admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing him to confeſs himſelf to him; ſoon after, all his Domeſtick Prelates come before him, and the chief of his Family; in whoſe Preſence, and in that of the Euchariſt, he makes uſually his open Confeſſion of his Faith, which he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſteth he hath ever conſtantly held, and maintained, and therein by the
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:46268:103"/>grace of God, will Live and Dye. Then he asks forgiveneſs of them, if by Inadvertency, he has injured any of them, and beſtows ſome Spiritual Benediction, or Graces on them, yet requires them to pray for his Soul; then he requires the Veſtry-Keeper, that he may receive the <hi>Viaticum,</hi> and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Sacraments, when the Prelates ſee it needful, and if he be in perfect Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and not in extraordinary pain; he ſends for the Cardinals, and again makes his Confeſsion of Faith before them, and asketh their pardon, if by mis-government he hath offended any of them; intreat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them to pray for him, and recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends the Church to their care; and to be diligent and unanimous in the Election of one to ſucceed him; and ſometimes no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minates whom he thinks fit for that charge: He likewiſe lets them know his Debts, and Credits, with all his Treaſure; and makes his Will, recommending to them his Family, and Retinue, and ſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſes them with his Benediction, who finding the Pope paſt Recovery, with the Chamberlain, take an Inventory of all things in the Palace; as likewiſe, take an Account of what is in the Lord Veſtry-keeper's Charge; and to prevent
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:46268:104"/>Tumults, privately draw the Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Militia into the City, poſting them to the beſt Advantage, and provide for the Provinces within the Territories of the Church, by Letters and Meſſengers to the reſpective Governors: And when the Pope is about to depart, the Croſs is held to him by ſome of his Domeſtick Prelates, to put him in mind that Chriſt died for the Sins of Mankind; and the Veſtry-keeper gives him the Extream Unction, and commends his Soul to God, whilſt the Penitentiaries ſtand round him, reading the Penitential Pſalm, and other Prayers, as he is expiring.</p>
               <p>Being dead, the Lord Chamberlain waſhes his Body with the Decoction of ſweet Herbs and Wine, ſtopping all the purging Vents with Aromatical Gums and Odors; after which, the Penitentiaries put on him his ordinary Cloathing, and over them the Veſtments he was wont to celebrate Maſs in; and ſo lay him upon a Bier, covered with Cloath of Gold, on which are the Popes &amp; the Churches Arms; under his Head they put a Pillow of the the ſame, and two under his Feet, and on them two Pontifical Hats; and thus if he dies in the Night is it watched till the Morning by the Penitentiaries, ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:46268:104"/>about it; and then by them carried to the great Chappel, the Sub-Deacons carrying the Croſs before it, and the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen of the Chappel ſing <hi>Subvenite, &amp;c.</hi> Whilſt his Eſquires bear many lighted Torches, as his Family following; and being in the Chappel, the Penitentiaries ſing <hi>Veſpers</hi> and <hi>Vigils,</hi> until the approach of the other Religious Orders: After ſome time the Colledge of the Clergy, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents of Friers come, and ſinging <hi>Vigils,</hi> ſprinkle the Corps with Holy Water, and cenſe it: Then with many Torches be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him is he carried to St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Church, and there placed in the midſt of it: He remains two days, that the People may ſee him and kiſs his Hand: Then is he carried again to the Chappel in the Night time, and buried, whilſt great preparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are made to ſolemnize his Funeral. In the Church a Hearſe hung round with his Arms is erected, Illuminated with Wax-Tapers. Then the Meſſengers of the <hi>Roman</hi> Court give notice of the Day of Obſequies to all the Cardinals, Prelates, Ambaſſadors, Officers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and the Morrow following, the Cardinals repair thither in their Mourning, and take their places on Seats prepared for that purpoſe, near the high Altar, and ſo the
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:46268:105"/>reſt as they are in Office and Dignity, as well Prelates as inferiour Servants, all in Mourning, the latter placing themſelves about the Herſe: Then the Celebration of the Obſequies is entered upon, after the Funeral manner of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church. On the firſt Day two hundred Maſſes are ſaid, and Alms bountifully diſtributed to Men and Women of ſeveral Religious Orders; and a sermon in commendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of him is made; and ſo continue to officiate till the ninth day, on which an equal number of Maſſes with the firſt day are ſaid; and an exhortatory Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, to encourage them to the Election of a new Biſhop, preached; and ſo ends that Ceremony.</p>
               <p>As ſoon as the Pope is dead, the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals ſend their Diſpatches, by the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of their Colledge, to the ſeveral Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Prelates, and ſuch as are dependant on the <hi>Roman</hi> See, to ſignifie it; uſeing the Apoſtolical Stile, in calling the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Sons, and the Prelates, Brethren. Alſo the Vice Chancellor, upon the Death of the Pope, takes away the Bulls, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the Apoſtolical Letters were Seal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, from the Keepers, and raſes out the Pope's Name, rendring it unfit for Seal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and redelivers the other part in a
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:46268:105"/>Linnen Bag, taking great Care, that no Letters paſs in the Pope's Name after his Deceaſe.</p>
               <p>And thus much, Reader, have we thought fit to ſet down, the which, tho be ſo unhappy, as not to prove beneficial to the Curious, in letting them know, what before they might be ignorant of; yet, at leaſt, it cannot prejudice or offend the impartial and unbiaſſed of the Age.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:46268:106"/>
            <head>There is lately Printed for <hi>Hen. Rodes,</hi> next door to the <hi>Swan-Tavern,</hi> near <hi>Bride-Lane</hi> in <hi>Fleet-Street;</hi> the following Books.</head>
            <p>THE Comical Hiſtory of the State and Empire of the World of the Moon. As alſo a Deſcription of the World of the Sun: Written In <hi>French,</hi> by <hi>Cyrano Bergerac,</hi> newly done into <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> in 80.</p>
            <p>The Strange and Prodigious Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Cuſtoms, and Manners, of divers Nations. Containing; <hi>Firſt,</hi> the Ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Rites, and Ceremonies of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens, in the Worſhip of their ſeveral Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. <hi>Secondly,</hi> the various changes of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Religion, and the State it is now in: With a full Relation of the Appariti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that foretold the fall of <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> as alſo of the dreadful Famine, wherein a Woman roaſted, and eat her own Child; with the Circumſtances of the Final Deſtruction of that Famous City, under <hi>Titus. Thirdly,</hi> The Riſe and Growth of <hi>Mahometaniſm,</hi> giving an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count
<pb facs="tcp:46268:106"/>of the Doctrine of the <hi>Turkiſh Alco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron. viz.</hi> Their Commandments, and Strange Pilgrimage to <hi>Mecca,</hi> &amp;c. With the Life of that Grand Impoſtor, <hi>Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met;</hi> as alſo Remarks on the Life of <hi>Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derbeg,</hi> with the many Victories he gained over the <hi>Turks. Fourthly,</hi> the Schiſms, and Hereſies in the Chriſtian Church: Being an Account of thoſe Grand Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, the <hi>Adamites, Mugletonians,</hi> &amp;c. and all intermingled with Pleaſant Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Fantaſtical Rites, both of the Antients and Moderns, in the Cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bration of their Marriages, and Solemni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zation of their Funerals: Faithfully col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected from Ancient and Modern Authors, and adorned with divers Pictures, of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral remarkable Paſſages therein; by <hi>R. D.</hi> price bound one Shilling.</p>
            <p>Hiſtorical, and Political Obſervations on the Preſent State of <hi>Turky;</hi> deſcribing the Policy, Religion, Manners, and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary Diſcipline of the <hi>Turks;</hi> with an Account of all the Battels, Seiges and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther remarkable Tranſactions and Revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions which have happened, from the Begining of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Empire, to this Preſent Grand <hi>Seignor.</hi> To which is added his Life, containing all the material Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currences, that have happened during his
<pb facs="tcp:46268:107"/>Reign; together with the Preſent State of <hi>Hungary,</hi> and Hiſtory of the Wars, Price bound one Shilling.</p>
            <p>Converſations on ſeveral Subjects, writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in <hi>French</hi> by <hi>M. de Scudery,</hi> and done into <hi>Engliſh,</hi> by <hi>Ferrand Spence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>London</hi> Jilt, or the Politick Whore, wherein is ſhewed all the Artifices and Stratagems, which the Ladies of Pleaſure make uſe of, for the Intriguing and Decoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Men: Interwoven with ſeveral plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant Stories of the Miſſes ingenious Perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances, in two Parts.</p>
            <p>A New Voyage to the <hi>Eaſt-Indies;</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining an Account of ſeveral of thoſe rich Countries, more particularly of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Bantam;</hi> giving an exact Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that Monarchs Dominions; the Religion, Manners, and Cuſtoms of the Inhabitants; their Comerce, and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of the Country; and likewiſe a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Narrative of the Kingdom of <hi>Siam,</hi> of the Iſles of <hi>Japan,</hi> and <hi>Madagaſcar;</hi> and of ſeveral other parts, with ſuch new Diſcoveries, as were never yet Extant by any other Traveller; the ſecond Editi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, by Mr. <hi>Olanius;</hi> price bound one Shilling.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:46268:107"/>
            <p>The School of Recreation; or the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman's Tutor, to thoſe moſt Ingenious Exerciſes, of Hunting, Racing, Hawk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Riding, Cock-Fighting, Fowling, Fiſhing, Shooting, Bowling, Tennis, Ring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Billiards, Price Bounel 1 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr>
            </p>
            <p>Coffee-Houſe Jeſts, Refined and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged, by the Author of the <hi>Oxford</hi> Jeſts, the Fourth Edition, with large Additions, Price Bound. 1 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr>
            </p>
            <p>Wit's Cabinet, or a Companion for Young-Men and Ladies, containing the whole Art of Wooing, and making Love; with the beſt Complemental Letters, Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant Epiſtles, Amorous Addreſſes, and Anſwers, in a moſt Pleaſant and Ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſtrain, with the neweſt Songs, Sung at Court, and both Theatres.</p>
            <p>The School of <hi>Bacchus,</hi> or the whole Art of Drinking, taught by a New, and moſt Learned Method.</p>
            <p>The Interpretation of all ſorts of Dreams.</p>
            <p>The Art of Chiromancy, and Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſtry.</p>
            <p>The ſeveral ſorts of Coſmeticks, for Chearing, and Beautifying the Face, and taking away all Freckles, Morphews, Tet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and Ring-worms, and for preſerving the Complexion; together with the way
<pb facs="tcp:46268:108"/>of making all ſorts of Perfumes and Sweet-Waters.</p>
            <p>The uſe of Mettals, and precious Stones, and the way to Counterfeit them.</p>
            <p>Several of the choiceſt Secrets of Art and Nature.</p>
            <p>General Rules for Genteel Behaviour of Young-Men and Ladies, in all Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies.</p>
            <p>Several ſorts of News, from divers Parts, very Jocoſe and Pleaſant, Price bound 1 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Chriſtian</hi>'s Guide to Devotion, with Rules and Directions for a Holy Life; as alſo Meditations and Prayers, by <hi>S. Smith;</hi> the Second Edition, Price bound one Shilling.</p>
            <p>The whole Duty of a Communicant; being Rules and Directions, for the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Receiving the moſt Holy Sacrament of the Lord's Supper, by the Reverend Father in God <hi>John Gauden,</hi> late Lord Biſhop of <hi>Exeter:</hi> The Second Edition, with Additions out of that Reverend Prelate's Original Copies, Price bound one Shilling.</p>
            <p>The Hiſtory of <hi>Cera Muſtapha,</hi> the late Grand <hi>Viſier,</hi> being a Faithful Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the Riſe, and ſeveral Degrees of his Fortune; his Amours in the <hi>Serag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lio,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:46268:108"/>his Exploits, the true Cauſe of his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking the Siege of <hi>Vienna,</hi> together with the Particulars of his Death. Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally Written in <hi>French,</hi> and Faithfully Tranſlated into <hi>Engliſh</hi> by <hi>F. Philo,</hi> Price bound 1 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Seraſquier Baſſa,</hi> or an Hiſtorical Novel of the times, containing all that paſſed at the Siege of <hi>Buda,</hi> out of <hi>French,</hi> Price Bound 1 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr>
            </p>
            <trailer>The End.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
